자 이번에 게임은스트레이라는 스팀 신작 게임이고요
Now This time The game is called Stray Steam New It's a game
Now, this game is a new game on Steam called Stray.
게임 가격은 35,000원입니다 게임평가를 보니까 거의 6만 명이 평가를
game price 35,000 won game evaluation  almost 6 only  evaluation
The price of the game is 35,000 won.
했는데98%
did 98%
압도적으로 긍정적이더라구요요즘 사람들이 계속이 게임을 해달라
Overwhelmingly Positive these days people keep going play games Please
It's overwhelmingly positive. These days, people ask me to keep playing this game.
해서도대체 어떤 게임인지 한번 해보려고
What the heck What kind of Is it a game Once Try
Anyway, I'm going to try what kind of game it is.
합니다이 게임의 스토리는 가족과헤어지고 길을 잃은 한 외로운
Game Story Breaking up with family down the road lost one lonely
The story of this game is a lonely one who has been separated from his family and lost his way.
고양이의 모험이라고 하네요 어느 정도퍼즐 요소가 있다고 하니까
Cat's It's an adventure says which degree puzzle elements say say say
It's called the cat's adventure, because it has some puzzle elements.
답답하더라도양해 부탁드리겠습니다 그럼 바로 한번
Sorry for frustrating please then immediately once
Even if it's frustrating, I ask for your understanding. Then once again
해보도록 할게요
I'll try I'll try
I'll try
비가 많이 오는구먼
Rain A lot It's coming
It's raining a lot
이 게임의 주인공이 이제 고양이다보는 맛이 있다고 하는데
this @@W1 of the game] the main character is now @@W4 watching the cat] [ W5@@ tastes like says says
It is said that the main character of this game now has a taste for being a cat.
한번 얼마나 귀여운지 봐볼까
Once How much How cute Let's see
Let's see how cute you are
여기 애기 고양이들 있네요
here baby cats there
There are kittens here
내가 누구지어 뭔가 제일 끝에 있어 보스 느낌
I who are you something best end Got Boss Feeling
Who am I? I'm at the end of something, I feel like a boss
오매한 것들
erroneous things
goofy things
지금 이제 패드로 하고 있습니다 패드제가 패드가 익숙치가 않아서
now now pad and are The pad is The pad is I'm not familiar with I'm not
Now I'm using pads because I'm not used to pads.
아 막 꼬리 갖고 논다
Ah Act Tail Have Play
Oh, just play with your tail
친구인가 봐 친구양펀치 바로 갈겨줘야지
Are you friends Look Friend Yang Punch Baro Gotta punch
I guess they're friends, I need to punch them right away
얘랑 놀았고얘랑 놀자
with him played with him Let's play
I played with him Let's play with him
막 싸우네이 게임 개발자 분들이 전부 다
just fighting game developer people All All
Fighting, all the game developers
고양이를 키우고 있다고 하더라고
@@W0 the cat] raising said said
He said he had a cat
이 자식이 어디서 건방지게
this bastard where cheeky
Where is this child so arrogant
얼굴을 핥아주네
Face Lick
lick your face
여기서 뭐 하지여기 뒤에
here what not here followed by
what are you doing here behind here
문도 있네요 그냥 쉼터인가 봐 그치여기 살짝 연구실 느낌이 나네
Mundo there just Is it a shelter look But here a bit lab feels like is nice
There's also a door. It's just a resting place.
어디로 가야 잘 갔다고 선물이 날까나가는 건가 어 뭐야
where go well went gift It's flying is it uh what is
Where should I go, I wonder if a gift will come out just because I went well?
자자 이제 게임 끝났네요
Let's go Now Game It's over
Come on, the game is over
주인공 이름이뭘까 스트레이
Main character What's your name Stray
What is the main character's name Stray
[음악]게임 이름이 스트레이라서
[Music] Game Name Stray
[Music] The name of the game is Stray
스트레이를
Stray
건방진 나비가잠을 방해했어
Cheeky The butterfly slept Interrupted
A cheeky butterfly disturbed my sleep
비가 그쳤나 보네
Rain Has it stopped I see
Looks like the rain has stopped
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
오늘[음악]
Today [Music]
today [music]
그래픽 괜찮다 그치
Graphics It's okay That's right
graphics are ok
벽에 안쪽[음악]
on the wall [inside W1@@ [Music]
Inside the Wall [Music]
살짝 세상이 좀 아포칼립스 세상인가멸망했나 아니면 여기만 이런 건가
A little The world A little Apocalypse Did the world perish or only here like this or
Is the world slightly apocalyptic? Has it perished or is it only here?
게임 소리 괜찮아요나쁘지 않아
game sound ok not bad not
game sound ok not bad
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
이제 어디가따라가야 되나
Now Where should I follow [Can I become W2@@
Where should I go now
가자 얘들아
Let's go Guys
let's go guys
야옹 소리 내기
meow sound bet
meow
어 서로 이렇게 주고받기 가능어디가
uh each other like this exchanging where possible
Where can we exchange each other like this?
도심관대 도심왜 가는 거야
downtown generous downtown why going going
Why are you going downtown?
왜 가는 거야
why go go
why are you going
왜 가는 거야응
Why going going
why are you going
왜 가는 거냐고
Why going going
why are you going
내가 오줌 싸려고
I pee try to cum
i want to pee
아 스크래쳐 같은 느낌인가
Ah Scratcher [Similar to W2@@ feeling
Oh, does it feel like a scratcher?
이렇게 막발톱질하네
Like this You're nailing your claws
You nail it like this
[음악]이거 문어 드릴 거거든 비켜 위험해
[Music] This Octopus Drill Get it Get out of the way [ W5@@ Dangerous
[Music] I'm giving you this octopus, get out of the way, it's dangerous
이거 떨어진다
this falls
this is falling
발톱 잘 다듬었어
toenails well trimmed
well trimmed toenails
어 나도 올라갈래
Uh Me too I want to go up
oh i want to go up
아 물도 마시고
Ah Water Drink
Oh and drink water
꿀맛미네랄이 풍부하구만
Sweet minerals It's rich
Honey is rich in minerals
시간이 없어 여기도물인가
out of time no Is this a thing
I don't have time. Is it here too?
맛있어 배달해[음악]
Delicious Deliver [Music]
Delicious, deliver [Music]
꿀맛
Sweet
sweet taste
여기서 뭐 해
here what do
What are you doing here
아 또 뽀뽀 받으려고 아둘이 사귀는 건가
Ah Again Kisses To receive  Dating is it
Ah, are you two dating just to get another kiss?
연애하나
One love
one love
이렇게 뭔가 풍경 좋다 그치 나도고양이처럼 살고 싶어요
Like this Something Scenery I like it That's right Me too Like a cat live want
Something like this scenery is nice, but I want to live like a cat too
아 나 진짜 고양이로 태어나고 싶어다음 생에
ah me real as a cat born I want next life
Ah, I really want to be born as a cat in my next life
이렇게 자유로운 영혼
like this free soul
such a free spirit
난 여기로 가야지
I am here I have to go
i have to go here
길게 눌러 연속 점프하기 여기서도가능 아 여기서 안 되네
hold press continuous jump also available here Ah here not becomes
Long press to jump continuously
지금 이제게임 초반이라 좀 튜토리얼 느낌으로
Now Now game Early game Some Tutorial By feeling
It's the beginning of the game now, so it feels like a tutorial
가나 봐일단 같이 가면 안 되네
Kana Look at as go not It works
I guess we can go together.
그래 그래 나한테 와 관심 좀 줘라응
yes yes me and interest Some give me
yes yes come to me and pay attention
주인공인데
is the main character
I'm the main character
나 편한 길로 갈래
me comfortable road I want to go
I want to go the easy way
어 여기 근데괜찮았는데 풍경 진짜로
uh here but it was fine scenery really
Uh here, but it was okay, the scenery is really good
앞에 길이 아래 구멍 있네
before length below holes there
There's a hole down the road in the front
애들 오고 있어 여기선 뒤 못 보나보다
kids coming there here behind can't Bonaboda
The kids are coming, I can't look back from here
아 여기 뭔가 살짝 어려워 보인다길게 눌러서 관찰하기
Ah here something slightly difficult looks Hold Press Observe
Ah, something seems a little difficult here. Long-press to observe
어렵게 확대도 가능
Difficult Magnification Possible
Difficult to zoom in
따라가면 될 것 같은데 왜 왜 왜 왜빨리 가라고 알았어
follows becomes becomes looks like Why Why Why Why quickly Go Okay
I think I can just follow you, but why why why why why go quickly?
알았어 가면 될 거 아니야
OK go become go no
ok you can't go
어 좀 위험한데 아 이거 왠지 내차례인데 떨어질 삘인데
Uh A bit It's dangerous Ah This For some reason It's my turn will fall I'm sprained
Uh, it's a bit dangerous, ah, it's my turn for some reason, but I'm about to fall
맞지100%다 이거 무조건 떨어진다
is 100% correct this unconditionally falls
It's 100% correct, this will definitely fall
어떻게 무리해서 이탈됐어 어
How did you do it I overworked it got away uh
How did you force yourself to break away?
[음악]헐
[MUSIC] Huh
[Music] Huh
애들이 살짝 표정이어떻게 이런 표정이 아니었는데
kids slightly expression like this expression [ It wasn't W5@@ but
How did the kids have a little expression, but it wasn't like this
드디어 보냈다 이런 표정이었는데
Finally sent like this It was an expression
I finally sent it with this expression
기절했나봐
I must have fainted
must have passed out
혼자 남았어
alone left
left alone
어 좀 아픈가 봐 어 뭐 지금 다리를절고 있어
Uh Some Does it hurt Look Uh What now lame has
I guess it hurts a bit
[박수]왼쪽 뒷다리
[Applause] Left Hind leg
[Applause] Left hind leg
크
big
nice
어떻게뇌를 다쳤나
How did the brain get hurt
how did you hurt your brain
여기에 뭐가 있을까어
here what is
what's going on here
뭐가 작동한다뭐지
what works what
what works
거북이들인가 뭐야
Turtles What
what are turtles
닌자 거북이
Ninja Turtle
ninja turtles
할 수 있어
do do do
you can do it
같이 따라가자
together let's follow
let's follow together
지금소리도 잘 못 내잖아 어 좀 나은 거
Even now well can't pay me uh Little Better Something
You can't even make a sound right now, it's better
같다 맞지 어 회복했어
same right uh recovered
It's the same, right, I recovered
근데 목소리가 좀 쉬었네 너도코로나니
But Your voice is a bit I rested Are you also corona
But your voice is a bit hoarse. Are you also corona?
움직인다
moves
move
데드시티이름이 불길한데
The name of the dead city is It's ominous
Dead City's name is ominous.
죽음의 도시
@@W0 of death] city
city ​​of the dead
저것들 뭐야 근데 해골인가
Those What is it But Skeletons
What are those things, but are they skeletons?
[음악]분명 지나가는데
[MUSIC] I'm sure passing by
[Music] It's definitely passing
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어CCTV
uhCCTV
UCCTV
날 감시하고 있어
me watching got
are watching me
어떻게 하지[음악]
how do [music]
how do i do it [music]
여기 내려가야 될 것 같은데내려가는 방법을
here going down going down going down going down method
I think I have to go down here. How to get down?
저 보이지쟤네들 뭐야 정체가 뭐임
That You can see them What is identity What is
I can see them, what are they, what are they really like?
[음악]어 여기 로블이 있다 로봇
[Music] uh here Robel there robot
[Music] uh here's the roblox robot
오 로봇이네
Oh It's a robot
oh it's a robot
여기로 가야 되나 봐요 길 따라서여기 트럼펫 금지인가 소리지르면 안
Go here Go or look road So here trumpet is forbidden if you scream not
I guess I have to go here. Follow the road. Is the trumpet prohibited here?
되는 건가 조용히 해야 되나 봐
be be quietly be be look
I guess I should be quiet
어 누군가 나를 지금 부르는 느낌이야그렇지
uh someone me now calling feeling That's right
I feel like someone is calling me right now
도와달라고그런 거 아님
Asking for help that or
I'm not asking for help
도움 요청하는 거 같은데
Help Asking Something Looks like
I think you're asking for help
잠깐만여기 뭐 하면 될까
Wait here What  will be
Wait a minute, what can I do here
길이괜히 있나
I don't care
Is there any way
뭔가 있을 줄 알았는데 없나 보네
Something Could be would be I thought Is there I see
I thought there would be something, but it seems there isn't
자꾸 길 안내하는 거 같아 어 뭐야팔로우미
keep way guide go same Uh What are you following
It seems like he keeps guiding the way
여긴가 봐
Is this place Look
look here
누구인
who is
who
어 양동이 집었어
uh bucket picked up
oh i picked up the bucket
용도가 있겠죠 양동이
uses must be bucket
There must be a use Bucket
양동일 집었는데
Dongil Yang picked up
I picked up a bucket
이거 물 같은 거 좀 받아야 되려나나중에
this water like stuff get some  to be later
I think I need to get some water or something like this
여기 들어가면은매우 위험하겠죠 근데 양동이를
Here is very It must be dangerous but the bucket
It would be very dangerous to go in here, but the bucket
이용한다면 만약에
if if
If using
어 맞네양동 이용했어 양동이 떨어뜨리는
uh right bucket I used bucket dropping
Oh right, I used a bucket. Dropping a bucket
연출로 해야 되는데 난 잘하면 갈리는줄
directed by should be should be I am hopefully Split line
I have to do it as a directing, but I thought it would change if I did well
이거 뭐지
this what
what is this
그래 고양이는 이런 것도 못 참치
yes the cat is this is nothing can't Tuna
Yes, cats can't do anything like this
음 다 했어 아주 만족
Well Everything Did Very Satisfied
Well done, very satisfied
[음악]어디로 갈까 위로 갈 수 있나
[Music] Where go up go be [W5 Is there @@
[Music] Where can I go? Can I go up?
올라왔어
is up
came up
이게 마지막인 거 같은데 어 맞다아래 길 열림
This is last is looks like uh Right under road open
I think this is the end, uh right, the road below opens
뭐 하는 거야무슨 자세인지 아는 사람
what do what stance know Person
What are you doing? Someone who knows what you're doing
응가야
oops
ngaya
뭐 하는 거임
what doing that's
what are you doing
아
ah
이것도 스크래쳐 같이 뭐 하는 거구나아 나 응가하는 줄
this is scratcher like what doing Ah me poo line
What are you doing like scratching? I thought I was pooping
순간
moment
Moment
우리 집 아니잖아 그지뭐라 할 사람도 없고
we home no what the heck do People no
It's not our house, there's no one to say anything about
성공적
successful
좋아 좋아
OK OK
Good good
물이다 물
water water
water is water
이거 물 마셔주는 거 뭐 영양이 있나나중에 갈증 이런 거 있으면
this water drink stuff what Nourishing later thirsty like this that if you have
Is this drinking water? Is it nutritious? If you feel thirsty later,
마시긴 해야 되니까
don't drink should be [Because W2@@ is
Because I have to drink
누가 나를 불렀을까 어 뭐야어 나 순간 나한테 오는 줄
who called me called uh what Me moment me coming give
Who called me? What is it?
얘는 또 정체가 뭐지
this is again identity is what is
What is he again
여기도 있어
here too is there
here too
외계인 같이 생기지 않았어
Aliens Like Not Like Not
Didn't look like an alien
어 움직인다
uh moves
uh move
넌 뭐니
you what is
what are you
어치명타 갈겼나 봐 어
What a fatal blow Did you get hit Look uh
It must have been a fatal blow
뇌진탕 온 거 같은데 내가 방금 지금막타 친 거 같은데 아래턱 그냥 갈겨
concussion came thing looks like i just just hit chin that one [Same as W9@@ lower jaw Just Slap
I think I got a concussion I think I just hit it but I just hit it on the lower jaw
버렸어어떻게
How did you throw it away
how did you throw it away
KU 당했어
KU got hit
I got KU
내가 죽인 건가
I Killed Is that
did i kill
여기도 있네
here too there
here too
개 많아
a lot
a lot of dogs
쫄았어 지금
I was scared now
도망가
run away
도망가야 돼
I have to run I can
I have to run away
아아 꺼져
Ah Get lost
ah go away
어 지금 사방에 난리야 지금[음악]
uh now everywhere go crazy now [Music]
Uh, it's all over the place right now [Music]
아
ah
뭔가
Something
어젤리들 개 많아
Ajelly  a lot
There are a lot of Ajellys
[박수]
[Applause]
[clap]
어 그만해
uh stop
아 근데 얘네들 지금 삶아 먹으면 좀맛있을 것 같기도 하고
Ah But These guys Now Boil If you eat it will be delicious will be looks like and
Oh, but if you boil them now, they might be a bit tasty.
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
이런 거 나한테 간지럽지
like this that to me itchy
It tickles me like this
야옹 소리네 이거[음악]
Meow Sounds This [Music]
It's meowing. This [Music]
누구야 나를 부르는 거[음악]
who is me calling that [music]
who's calling me [music]
누가 날 불렀지
who called called me called
who called me
목을 다 쳤나 야옹 소리가 이렇게 막
strangle da hit meow sounds Like this Act
Did you hurt your neck?
시원하진 않아어디로 가야 여기다
Cool Where Go Here
It's not cool, where should I go?
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
여기는 괴물 없네요 애들이
this is monster no kids
There are no monsters here, kids.
아주 그냥 천재구만
very just genius
just a genius
천재 고향이야
Genius This is my hometown
hometown of genius
아니 누가 자꾸 이렇게 개멀리 부르네어 한번 가까운 거리도 아니고
no who keep like this far away Brunei once close distance not
No, someone keeps calling me far away like this, it’s not even close once
어디까지 날 데려가셈이야
How far me I'm taking you
how far are you going to take me
이건 어디로 가야 될까
This is Where should go should be
where should this go
이거 미는 거구만
This is is That's a big deal
I'm pushing this
안 밀어지네 어 뭐야 방금 뭔가반응했어
not pushing uh what just Something reacted
I'm not pushed, what is it, I just reacted to something
[음악]여기 넘어가라는 거 같은데
[MUSIC]Here go over that thing [Same as W3@@
[MUSIC] I think it's over here
어떻게 넘어가 이거땡길 아 설마 안에 들어가서 하는
how can go beyond this is good ah no way in in in
How can I get past this?
건가
is
is it
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어디 있니
Where Are you
where are you
여기 cctv가 많다 맞지
here cctv a lot right
There are a lot of cctv here, right?
어디 어 안돼 어위험했어
Where Uh No That was dangerous
No way, no way, it was dangerous
이런 건끄떡없지
like this I don't care
There's nothing wrong with this
여기는
This is
here is
여기는여기는
here is here
this is here
어디로 가야 되냐면건너편으로 안 넘어가지네
Where must go to the other side not it goes over
Wherever I have to go, I can't cross over to the other side
어디로 가야 되지자유도가 좀 있나 아닌가
where go not have degrees of freedom some have Isn't that
Where should I go? Isn’t there some degree of freedom?
똑똑한스마트캣
smart smart cat
길이 참
length true
length is true
고양이라서 가능한 길이지
because it's a cat possible length
It's a cat, so it's possible
여기서는
here
여기로닭은 못 가나고
Here's the chicken Can't Go
Chickens can't go here
닭은 당연히 안 되지이 사람은
chickens sure not not people
Of course chickens aren't this guy
여기도 CCTV 있어
here too CCTV is there
There is also CCTV here.
아마 내가 볼 때 지금 이제플레이어들의 그런
maybe i see when now now Players that
Maybe when I look at it now, the players are like that
감각을 좀 알려주기 위한챕터 같은
sense some tell me chapters for like
Like a chapter to let you know the senses
그렇지
right
yes
뭔가 떨어지는 소리 난다
something falling sound flying
I hear something falling
저기도 지나가야 될 것 같은데 이거뭐 필요한 건가 이거다
there too go by will be will be looks like What is this is necessary is this is this
I think I'll have to go through that too, but what do I need?
스위치 뽑기 머리나 뽑아 버렸어
Switch Pull Hair or Pull Throw away
I pulled out the switch, pulled out my hair
혹시 몰라 들고 가자
Maybe I don't know carry let's go
Just in case, let's go
아파트
Apartment
apartment
여기 사람 있으려나
here person would be
Is there anyone here
이건 못 참지
this is can't can't stand it
I can't stand this
어 나 근데 그거 어디 감들고 온 거
uh me but that where sense Holding On Going
Uh, but where did it come from?
버렸나 살아났네
Abandoned Resurrected
Abandoned or revived
[음악]어 뭐야
[Music]uh what
[Music] Uh what
도움 필요
help need
need help
자도움이 필요한
help needed
need help
그래이거는
Graiger is
[음악]얘기해 봐봐
[Music] Talk Look
[Music] Talk about it
자이거는이 정도면 되겠어
Zaiger
Jager should be good enough for this
[음악]문으로 들어가 줘 전기를 켜 줘
[Music] To Door Enter Give Electricity Turn On give me
[MUSIC] Go through the door, turn on the lights
그것 좀 힘들 것 같은데내가 맞는 거야
it's kinda tough it's looks like I'm Fit is
That sounds a little tough, but I'm right
지랄 말만 하네
fuck just say say
I'm just saying shit
문이
Moon
door
이건 뭐야
This is What is
What's this
어이거구만
Wow
oops
여기다 꼽는 건가아 이거 다 꼽으면 되나 보다
Here pick Gungaa This everything If plugged in
Is it possible to list all of these here?
그럼 아까 하나도 가져왔었는데 그어디 갔지
then earlier not one I brought it where gone
Then I brought one earlier, but where did it go?
아 여기 위에도 있네어 방금 떨어질 뻔한 거 잡았어
ah here above there just Falling obvious almost caught
Oh, it's up here too. I just caught the one that almost fell.
이제 두 개 남음 두 개여기도 있다
now two  remaining two Also here there
Now there are two left, two are here too
여기다 꽂아주고
here plug it in
plug it in here
나머지 하나는 저기 위에 있다가질려면
the rest one over there on top of to have
The other one is up there to get it
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
야 진짜 이런 고양이 있으면진짜
hey really like this cat really
Hey, if you really have a cat like this
지리겠다
I'm going to miss
I'm bored
완전 지니어스야 지니어스
Totally Genius Genius
Totally Genius, Genius
비밀의 문이 열렸네[음악]
secret door open [Music]
The secret door has opened [music]
뭐야 누가 날 불렀어
what who called me called
who called me
너는
you are
you
어 여기 캡슐 같은 거 안에 들어있는 건가
uh here capsule like stuff [in W5@@ contains is
Uh, is this in a capsule or something?
맞지
right
Right
이게 뭐지이거 이게 뭘까 뭐 집었는데
this is what is this what is this what is this what is I picked it up
what is this what is this what is this
어디다 끼우는 건가
where put is
where do you put it
마지막 하나도 저기 밖에 나가서끼우는 걸렸나 내가 근데 뭘
last not one over there outside go out Did you catch it me but what
Did the last one go outside over there and get caught?
집었는지를 모르겠네
I don't know I don't know
I don't know if I picked it up
어 여기 화살표 있어 여기구나
uh here arrows there here
Uh, there's an arrow here.
뭐야
What is
what
이게 뭐임[음악]
this is what is it [Music]
what is this [music]
설마 너냐날 부른 거 어
No way you called that uh
Could it be that you called me
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아니 뭐 코딱지만 하네 나 뭐 어떤대단한 놈이 불렀나 했는데
no what snot only yes me What What a great called called but
No, it's just snot, I wondered if some great guy called it.
어 뭐야 저기 플랑크톤쪼꼬미는
uh what is it over there Plankton little
Uh, what is that plankton bitch over there?
어떻게 문방구에서 팔 것 같은 놈이날 불렀어
how stationery arm thing like He called called
How did a guy who seemed to be selling at a stationery call me?
[음악]어 너 죽인 건가
[Music]uh you killed that
[Music] Did I kill you?
[음악]이게 뭔데
[Music] This is What is it
[Music] What is this
뭐라는 거야
what @@W0 said] said
What is he saying now
효과가 있었어 난 이제 자유야 고마워내 카메라가 이상해진 줄 알았어
worked was I was now free Thanks camera weird lines OK
It worked, I'm free now thank you I thought my camera went crazy
데드시티의 고양이가 있다니 내 이름이기억이 나지 않아 메모리가 손상된 거
Dead City's Cat  My I don't remember the name Not Not Out of memory Corrupted Thing
There's a cat in the dead city. I can't remember my name, so my memory is damaged.
같아요 오랫동안 전자 네트워크에 갇혀있었어 여기에 살고 있던 과학자를
I guess long e network stuck @W5 here live was @@W8 scientists]
I think I've been trapped in an electronic network for a long time. Scientists living here
위해 일했었지 지금은 나를b12라고 불러 줘 근데 b라고
[@@W0 for W0@@] worked now call me b12 call me [ W5@@ give me but say b
I used to work for you but now call me b12 but b
부르자 내 표면에 그렇게 적혀 있거든
let's call inside on the surface like that written There is
Let's call it 'cause it's written all over my face
데드시티는 위험한 곳이지만 너는괜찮을 것 같네 여기서 나가자 나를
Dead City is is dangerous is a place, but you will be fine will be [ It looks like W5@@ here let's go me
Dead City is a dangerous place, but I think you'll be fine. Let's get out of here.
따라와B
Follow me B
[음악]친구가 생겼어
[Music] I have a friend [I got a W1@@
[Music] I made a friend
어디 갔어야따라오라며
Where told me to follow you
Where should I go, follow me
어디 갔니
Where Did you go
where did you go
아 이거 무너져야 제맛인데어 나이스
ah this must fall apart I like it Nice
Ah, this is the best thing when it collapses, nice
그렇지
right
yes
친구야나갔니
Are you gone
Are you gone, friend?
얘야
sweetheart
Hey
어디로 갔는지 좀친구야 어디
Where went Little friend Where
Where did you go, little friend?
컴퓨터 하고 있니
computer and do you have
are you working on a computer
아 여기 있다 아 나 나간 줄알았잖아
ah here here ah me out You thought it was
Ah, here it is. Ah, you thought I left.
저 키로 문을 열 수 있어이 정도면기억하고 있지
low key statement column be Yes I remember Yes
You can open the door with that key. I remember this
내가 가져다 줄게
I will I will bring you I will give you
i'll bring it
좋았어 배터리가벌써 무척해 따라와 같이 조종할 수
I liked it The battery is already running out It's amazing Follow me like [ W5@@ can control can control
It's good. The battery is already very bad. I can steer with you.
있는 건가 봐 맞지
is is is is
See if there is, right
이걸 착용해
Wear this wear it
wear this
이게 뭔데어
This is What is this
what is this
무겁잖아요 무겁네[음악]
That's heavy That's heavy [Music]
It's heavy, it's heavy [Music]
어 뭐 개꿀 빨겠다 이거에 들어가가지고
uh what gag I'm going to suck this Enter and take
Uh, I’m going to suck honey. Go into this and take it.
아 좀 적응 못 했나 봐 맞지적응 못 했어
ah kinda adapt couldn't did look I did couldn't did
Ah, I guess I couldn’t adapt.
아장아장 기어가는 거 봐
Toddler Crawling Rough Look
Look at the toddler crawling
야 나와[음악]
Hey Me [Music]
Hey me out [music]
응무겁다고
That's heavy
yeah it's heavy
[음악]아직
[Music] yet
[MUSIC] Not yet
적응이 더 필요해
adapt more need
need more adaptation
이게 백팩은 너같이 작은 네발동물을위해 만든 거야
This is backpack like you small for tetrapods made made
This backpack is made for little tetrapods like you.
불편 안 해 불편해걱정하지 마 익숙해질 거야
Inconvenient Not Do Inconvenient don't worry Don't I'll get used to it I'm going to
It's not uncomfortable, don't worry, you'll get used to it
키를 디지털화해서 배낭에 넣었어인벤토리 열기
key digitized backpack put in inventory open
I digitized the key and put it in my backpack. Open the inventory.
키가 있네요 키 이거 조사하기는 뭐지
key is is there key this is check What is
There is a key. What is the key to examining this?
돌려서 볼 수도 있어
turn see might be got
you can turn around
[음악]그렇구만
[Music] That's right
다른 거는 뭐임 메모리는 뭐예요이건 뭐지
other what is what is memory is what is this What is
what is the other what is memory what is this
[음악]간단하지
[MUSIC] It's not that simple
[Music] It's not that simple
궁금한 물건 있으면 내게 보여줘지나가다 다른 로봇이 있다면 그
curious stuff if you have it show me show me pass other if robot is if that
If there's something you're curious about, show it to me. If there's another robot passing by
로봇에게 보여줘도 돼 아파트에서나가자
@@W0 to the robot] even if you show it you can Let's get out of the apartment
You can show it to the robot. Let's get out of the apartment.
여기 지나갈 수 있나 이제
Here Pass Can Got Now
can i get through here
오 이거 어떻게 하지
oh this how not
oh how do you do this
[박수]음
[Applause] Mmm
[Applause] Um
[음악]조명 켜기
[MUSIC]Lights ON
[MUSIC] Turn on the lights
조사 가능[음악]
Survey Available [Music]
Investigable [Music]
여기 위에 뭐 적혀 있는 거 같은데아닌가
here on what written in stuff [It looks like W6@@, isn't it
I think something is written above here, isn't it?
코드 있냐 아저기서 비밀번호 찾아야 되나 보다
Code Is there Somewhere Password Find Becomes [than W6@@
Do you have a code? I need to find the password somewhere.
맞지비밀번호가 어디 적혀 있나 봐
correct password is where is written is look at
That's right, guess where the password is written
어 3748
uh 3748
Uh 3748
74 8
와우
wow
멋진 곳이네 저쪽 엘리베이터가 있어아무래도 중요해 보여요 올라가야 할
Cool It's a place Over there There's an elevator There's no doubt important can see must go up do
It's a great place. There's an elevator over there. It looks important no matter what.
것 같아
like like
I think
아니 너 날아다니는데 너 타고 다니면안 되니
no you flying around you ride If you don't go , so
No, you can fly, but you can't ride it
분위기 괜찮다 여기도
atmosphere okay here too
The atmosphere is good here too
[음악]어 편한데
[Music] uh It's comfy
[Music] It's comfortable
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어 기억났어 아웃사이드 말이야
uh I remembered outside I mean
Oh, I remembered, outside
이전에 가본거 같은 느낌이 들어 넌여기에서 온 거니
before been there like feels like heard You are here came you are
I feel like I've been there before, are you from here?
저기가 아웃사이던데 나 누군가에게아웃사이드에 가겠다고 약속했었어
That's It's outside Me Someone outside I'm going I promised
It's outside, but I promised someone I'd go outside.
누구였을까
Who was it
who was it
이 엽서에 벽화가 그려져 있어가져가자
Postcard Mural drawn , let's take it
There's a mural painted on this postcard. Let's take it.
새로운 아이템 같은
New Item Same
like new item
난 왜 이런 기억을 가지고 있는거지이 기억은 어디에서 온 걸까
I why oops remember got It's there remember where came from I wonder
Why do I have these memories and where do these memories come from?
계속하자[음악]
Let's go [Music]
let's go [music]
엽서는 뭘까요 어 뭐야 아 이거 기억같은 거 전부 다 찾아주면은
What is the postcard What is uh What is Ah This like a memory that all all find it
What is a postcard?
뭐가 되나 본데맞지
What can be is the same
I saw what happened
우리는 하늘을 다시 볼 수 있어약속해
we sky again see be I promise you
We can see the sky again, I promise
어 잠깐만 뒷면에 한번 가볼까 뭐있는지
uh wait on the back once shall we go What's there
Uh, wait a minute, let’s go to the back, see what’s there
그냥
just
살아있는생물체는 없나 사람 같은 그런
live creatures are there any people like like that
Are there any living creatures like humans?
이건 뭐야 번역하기세이프존
this is what is Translate Safe Zone
What is this? Translate Safe Zone
안전하다는 건가
it's safe is it
is it safe
뭐냐 이거
What is This is
what is this
어여기도 괴물들 많아
Here too monsters a lot
There are too many monsters here
아잠깐만 잠깐만
Wait a minute Wait a minute
Oh wait a minute
세이프존 아니네
Safe Zone No
It's not a safe zone
저 로봇이 있다 로봇
that robot is is robot
there is that robot robot
슬럼
Slum
slum
뭔가 뒷골목 세상 같은
something back alley world like
something like a back alley world
뭐야 꺼져 어경보 누르고 튀어나는데 뭐지
[What is it? @ What is
What is it, press the alarm and it pops out, what is it
로봇들이 나를 무서워한다그냥 고향인데
robots me are afraid of me, just is my hometown
Robots are afraid of me. It's just my hometown.
이유가 있겠지 당연히
The reason is must be of course
There must be a reason, of course
왜 나를 무서워하지
why me don't be scared
why are you afraid of me
문지기인가[음악]
Gatekeeper [Music]
Are the Gatekeepers [Music]
그래 나랑 싸워보자 이거야
Yes with me let's fight this is
yes let's fight me
아닌 거 같은데
not like looks like
I don't think
[음악]어 웃고 있다
[Music] uh laughing there
[MUSIC] Uh I'm laughing
대화하기[음악]
Talking [Music]
talk [music]
뭐라는 거야이들만의 독자적인 언어가 있는 것
@@W0 what they say] their own unique @@W3 with language] [@@W4 with W4@@] thing
What do you mean, they have their own language
같아[음악]
looks like [music]
Same [Music]
넌절크가 아니구나
You're a jerk That's not it
you're not a jerk
우리는 너 같은 종을 본 적이 별로없어
we you like species seen Enemies not so much
We've never seen a species like you
아무도 먹지 않는다면 우리 마을에있어도 돼 아무도 안 먹어 뭐 내가
no one eat  we even in town ok nobody not eat what i
If no one eats, you can stay in my town, no one eats what am I
로봇 먹겠니[음악]
Robot Wanna Eat [Music]
Would you like a robot [music]
절크가 뭐지 절크[음악]
Jerk is What is Jerk [Music]
What is Jerk? [Music]
얘네들이 뭔가겁이 많은 애들인가봐
These guys I'm afraid of something a lot must be kids
I guess these guys are scared of something
아까 그벌레들이 제일 큰가 저크
Just now those bugs the best big jerk
Are those bugs the biggest jerk?
귀엽게 생겼다 표정들이 개성이 없게생겼네 애들이 얼굴이
cute looks good expressions personality doesn't look kids faces
They look cute, their expressions don't have personality, the kids' faces
다 똑같이 생겨가지고
everything the same born
they all come out the same
[음악]길을 이런 거 같네 뭐가 필요하지
[MUSIC] road oh something sounds like what [ W5@@ not needed
[Music] The road looks like this, what do you need?
아이템 보여주기는 뭐야엽서 이거 보여줄 수 있는 거고
item show what a postcard this show be be go
What is it to show items? Postcards can show this
아웃사이드 사진이라니 말도 안 돼엘리베이터는 작동하지 않아 여기를
outside photos nonsense not the elevator is [ W5@@ doesn't work doesn't work @@W7 here]
Outside photos are ridiculous. The elevator doesn't work.
떠나는게 불가능하다는 건 모두 잘알고 있어 뭐 아웃사이더는 그렇게
Leaving Impossible things Everyone Knowing there is what the outsider is like that
Everyone knows that leaving is impossible.
생각 안 하겠지만[음악]
think don't but [music]
You wouldn't think [Music]
하지면 하지면 내 녀석들도 지금 모두사라졌어 모모만 빼고 말이야
if not if not my guys now [ W5@@ are all gone Momo only [Except W7@@ I mean
If I do it, all of my guys are gone now, except for Momo.
합치면 아니에요 번에 오르간 건가만나서 얘기해 볼 수는 있겠지만 이미
combined no at the same time organ meet Talk see count but already
If you combine it, no
그는 떠나려는 걸 포기했어 그게최선인 거지
he leaving girl gave up that's the best [ W5@@ beggar
He gave up trying to leave, that's for the best
그는 주황색 네온사인이 있는 저 높은건물에 살고 있어
he orange neon sign that that In a tall building lives is
He lives in that tall building with the orange neon sign
아 저거 저거[음악]
ah that that [music]
Oh that that that [music]
아 하지면이면 아래쪽 애들 뭐 이런건가
ah if not bottom kids what Is this like this
Oh, if not, what are the kids below?
도움 요청하기[음악]
Help Request [Music]
Asking for Help [Music]
언제든 주저하지 말고 나를 불러 내가도와줄게
Anytime Don't hesitate , not call me call me I'll help you
Don't hesitate to call me anytime and I'll help you
얘가 주황색 네온사인의 큰 건물에있는 모모에게 말을 걸라고 했어 그는
this guy orange neon big @@W4 in the building] told momo said bet said he
He told me to talk to Momo in the big building with the orange neon sign.
우리가 여기서 나갈 수 있는 유일한단서야
us where get out be be It's the only clue
It's the only clue we can get out of here
그래 그래서 뭐
yes so what
하는 거야너 때문에 깜짝 놀랐네 저크인 줄
do you because surprise surprise Jerk in lines
I was surprised because of you, I thought it was a jerk
알았잖아
Okay
okay
어 자고 있는 거야자고 있는 거 같은데
er sleeping  sleeping  That's [It looks like W6@@
Hey, you're sleeping. I think you're sleeping.
너가 정말로 엘리베이터 탈 수 있을거라 생각하니 난 내일이면 374살이
you really elevator ride can be [Do you think W6@@ I am Tomorrow 374 years old
Do you really think you can ride an elevator? I'll be 374 tomorrow.
되는데도 저게 작동하는 걸 본 적이없단다
works that works that saw Never ever
I've never seen it work though
왜 올라가려고 하는 거야 거긴 아무도없어 아무것도 없어
why go up do go there No one nothing no
Why are you trying to go up? There's no one there, there's nothing.
오음모는
five conspiracies
Five conspiracies
이상한 이미지로 내 명상을 방해하지마
Weird As Image My Meditation Don't Disturb
Don't disturb my meditation with strange images
다른 거 없지 어 잠깐만
another that no uh wait
nothing else, wait a minute
내가 말고
i not
not me
열심히발톱도 좀 깎아주고
Work hard on your toenails A bit Cut them off
Cut your toenails too hard
그러면 어디로 가야 되지저 위로 올라가야 되잖아
then where go go up Go up can do it
Then where do you go? You have to go up there.
길이 어디로 나 있을까
Length WHERE I WHERE
where will the road be
밟고 올라갈 수 있나
step on go up can go up
can you step on
여기선 안 될 것 같은 느낌이기도하고 될 것 같기도
here not would be would be same as feeling would be would be would be would be
I feel like I shouldn't be here, and I feel like I can
여기 애들 많이 있네
here kids a lot there
there are a lot of kids here
어 뭐 작업 하나보다
uh what work more than one
uh, more than a job
옆에 가서 방해할 수 있나 이거
beside go get in the way be be this
Can you go next to me and disturb me?
아 이거 떨어뜨려야 꿀잼인데 어대화하기
Ah This You should drop it It's fun Talking
Oh, it's fun to drop this, but how about a conversation?
바포라를
Bapora
방해하지 말았죠 너무 서투르거든
Don't bother I didn't too I'm clumsy
Don't interrupt me, I'm too clumsy
바로 방해하러
right away interrupt
just to interrupt
조심해 집중해야 한다고 양동일도떨어뜨리고 싶지 않아
Be careful You have to focus say Drop both sides I don't want to [ W5@@ not
I don't want to drop a bucket saying I have to be careful and focus
타이밍던질 때
timing throw when
timing when throwing
언제놀래키는 거지
Always surprised Beggar
When are you kidding me
어 나이스
uh Nice
A Nice
아 일 좀 똑바로 하란 말이야 어
ah th little straight Haran  uh
Oh, I mean, do it right
[웃음]오늘 일 똑바로 했어야지 인마 어
[laugh] Today day straight should have done nigga [ W5@@ uh
[Laughs] I should have done the right thing today man uh
덜렁대고
clumsily
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
똑바로 하고
straight and
do it right
아냐
no
그러니까 말이야 일도 제대로 못하고
So I mean  properly can’t
That's why I can't do my job properly
어디로 가야 되지
where go not
where to go
여기서 쉴 수도 있네 이런 뭐 효과같은 거 있나
here rest might be there like this what like the effect something
You can rest here. Does this have any effect?
이제
now
어골고을 송 들려
Eogolgoeul Song I can hear you
I hear the eogolgoeul song
어옆에 또 누구 있는데
next door again who is there
Is there someone else next to me
그건 뭐야야
that's what is it
what is that
세상 팔자 좋게 자고 있네 누워서
world let's go good sleeping there lying down
Let's sell the world, I'm sleeping well, lying down
요
yo
yo. this
아 너구나 넌 생긴 것도 이상하고작지만 뭔가 특별한 구석이 있어
Ah You are You are looks like is also Weird and small something special corner got
Oh you, your appearance is strange and small, but there is something special about you
널 쓰다듬어 주고 싶은 느낌이 들지만그 이유를 이해하지 못하기 때문에
You Stroking Giving Wanna Feeling I heard that why don't understand don't because
I feel like stroking you but I don't understand why
그렇지 않을 거야
would be would not be would be
won't be
표면 아 그건 여기서 민감한 주제야그 개념을 이해할 수 있는 코드를
surface ah that's where sensitive subject Yag concept understand   code
surface ah that's a sensitive topic here code to understand that concept
가진 자들이 일부 있어아웃사이드에 대해 알고 있지만 전부
with those with with some got outside with [ W5@@ knows but all
There are some who have it, know about the outside, but it's all
포기해버렸지 그리고 아웃사이더가 있고그들이 어떤 기분인지 상상이 될 거야
gave up and outsiders and they are some feel like can imagine will be will be
I gave up and there are outsiders and you can imagine how they feel
이제는 모모만 남았어
now Momoman left
Now only mother is left
모모를 만나러 가야겠군요
Momo To meet I have to go
I'm going to go see my mom
어 뭐야 개이득에너지 드링크 스피드 얻기
uh what gain energy drink speed get
Uh what the doggainEnergy drink speed gain
에너지 드링크 이건 뭐임
Energy Drink This is What is
what is energy drink
뭐 할 때 쓰는 거지이유는 모르겠지만 슬럼의 로봇들은
what do when write why I don't know, Slum's robots are
I don't know why, but the robots in the slums
그걸 일종의 화폐로 사용하는 것 같아
that sort of currency use something Same
I guess they use it as some kind of currency
화폐로 사용한다고
as currency [Use W1@@ as
used as currency
한 번도 안 되나돈이 공짜로 나온 거네 한마디로
one no not no for free W5 that came out of @@] [That's W6@@ in a word
The money came out for free, in a word
TV 신호가 좋지 않다재밌는 뭐 동물의 왕국 이런 거 없어
TV signal good not funny what Animal Kingdom Oh shit That No
TV signal is not good. There is no such thing as the animal kingdom.
다른 채널 틀어볼까
Another Channel Let's Play
Should I turn on another channel?
어 있을 것 같은데
uh be be look like
I guess
아노잼 세상이야 이거
Anojam It's the world This
It's a no jam world
로봇들
robots
내려가자
Let's go down
let's go down
어디로 갈까
Where Shall we go
where should we go
어디로 가야 되지
where go not
where to go
여기 아래 사이에 틈이 있다여긴
Here Below Between Gap Here
I think there is a gap between here and below
딱 봐도 뭔가 똑똑한 뭔가가 있을 것같아 로봇이
just look something smart something There might be I guess the robot
Just looking at it, it looks like there must be something smart, a robot
나이스 어 뭐야금고 사용 뭐지
nice uh uh use uh
nice uh what the safe use what
뭐 사용할 만한게 없는데 비밀번호도뭐 아니면 뭐 다른 거 찾아야 되나
What @@W1 to use] is something like doesn’t exist password, what or what something else something find
I don't have anything to use, but I need to find a password or something else
이거 다 하다 보면은단서 같은 거 얻을 수 있을지도 여기
This Everything Do Look for clues Same Got get get get here
If you do all of this, you might be able to get a clue here
뭐가 있나번역하기
What Translate
translate what is
[음악]실제 인간만큼 창의력을 키우기 위해
[Music] Real As much as humans Creativity Grow
[Music] To be as creative as a real human being
나의 인공지능을 개발하는 방법42번
My Artificial Intelligence Developing Method 42
How to develop my artificial intelligence #42
[음악]책임을 다 죽었나 맞지 거미줄 쳐져
[MUSIC] Responsible da dead right cobwebs [ W5@@ down
[Music] Are all the responsibilities dead, right?
있어
is
there is
[음악]악보 어 악보
[music] sheet music uh sheet music
[Music] Sheet music a sheet music
이건 뭐야
This is What is
What's this
아잠깐만이 곡은 약간 중요한 정보야
Wait a minute The song is Somewhat Important Information
Wait a minute, this song is a bit of important information
이 곡의 연주를 듣고 싶어[음악]
Song Play Listen Wanna [Music]
I want to hear you play this song [music]
다른 거 뭐 단서 있을 것 같은데
else thing thing clue thing thing [Same as W6@@
I think there might be a clue about something else.
어 뭐야
uh what
괜히 이런게 있을 건 아닌데[음악]
for nothing something like this would be thing it’s not [Music]
It's not like this is happening for nothing [music]
괜히 있는 건가 자는 건가왜 자는 공간을 만들어 놨지 근데
nothing is is is is why Sleep space make put but
Are you there for nothing? Why are you sleeping? Why did you make a sleeping space?
[음악]맞지
[MUSIC] That's right
[MUSIC] Right
잠깐만 누웠을 때 뭐가 있나
wait lay down when what got
What happens when you lie down for a while
주변에 뭐 없지 안 보이는데
around what isn't isn't is visible
I can't see anything around
그냥 귀여운 거 보라고귀여우라고
just cute pretty look cute
Just look cute, say cute
[음악]찾아보자
[Music] Let's find
[Music] Let's find it
어제 뭔가 단서가 분명히 있을 것같아 여기다
yesterday something clue apparently be I think here
I think there must be some clue yesterday
딱 봐도 여기다
just look here
Just look here
금고의 키를 찾았대
@@W0 in the safe] keys found
They said they found the key to the safe
이미 우리는 찾았죠 가기만하면 돼 여기
already we are we found just go you can here
We already found it, we just need to go here
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
뭐가 들었지
what heard
what did it cost
기호가 그려진 이상한 노트야독이라는 로봇의 것으로 보여
symbol drawn weird @@W3 named Knotyadok] robot [ W5@@ as as
A strange note with a symbol appears to belong to a robot called Yadok.
몇 주간의 연극 끝에 분광계와 강력한UV 램프를 결합하는데 성공했어 이걸
Few Weekly Play End of Spectrometer Powerful UV Lamp Combining Success This
After weeks of play, I succeeded in combining a spectrometer with a powerful UV lamp.
사용하면 나가는 길에 저크를 물리칠수 있을 거야
out on the way @@W3 jerk] beat [ W5@@ will be will be
Use it and you'll be able to defeat Jerk on the way out.
어 그럼 그 괴물들 있지 좀 사냥가능
uh then that monsters yes Some Can hunt
Uh, then those monsters are possible to hunt.
맞지 저 금은 안 챙겨어 제일 중요한 건데
right that gold and silver not take care most important things
That’s right, don’t take that gold, it’s the most important thing
제일 중요한 걸 안 챙겨 버리는
most important important gal not take care throw away
Not taking care of the most important thing
주황색 네온 있는 집으로
Orange Neon In Home
home in orange neon
아 여기 저기 올라가면 되네 이제올라가는 길이
Ah here there goes up becomes now up length
Ah, all you have to do is go up here and there, the way up now
왼쪽으로는 가기 힘들 것 같은데엘리베이터 타고 가야 되나
Left Go Hard Things Elevator ride go [w7@@ become
I think it's hard to go to the left. Should I take the elevator?
엘리베이터 근데 아래에 있어서 되려나모르겠네
Elevator but under is there I don't know what to do
Elevator, but I don't know if it's down there
이거잖아근데 저게 못 올라가잖아
This is it, but That's I can't It's going up
It's this, but it can't go up.
그렇지
right
yes
어떻게 가야 잘 갔다고 소문이나
how go well went rumors
Rumor has it that it went well
아 저거 이거 밟아서
ah that this stepped on
Oh, step on this
이걸로 되겠지어 방금 캥거 뭐야
With this will be just Kangar what
I'll be fine with this. What is Kangaroo?
캥거루캥거루
kangaroo kangaroo
여긴가 보다
Is this place more than
I guess it's here
얘가 뭐 뭐
this is what what
what is he
뭐 잘 안되나얼굴이 무지개색이네
What Well I can't do it It's a rainbow color
What's not going well? Your face is the color of a rainbow
무슨 걱정 같은 거 있나 또 내가해결해 줘야 되나
what worry about like thing do again I'll solve it should give it to will be
Do you have any worries, should I solve it again?
아무래도 고쳐지지가 않아 왜 친구들을붙잡지 않았을까 이제 난 혼자야 이봐
I don't know what can't fix it can't why don't catch my friends  Now I'm I'm alone Hey
I guess it can't be fixed, why didn't I catch my friends? Now I'm alone, hey
너 원하는게 뭐지 나 이거예요 엽서아웃사이드 사진이야 거기에 가고 싶어
You What you want What is Me This is Postcard outside It's a picture there go want
What do you want? I am this. Postcard outside picture. I want to go there.
그만둬 시간낭비니까 외로움과 제목만가져다줄걸 내 친구들도 같은 꿈을
Stop it It's a waste of time Loneliness and I'll just bring you the title My friends same dreams
Stop wasting time, I'll bring you loneliness and a title, my friends have the same dream
꾸었지 하지만 이제 다 사라지고 나만혼자 남았어
I made up but now everything disappeared I'm alone I'm left
I dreamed, but now it's all gone and I'm left alone
친구들이 어디로 갔는지 모르겠어연락을 해보려 했지만
friends where went I don't know, contact me try but
I don't know where my friends went, I tried to contact them
빌어먹을 트렌시버가 작동하지 않아친구들과 내가 아웃사이드에 대한
damn transceiver not working not with friends i outside
My fucking transceiver isn't working. My friends and I are talking about the outside.
연구를 노트에 기록했어 정말로 나가고싶다면 내 것을 가져가
research note wrote really if you want to leave [ W5@@ my that take
I recorded my research in a notebook, take mine if you really want to go out
어고마워
Thank you
thank you
행운을 빈다
good luck best wishes
Good luck
모모는매우 슬퍼 보여 친구들이 그리운가 봐
Momo is very Sad I can see Friends Do you miss see
Momo looks very sad, she must miss her friends
그가 우리에게 준 노트를 확인하자뭐라고 아웃사이더 선언문 우리는 어떤
he gave us gave @@W3 notes] let's check what [ W5@@ outsider manifesto we are which
Let's check the note he gave us. What is the Outsider Manifesto?
대가를 치르더라도 아웃사이드로 나가야한다 우리는 우리
the price even if we pay outside we have to get out we are we
Even at the cost, we must go outside
형제자매를 보여야 한다 우리는저크로부터 멀리 떨어져야 한다
Siblings should be seen should be we should jerk off away from must leave must
Brothers and sisters must be shown, we must stay away from jerks
4명의 로봇이 사명했대다른 노트를 찾아야겠어
4 people robot did another notes I need to find
The four robots are on a mission. I need to find another note.
어 그 쓸모없는 노트를 아직도 찾고있니
uh those obsolete notes still Are you looking for
Are you still looking for that useless note?
예 알려주세요야 나 이거
yes please tell me or this
yes please let me know
저기 돈 돈 줄테니까 알려 줘
over there money money I'll give it to you let me know Give
I'll give you money over there, so tell me
악보연주 못하는데 너 할 줄 아는게 뭐야
Play sheet music can't do it you do line I know what is
You can't play sheet music, so what do you know how to do?
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어 얘네들 친구인가봐 사진이 다 봤지
uh these guys must be friends picture everything I saw
Hey, they must be friends, I've seen all the pictures
아주 사이가 좋았나 보네
very close good look
Looks like you got along very well
어디 보자아웃사이더
Where Let's see Outsider
let's see outsider
어
uh
이런 거 꼭 한 번씩 해줘야 돼
like this that must one once  Yes
You have to do this once in a while
어 뭐야 어 이거 쓰니까움직이는게 이상해졌어 지금 어
uh what uh this so it moves It got weird now uh
Uh, what is it? Because I use this, I move strangely. Now, uh
앞이 안 보여서 그런가 봐요 아 나도와줘 아무것도
front is not is visible is that so look Ah Come with me Nothing
I guess it's because I can't see, come to me, nothing
움직여주지
will move you
move me
조용히 살아
quietly alive
live quietly
도시의 지도문 약 450m이면 원기도모형이다 모양이다 우리 위에는 층이
@@W0 of the city] map about 450m original prayer model looks like we is on top of layer is
Map of the city At about 450m, it looks like an original prayer model. Above us is a layer
있다도시의 천장이 있는 것 같다 내
is is is is is My
There seems to be a ceiling in the city
책들에 따르면 천장 위에 크고 푸른하늘이 숨겨져 있다
Books According to Ceiling Above Big The blue sky is is hidden is
According to the books, a large blue sky is hidden above the ceiling
노란색인 거 보니까 뭔가힌트 아님
yellow that see something hint not
It's yellow, so it's not a hint
뭔지 모르겠네
what I don't know
I don't know what
여기 뭐
here what
what here
이거 왜 하는 거야 그냥 손톱간지러워서
this why what what just nails It tickles me
Why are you doing this? It's just my nails itching
손도 간지러워서 하는 거예요
hands itchy doing is
I do it because my hands are itchy.
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
떠올리기
Remember
recall
아 빼꼼 2이 비디오 게임 기억나내가 만들어진 직후에 만들어진 거
ah poke 2 video game I remember was created right after was created was created
Oh, I remember this video game, Peek Kkom 2, it was made right after I was made.
같은데 정확하게 기억은 안 나과학자 나는이 게임을 하면서 많은
looks like exactly remember not I am a scientist I have play games while a lot
I think I don't remember exactly, but I'm a scientist. I played this game a lot.
시간을 보냈어재밌었어 그가 그리워 왜 그의 이름이
time it was fun he miss why His renamed
We spent time. It was fun. I miss him. Why is his name
기억나지
I don't remember
좀 더 복구됐나 봐
Some More Recovered Look
I guess it's more restored
뭔가 브금이 지금 살짝뭔가 무서워졌는데
Something Bgeum Now Something I got scared
I'm slightly scared of something right now
너 설마 꿍꿍이 있냐 어
you no way gongkkong is there uh
Do you have any plans?
찾고 있으니까 좀 알려주세요 예
looking for so some tell me yes
I'm looking for it so please let me know
여기에서 이제 뭐 하는 거야 아니면여기도 있다
here now what what what Or here too there
What are you doing here or here too
지구 지구는 태양에서 세 번째행성이며 태양계에서 질량과 지름이
Earth Earth @@W2 from the sun] three th planet [ W5@@ @@W5 in solar system] mass and diameter
Earth Earth is the third planet from the sun and has a mass and diameter in the solar system.
다섯 번째로 큰 행성이다현재까지 생명체가 살 수 있는 것으로
five second big is a planet so far life be be be be
It is the fifth largest planet and is currently considered habitable.
알려진 유일한 천체이다방사성 연대 측정에 따르면 지구의
known the only celestial body is radioactive age measured according to on earth
It is the only known celestial body of the Earth according to radioactive dating.
나이는45억 4천만 년이다 지구는 곧 이어
age is 4.5 billion 40 million years Earth is soon followed by
Age is 4.54 billion years Earth will soon
형성된 자연 위성인달을 가지고 있다
Formed Nature Satellites Have Have
It has a formed natural satellite, the Moon.
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
지루하나 봐 고양이가읽지 말래 시끄러운 소리 하지 말래
Bored Look The cat reads Stop Noisy sound don't don't
I think it's boring, the cat won't read it, won't make loud noises
저쪽 벽에 기호와 노트에 기호가일치해 아 저거
over there on the wall symbols and notes symbols match ah that
The sign on the wall over there matches the note
얼굴같이 생겼네 저기로 가야 되나보네
Like a face [Looks like a W1@@ Over there Gotta go [Looks like a W4@@
It looks like a face, I guess I have to go over there
이게 단서인 거 같아어 그러네 생김새가 똑같이 생겼네
This is is the clue is is the same That's right Looks like looks the same looks like
I think this is a clue. Yes, they look the same.
아까 봤어 그만 얘기해 그만하게 이제
[I saw W1@@ Stop Talk Stop now
I saw it earlier, stop talking, stop talking now
아 엘리베이터 개꿀이게 제일 편하다
Ah Elevator This is the best The best Comfortable
Ah, the elevator is the most convenient
여기로 가야 되나 봐
Go here Go or look
I guess I have to go here
여기는 뭐지 여기서 이제 다음 책에대한 단서가 있는 건가
here what here now next book for [w6@@ clue for for for
What is this? Do you have a clue about the next book?
가족사진인가
Is this a family photo
Is it a family photo
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
여기도 악보가 있나요 악보악보는 근데 모아서 나중에 뭐
Here too sheet music is there sheet music but Gather later what
Is there sheet music here too?
누구한테 연주해달라고 하는 건가아포 같은 것들이 나오네
ask someone to ask me to play doing go apo same things coming out
Are you asking someone to play it?
[음악]어 노트도 있다
[Music] uh notes there
[Music] There's also a note
또 다른 노트를 찾았네 잘했어 이거
another another notes found nice this
I found another note, good job this
어쩌고의
blah
whatever
로봇의 것인가봐
Robot's I guess
I guess it's a robot
모든 것이 계획대로 진행되고 있어트랜시버가 다운되기 전에 상위 레벨에
all is as planned is in progress is transceiver [ W5@@ down [@@W6 before W6@@] up [@@W8 to W8@@ level]
Everything is going according to plan. Get to the upper level before the transceiver goes down.
연락할 수 있었어 그들은미드타운이라는 곳에 있는데
contact could was they called Midtown where [ W5@@ exists
I was able to reach them. They're in a place called Midtown.
압제 세력이 그곳을 통제하나 봐전에 모모와 이야기를 나눴어 그의 눈
oppressive forces that place control look at [ W5@@ Momo and talked talked to his eyes
I guess oppressors control it. I've talked to Momo before. His eyes
그 표정을 잘 알아요 그는 우리와함께 하지 않을 거야
that expression well I know he Join us won't won't won't
I know that look. He's not with us.
다른 노트를 찾아보자다른 노트
another note find another note
Let's find another noteOther notes
잠깐만
Wait a minute
wait for a sec
이렇게 생긴 곳에만 가면 되는 건가이제 두 개 남았네 그렇지 노트 두
like this  only   Now two two left right notes two
Is it only necessary to go to a place that looks like this? Now there are two left, right, two notes
개만 더 찾으면 되나 봐 또 나가자
only more find become look again Let's go
I guess I just need to find more dogs, let's go out again
여기 하나 있네 하나 더 있어 저기안 갔던 데잖아
here one there one more there Not there went That's where
There's one here, there's another one.
그렇지
right
yes
여기 안 갔습니다
here not went
I didn't go here
여기에 여기
here here
뭐
what
번역하기
translate
환기 전원 공급 장치
Vent Power Supply Device
ventilation power supply
이거 막 빼도 되는 건가
This is just subtracted becomes is
Can I just take this off
이러면 큰일 나는 거 아님 환기 안돼 가지고
if this is big deal I am that or not ventilation no have
If this is the case, it is not a big deal or there is no ventilation
아여기
Ah here
Oh here
이거
this
빼버린 거구나 그래서 이제 들어갈 수있는 거구나
removed that's so now go in Can that
You took it out, so you can go in now
연관이 있는 거예요물 좀 마시자
related with  little let's drink
It's related. Let's drink some water.
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
너무 달고
Too Sweet
too sweet
책을 한번 봐보자
book once let's see
Let's take a look at the book
길인가 봐야 돼
Is this the road Must see Can be
I have to see if it's the road
마지막 노트야 아 마지막 노트였나이것은
last note ah last note this is
It's the last note. Ah, it was the last note.
라는 로봇의 것인가봐 우리가 저크라고부르는 것을 제외한 모든 유기
[@@W0 called W0@@] [@@W1 of W1@@ robot] I guess we @@W4 we call jerk]  except all Organic
All organic except for what we call a jerk.
생명체의 흔적이 사라졌어그들은 움직이는 거의 모든 걸
creatures traces gone they moving almost all gal
All signs of life are gone. They see almost anything that moves.
잡아먹고 상상을 할 수 없는 속도로번식해이 도시에 갇힌 것만으로도
eat imagine do be no Breeding at speed @@W6 in the city] trapped just
It eats and reproduces at an unimaginable speed, just being trapped in this city.
힘든데 말이야 오이책에도 메모가 있네
It's hard I mean Cucumber book notes there
It's hard, but there's a memo in the cucumber book
설계결함을 발견했지만 고칠 방법도 알아낸
design flaw found but fix method also found
Found a design flaw, but figured out how to fix it
것 같다 공식은 다음과 같다 이게있으면 모모가 트랜시버로 수리하는데
equals equals equals equals equals If you have this Momo Transceiver Repair
It seems that the formula is as follows. If there is this, Momo repairs it with a transceiver.
도움이 되겠어
will help will help
would be helpful
야 모모한테 이제 가면 되나 봐 그아까 젤리같이 생긴 애들이
hey to Momo now go will be Look Just now like jelly looks like kids
Hey, I guess I can go to Momo now, those kids who look like jelly
[음악]생명체들을 전부 다 먹나 봐 그냥
[Music] Creatures All All Eat Look [ W5@@ just
[Music] I think it eats all living things, just
뭐든지[음악]
Anything [Music]
근데 걔 센과 치히로였나[음악]
but he Sen and Chihiro [Music]
But was he Sen and Chihiro? [Music]
아니 하울의 움직이는 성이었나 거기가나오는 그
No Howl's Moving Was it a castle @@W4 coming out of there] [ W5@@ that
No, was it Howl's Moving Castle?
무슨 요리 같이 생겼어 아빠가 먹는거
What cooking like looks like dad Eating
What kind of dish does it look like, what dad eats
요리 같은 거 있잖아[음악]
cooking like stuff you know [Music]
There's such a thing as cooking [music]
자 왔어 다
now here everything
here you come
찾았다 어 이거 먼저 보여줄게그거 하는 말은 거의 이해하지
found uh this first I'll show you that that mean almost don't understand
I found it. I'll show you this first. I hardly understand what it says.
못했지만 매우 현명했던 건 분명해
failed very wise thing clear
but it must have been very wise
뭐 알려주지 않으련다 찾은 거 아니야 이건가
What I'll tell you I don't want to found something No Is this
I won't tell you what, I didn't find it, is this it?
아니 알려줄 사람
no tell me person
no one to tell
어 찾았어 찾았어 아 그 노트는 뭐야트렌시볼을 수리할 수 있다고 굉장한데
uh found found ah that Note Transiball Repair Can  That's great,
Oh, I found it, I found it. Ah, what is that note?
우리가 슬럼 밖에서도 소통할 수있다는 거지
we slum outside communicate can [ W5@@ beggar
That we can communicate outside the slums
[음악]응 좋아 가자
[Music] Yeah Okay Let's go
[Music] Alright let's go
[음악]되려나
[music] to be
[MUSIC] Will it be
작동한다 자 날 따라와
works now follow me Follow me
It works now follow me
뭔데
What is
What
저 위쪽 다른 건물보다 높은 건물보여
lower upper other higher than higher Show the building
I see a taller building than the other buildings up there.
송신탑에 맨 꼭대기에 트렌시버를설치하면 전체와 통신할 수 있을 거야
[@@W0 on W0@@ transmission tower] top [@@W2 on top of W2@@] install transceiver all and communicate be be be
If you put a transceiver on the top of the transmission tower, you'll be able to communicate with the whole thing.
오케이트랜시버
OK transceiver
그래 나만 믿어라 간다
Yes Only Believe me Go
yes just trust me
아니지아 이건가
No, Is this
no, this is it
저거 아니잖아 빛나는 거일단 이거 타는거
That Isn’t that Shining Geoildan This riding
It's not that one, it shines, once it burns
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
엄청 말도 잘 알아듣는다
very words well understand
I understand very well
옥상
Rooftop
rooftop
마음의 준비
@@W0 of the heart] ready
mental preparation
저크들 개막
Jerks Opening
Jerks opening
얘네들 보니까 하프라이프에 나오는 그누구랑 좀 비슷하게 생겼다 몬스터들
guys seeing Half-Life coming out with someone [ W5@@ kinda similar looks like monsters
Looking at these guys, they look a bit like someone from Half-Life Monsters
적 유인하기 유인해서 뭐 해 위험할것 같은데 웬 해야 되나
enemy lure lure what do It must be dangerous [It looks like W6@@ What should be should be
Lure the enemy What should I do by luring it?
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
바로론바로랑
Baro Ron Baro and
Baro Lon Baro
바로 런
right run
한 바퀴 돌아주고
one wheel turn
give a round
돌면서어디로 갈지 파악을 여기다
turning to where going figure out here
Thinking about figuring out where to go
너희들은 안 된다이 말이야[음악]
you guys don't do this [Music]
You guys say no [music]
어 못 올라와 못 올라가
uh can't up can't up
I can't go up, I can't go up
떠올리기메모리
recall memory
도시는 내원으로 가득 차 있었어 항상그랬던 건 아니지만
city visit full car was Always is but not
The city was full of visits, it wasn't always like that
특히 슬로우맨은 엄격한 에너지 한도가있었지 하지만 사람들은 계속되는
especially slowman is strict energy had limits [ W5@@ but people continued
Slowman in particular had a strict energy limit, but people continued to
어둠을 견딜 수 없었어 어느 날 누가무지개 램프를 켰어 집 전체
Darkness Withstand Can Never Which me who rainbow lamp turned on house all
I couldn't stand the darkness. One day, someone turned on the rainbow lamp.
네온사인을그 사람은 잡혀가 없고 다시는 볼 수
Neon sign person got caught no never again see see
Neon sign. The person is never caught and will never be seen again.
없었어 하지만 사람들은 희망을 보았고얼마 지나지 않아 모두가 집에 많은
didn't have but people hope saw how much  not everyone home a lot
No, but people saw hope and soon everyone was at home.
조명을 설치하기 시작했지압제자들은 더 이상 아무것도 할 수
lighting installing started the disciples more more Anything Do Do
They started installing lights, but the oppressive disciples could do nothing more.
없었어그렇게 해서 사람들은 아웃사이드처럼
didn't exist like that so people like outside
There wasn't, that's why people like the outside
색을 다시 볼 수 있게 되었어
color see see be be Got it
I can see colors again
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
여기 아니고여기도 아니고
here not here not
not here, not here
어디로 가야 돼여기인가
Where Go Is it here
Where should I go?
아 다시 반동
ah again recoil
Oh rebound again
이거는 안에 들어가서[음악]
this is [in W1@@ go in [MUSIC]
It goes inside [Music]
천재야
genius
어 엄청 위험한데 그치
uh very that's dangerous that's right
Oh, it's very dangerous, right?
문 해킹하기[음악]
Moon [Hack W1@@ [Music]
Hack the door [music]
어 잘했어 잘했어 잘했어야 가도 가둬 가둬 다 들어오면
uh well done well done well done go lock up lock up all come in
Uh good job good job should have done well
가둬 가둬가둬
lock up lock up
[음악]아니 아니 아니 아니
[Music] no no no no
[Music] No no no no
잠깐만 잠깐만
Wait Wait
wait wait wait
유인한 다음에 오케이아 그냥 가도 되나 어 바로 가도 돼
yinhan then okay just go can be uh right can go can be
After luring in, okay can I just go?
어 바로 가도 돼좋아 못 넘어와
uh right can go good can't Come over
You can go right away.
로저드는 절대 뭐[음악]
Rodgers Never What[Music]
Rogers never did anything [music]
어떻게 하려고 어떻게 하려고
how try how try
how to do how to do
주둥이 보여 줘 봐 봐
Snout Show Give Look Look
Show me your snout
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
너네들도 나처럼 이렇게 귀엽게태어났어야지
you guys like me like this should have been born cute
You guys should have been born this cute like me
찐득이 녀석들
sticky guys
goo guys
저기로 하는 건가
over there that that's
Are you doing it over there?
저기 들어가는틈이 보이네
over there through the gap can be seen
I see a gap there.
설마 이것들
no way these
들어왔어
came in
뭔가 애들 많을 것 같이 생겼다 맞지
something kids a lot something like looks like right
It looks like there are a lot of kids, right?
뭔가심상치 않은 느낌
Something unusual not feeling
feeling something out of the ordinary
[박수]
[Applause]
[clap]
여기 아주난장판이구만
Here What a mess
It's such a mess here
애들이 많아요
kids a lot
I have a lot of kids
벌레들얘네들을 뚫고
Insects break through
Break through the worms
[음악]저기 넘어가야 되나 보다
[Music] Over there Gotta go or more than
[Music] I guess I have to go over there
나 여기 있다
or here there
i am here
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
개
out
dog
빠르네 그냥 어깜짝 놀랐네
That's fast It's just I'm so surprised I'm surprised
It's fast, I was just surprised
근데 진짜발로 한번 쳐보고 싶다 저거지
but with real feet once try [I want W4@@ That's
But I really want to hit it with my feet, that's it
타격감 진짜 지릴 듯끊을 것 같지 않아 바로 차면은
Sense of blow Really Grill I'm going to cut it would be Same Not right is
The feeling of hitting seems really tiring, it doesn’t seem like it will stop
[음악] [박수]
[Music] [Applause]
그러면해킹하고 얘네 나오게 유인해서 저거
then hack it these guys make it come out lure it that
Then hack it and lure them out and that's it
안에 거 굴러오게 만들어서 이거 타고
in stuff roll it make it this ride
I made it roll inside, so I rode it
위로 올라가는 거구만맞지 자
Up Up That's right now
You're going up, that's right, come on
준비
ready
preparation
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아잠깐만 아 잠깐만 아 잠깐만 잠깐만
Wait a minute Oh wait Wait a minute Oh wait Wait Wait a minute
Oh wait, oh wait, oh wait, wait
잠깐만잠깐만
Wait a minute
wait a minute
올라갈 수 있어 올라갈 수 있어올라갈 수 있어 잠깐만 잠깐 잠깐만
go up go up go up go up go up go up Up can there wait wait wait
I can go up, I can go up, I can go up, wait, wait, wait
잠깐만 잠깐만잠깐만
Wait a minute Wait a minute
wait wait wait wait
잠깐만 일단 나와 봐 나와서 얘기하자나왔어
wait a minute come out come out look come out talk It came out
Wait a minute, come out, let's talk.
침착해
Calm down
calm down
어
uh
그대로 생각보다 많아 가지고 이거
as it is is bigger than I thought is a lot has this
As it is, there are more than I thought, and this
한껏 여유 즐기기네코
To the fullest Relax Enjoy Neko
Enjoy your time to the fullest Neko
크롭그들은 폐기물 관리를 담당했지 그들은
cropthey waste management take charge they
Crop, they were in charge of waste management, they
상류 레벨의 쓰레기가 슬럼을 뒤덮자박테리아를 개발해서 모두 녹여버리려고
Upstream Level Garbage Slum Overwhelm Bacteria developed all to melt
When upper-level trash covers the slums, they develop bacteria to melt them all down.
했어인간이 사라진 후 그 박테리아가
did humans gone then that bacteria
I did. After humans disappeared, the bacteria
돌연변을 일으켰어 점점 성장하면서쓰레기보다 훨씬 더 많은 것들을
mutated caused getting growing more than crap much more more a lot things
It's mutated, growing up, doing so much more than trash
먹었지 아돌연변이
ate Submutation
I ate a mutant
너네들이[음악]
you guys [music]
박테리아
bacteria
이거 어떻게 해야 되지 저기
this how should be not there
how do i do this
아 여기 가서이거 그냥 올라가는거다 올라가서
ah here go to this just go up go up
Oh, go here, this is just going up, go up
올라가고
going up
여기로 유인을 시켜그렇지
go here yin make it right
Let me lure you here, right?
계속 유인시켜 가만히 있어 그 다음해킹에서 문 아니다
Continue Enticing Stay still Stay That In the next hack statement not
Keep luring me, stay still It's not a door from the next hack
일단 유인했잖아그렇지
First of all lured you, right
You lured it once, that's right
다 여기 모였거든그 사이에 조금 그냥 끌고 나가서
everything here we got together that between little bit just drag go out
Everyone has gathered here. In the meantime, I just dragged them out for a while
타고 올라가서 그냥 바로 나가는 건가시간이 될까
ride go up just right go out Will it be time
Is it time to get on board and leave right away?
야 너 뭐냐 야 야 야꺼져이 자식이 지금 위험한
hey you hey hey hey hey Fuck this bastard now dangerous
Hey, what are you? Hey, hey, what are you doing?
[음악]아 꺼져
[Music] Ah Get lost
[MUSIC] Oh fuck it
쓰레기가 한 마리[음악]
Garbage One Marie [Music]
One Garbage [Music]
쑥쑥쑥
Growing up
야 미친 뭐야
Hey Crazy What
hey what's crazy
헐수틀리면 애들한테 또 죽는다
If you're wrong to the kids again die
If you're wrong, the kids will kill you again
넘어가 넘어가넘어가
go over go over
pass over pass over
달려 잽싸게 달려 잽싸게 달려 잽싸게달려 오케이
run run run run run run quickly Run okay
Run, run, run, run, run, okay
진짜 로봇들은 좀 힘들긴 하겠다 그치날아서 이렇게 하는 거지 고양이라
Really Robots are A bit It's hard I'll do it Just flew by like this doing beggar a cat
Real robots must be a bit difficult, but they do it because they fly. It's a cat.
가지고[음악]
have[music]
have [music]
엘리베이터
Elevator
elevator
넘어가면 돼넘어가면 그만이
if it goes over if it goes over is enough
It's okay if you go over it, it's over
다시 이렇게 한 바퀴 돌면 그만이응 더 돌면 그만해 더 돌면 점프하면
again like this one wheel turn stop Eung more turn stop more turn jumps
If you spin one more time like this, stop
그만하네 더놀아주면 그만해
Stop Play more Stop
Stop it, if you play more, stop it
넘어가서
go over
저거 문 어떻게 열지
that door how to open open
how do i open that door
절대 안 돼
never not ok
no way
태생부터가 다르다 꺼져 바로차기 전에
from birth different go away straight kick before
We're different since we were born
어디 매달리나 얘들아
Where Hang on Guys
Where are you hanging guys
은근히 점프력 좋네어제도 막 터진다
Subtly Jumping power I like it even yesterday Just Explodes
You have good jumping ability, you just exploded yesterday
스펙타클이
Spectacle is
the spectacle
박수 해주는 거 봐봐 고생했다고왜 안 열리네
applause do that look at why did you have a hard time not open
Look at the applause. You said you worked hard. Why doesn't it open?
여기야이 안테나의 트렌치볼을 넣어
Here's this Antenna Trenchball put
This is where I put the trench ball of this antenna
[음악]작동 중
[music] works [@@W1 of W1@@]
[music] working
아 저기 위에가 저기 그 상위레벨 뭐 이런 건가 맞지 여기가 이제
ah there there there there High level what like this is it right this is now
Oh, go upstairs, that top level, right?
데드시티였잖아
It was Dead City
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
smart
cat
아름다운 광경이야이제 기억이 나이 도시가 원래는
beautiful sight now I don't remember age city [ W5@@ Originally
It's a beautiful sight. Now I remember that this city was originally
대피소였어
It was a shelter
it was a shelter
저 별처럼 보이는 빛은도시를 봉쇄한 지붕을 표시하는 불빛일
That Like a star Visible Light City Blocked @@W5 roof] @@W6 displaying] lights
The light that looks like a star is a light marking the roof that sealed the city.
뿐이야아웃사이드로부터 인류를 보호하기
only from the outside protecting humanity protecting
It's only to protect humanity from the outside
위해이 껍데기를 만들었어 하지만 그에대한 대가가 따랐지 아무도 나갈 수
for this shell made but for that price follow no one get out be
Wei made this shell, but it came at a price. No one could get out.
없었던 거야
didn't exist was
there was no
아웃사이드는 재앙이었어 완전한불모지라 생존할 수도 없고 위험했지
Outside It was a disaster Completely barren Survival capital city [There was no W5@@ was dangerous
Outside was a disaster, completely barren, unsustainable and dangerous.
하지만 네가 그곳에서 왔다면 다시그곳이 안전해졌다는 의미겠지
but you there if you came again there [ W5@@ @@W5 says it's safe] must mean
But if you came from there, that means it's safe again
그리고 내 약속은 아웃사이드로 가는것 뿐만이 아니야 도시를 개방하는
and my promises outside going [ W5@@ only not city opening
And my promise isn't just to go outside, it's to open up the city
것도 있었어 아까처음에 시작됐던 그 고양이들이 살았던
was there at the beginning started that Cats lived
There was also something. Those cats that started earlier lived
그 평화로운 데가 아웃사이드구나 맞지
That Peaceful Day Outside Right
That peaceful place is outside, right?
하지만 이제 이게 내 목표인 건확실해 도시를 개방해야 해 자
but now this is my target I'm sure city open do characters
But now I'm pretty sure this is my goal I need to open up the city now
돌아가서 모모를 찾자 이제 송신기를연결했으니까 도움을 받을 수 있을
Go back Momo Let's find now I connected the transmitter help get be be
Let's go back and find Momo. Now that we've hooked up the transmitter, we can get some help.
거야
is
going to be
아 그럼 고양이가 세상을 구해야 되는거야
ah then the cat save the world save It works
Oh then the cat has to save the world
어 개꿀 여기 아 좋다
uh gag here ah good
Uh honey here ah good
이거 좀 떼야겠다허리 아프다
This A bit I need to take off my waist It hurts
I need to take this off. My back hurts.
가는 거 다 보여주지 어경추 좀 보려고 그랬는데
go go go I'll show you go Somewhat [To see W6@@ I did
I'll show you everything I'm going to.
[음악]슬럼 파트 2
[Music] Slum Part 2
내가 나왔어 모모에 어디 갔니 뭐야이쪽지 가출했나 저 메모다
I am is out Momoe where are you gone What is this note ran away that memo
I came out, where did you go to Momo?
작은 아웃사이더 네가 이것을 읽고있다면 네가 아직 살아있다는 거겠지
Little Outsider If you are reading read this  You still is alive must be
Little Outsider If you're reading this you're probably still alive
잘했어 안테나를활용하기 위해 내가 몇 가지 장비를
good job to utilize antenna to i several [ W5@@ things equipment
Nice job. To utilize the antenna I have some equipment
따로 가져왔어 바에서 만나창을 잠갔지만 여는 코드는 매우
separately [I brought W1@@ at the bar meeting window locked open code is very
I brought it separately. I locked the window at the bar, but the code to open it is very
간단해 코드
simple code
[음악]이거 어떻게 간단한 거지
[Music] This How Simple Beggar
[MUSIC] How simple is this
대소문자를구
lower case
uppercase letters
[음악]분 네가 해줄 거지 어
[Music] min you do beg uh
[Music] Min, you'll do it, uh
너가 해줄 거잖아어
you will do it for you that's it
you're gonna do it
맞지
right
Right
고등을h였던
high school
who graduated from high school
[음악]이제
[MUSIC] Now
[Music] Now
빠로 가야 되나 봐[음악]
Paro Go Become Look [Music]
Guess I'll have to go to the bar [Music]
이거 타고 가도 되나
this ride can go will be
can i ride this
아 생각해보니까 아래쪽일 것 같긴하다 맞지 왜냐면 아까 바텐더같이
Ah Come to think of it the bottom one stuff looks like That's right because earlier like a bartender
Oh, now that I think about it, it seems to be down there, right, because like the bartender before
입었던 로봇이 한 명 있었거든걔 왠지 좀 빠듯한 거 같은
wore robot one people had him Somehow kinda tight like like
There was one robot who wore it. He seemed a bit tight for some reason
나 방금 무슨뭐였지 방금
Me Just What was Just
what did i just do
[음악]고양이도 이제 디지털화가 되어가는
[Music] Even cats Now Digitization becoming
[Music] Cats are becoming digital too
건가[음악]
Gunga [Music]
Gunga [music]
로봇이 되어가고 있는 거야[음악]
robot is becoming is is [Music]
You're becoming a robot [music]
번역하기
translate
의류
clothing
clothes
옷 3
Clothes 3
clothes 3
난 뜨개질 좋아해요 지금까지 스카프를770km나 짰어
I Knitting I like So far Scarves 770km [ W5@@ made up
I love knitting. I've knitted 770 km of scarves so far.
와전선을 가져오면 판초를 만들어 줄 수
and wire get poncho make give [ W5@@ number
If you bring a wire, I can make a poncho for you.
있어 너는 내게 영감을 주거든 하지만이곳에서 적절한 재료를 찾기 쉽지
I have you give me inspire me give me But here appropriate material find easy
Yes, you inspire me, but it's not easy to find the right ingredients here.
않아요돈 줄게요 그러면 내가
No money I'll give you Then I'll
I'll give you the money then I
물물교환자가 그런물건을 찾고 있다고 들었어
Barter @@W1 looking for stuff like that] looking for said heard
I heard the barter was looking for stuff like that.
물물교환
barter
널 허락하면너를 허락하지
you allow you allow you
If I allow you, I will allow you
물물교환자 찾으면 이거 뭐 교환가능할 듯
barter find this what can be exchanged seems to be
If you find a barter, you can exchange this for something.
아무것도 없을 것 같아
Nothing Nothing Something Like
there seems to be nothing
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
트림 소리가 들려 어
burp sound hear uh
I hear a burp
뭔
What
what
오늘이 어제 내일이면 내일은 오늘이어제가 되는 거지 시간이 이상해
Today is Yesterday Tomorrow is Tomorrow is Today is becomes beggars time is strange
If today is yesterday and tomorrow, tomorrow will be today and then the time is strange
우리는 물렁한 조상들처럼 늙지 않아우리는 여기 영원히 갇혀 있는 거야
we are soft like our ancestors not old not we are here forever stuck in gonna be
We don't grow old like our soft ancestors we're stuck here forever
돈 좀
money little
some money
착한 녀석이구나
Kind That guy
What a nice guy
알림 세이프존 남쪽 입구 감시자 구함일당은
Notification Safe Zone South Entrance Watcher Wanted crew
Reminder The group looking for guards at the southern entrance of the safe zone
슈바 오일 1리터 여기는 이제일당을 기름으로 주나 보네
Shuba Oil 1 liter This is Lee Jeildang Oil Joona I see
1 liter of Shuba oil, it seems like they pay a daily wage for oil here.
이것도 알바 같은 거 할 수 있나본데
this is also Alba same thing do be seems to exist
I thought I could do something like this part-time job too
어
uh
물물교환 여기 왼쪽으로 가면물물교환하는데 있나 보다 맞지
bartering here to the left bartering is there more than right
Barter If you go to the left here, you're probably bartering, right?
물물교환여기로 가면은
barter here mask is
If you go to barter here
아이고 수고 많으십니다 아까 그 위엔놈이 떨어뜨린 거죠 아직도 닦고
Aigoo Good job You’re a lot Earlier That Wiennom dropped was still wiped
Oh, you've worked hard. That guy dropped it earlier. I'm still cleaning it
있었네 지금또 매장 현관을 치워야 하잖아 내
was there now again store the front door I have to clean it Hey My
Yes, I have to clean the front door again now, my
가게 위에서 놀지마이 어줍잖은 것들아그러게 말입니다 고생하세요 예
shop on top don't play shy things like that I mean Please work hard Yes
Don't play on top of the store.
[음악]여기가
[MUSIC] Here it is
슈퍼스 프릿 이거 뭐예요 여기세탁하는 곳인가 여기서 천 같은 거
Supers Frit This What is it Wash here where is where thousand like where
What is Super Frit? Is this a place where you do laundry?
아까 뭐지 아니 전선이었나 없나 여기없으려나 뭐 챙길만한 거 있을 것
Earlier What is No Was it a wire [Is there no W4@@ Shouldn't it be here something worth taking something something something
What was it earlier, or was it a wire or not?
같은데돈 같은 거 훔칠 수 있지 않을까
same money same thing steal be Hey I guess
I wonder if I can steal something like money
어디 카운터 없음
where counter no
no counter anywhere
뭔가 있을 것 같은데
Something Something Something Something
there must be something
어슈퍼스프리 세제였기
A Super Spree It was detergent
It was A Super Spree detergent.
엄청
very
[음악]넘어요
[MUSIC] Go beyond
[Music] Get over it
저녀석은 또 세제를 잔뜩 써서 페인트를
That guy is again Detergent lots of  paint
That guy uses a lot of detergent again to paint
지우고 있네
delete exists
I'm erasing
값이 많이 나갈 것 같아
value much going out going going out
I think it will cost a lot
계세요
stay
anybody home
제발 어린애처럼 굴지 마 널 해치지않을 거야 안에서 얘기하는 건데
Please Like a child Become Do You Won't hurt is inside talking is
Please don't act like a child I won't hurt you I'm talking inside
뭐 하고 있는 거야 어
what and what what uh
what are you doing
뭐 하고 있는 거야
what and what what
what are you doing
응
yes
huh
번역하기
translate
여기 왼쪽으로 여기가 그러면은 그거같은데
here to the left this is then I think that's it
Here to the left, here, then it seems like that.
상점
store
shop
어 스타필드나 이거 안되네 여기서 돈 나오던데
uh Starfield or this doesn't work here Don came out
Uh, Starfield, this doesn't work. Money comes from here.
길을 잃은 것 같네 뭐가 필요하지 뭐안 필요해요
way lost things like what I don't need I don't know what I need
I think I'm lost, I need something, I don't need anything
돈 있나요 가져갈 만한 거
Money Got Take Worth Thing
Do you have any money to bring?
고대 이야기에는 별에서 새어나와 우리발 아래에 닿는 자연스러운 빛에 대한
ancient stories from the stars seeping out our feet [ W5@@ under tethered natural light on against
Ancient stories tell of the natural light that leaks from the stars and reaches beneath our feet.
거 좋아하지 않아고양이는 지루해
I don't like I don't like cats I'm bored
I don't like cats. Cats are boring.
오랜 초상에 물렁한 자들은 우리에게이도시를 남겼다 우리의 집이 그들의
old portrait soft guys us this city left our their their
Those who are soft with old portraits have left us this city, and our home is theirs.
유산이다 그러니까 인간이로봇을 만들어냈을 거 아냐 그래서
Legacy So Humans made robots created things no so
It's a heritage, so humans must have created robots, so
조상이라고 하나 봐그렇지
ancestor one look that's right
Look at my ancestors, right?
딱 봐도 왼쪽이 인간이고 오른쪽이로봇이잖아
just look the one on the left is is a human the one on the right is a robot
As you can see, the one on the left is a human and the one on the right is a robot.
우리 조상만에서이 색들을 구별할 수있었다 한때 전 세계는 색깔이 잔뜩
us ancestor only colors could distinguish  once before the world color a lot
Only our ancestors were able to distinguish these colors. At one time the whole world was full of colors.
있었다고 한다
said said
It is said that there was
고생하세요상인 만나야 되거든요
Thank you for your hard work, Merchant I have to meet you will be
Have a hard time. I have to meet the merchant.
어 너구나
uh You are
oh it's you
안녕 나는 시장에 상인이야 너가나한테 뭘 주면 내가 너한테 뭘 주는
hi I'm to the market I'm a merchant you to me [ W5@@ what give I you what give
Hi I'm a trader at the market what do you give me what do I give you
거지 간단하지 않아 이건 고대유물이야 우리 선조들의 재능에 대한
beggar not simple not this is it's an ancient artifact us ancestors talent
It's not simple. This is an ancient artifact. It's a testament to the talents of our ancestors
증거지교환하려면 에너지 드링크 3개 어 나
To exchange evidence Energy Drink 3 pieces uh [ W5@@ or
3 energy drinks to exchange evidence
돈 없는데
money doesn't exist
no money
이거 뭐야시장 어 전선이다 이거 얼마 하우머치
This is What's the market uh It's a wire This is How Much How Much
What is this market uh wires how much is this
how much isit어야
how much is it
야 야야 오다 주웠다
Hey Hey Come Pick up
Ya ya ya come pick it up
나이스
Nice
nice
전선 3 이거 뭐야악보
Wires 3 This What's Music
frontline 3 what is this sheet music
어 야 이거 악보도 줘플렉스 해야겠다
uh hey this sheet music give me a flex I have to
Hey, give me the sheet music for this too. I need to flex it.
플렉스
Flex
flex
그다음 이거 하나 파는 건가 이거고대 유물도 필요하려나
then this one selling or this Ancient Artifacts I need
Do you want to sell this next one? Do you need an ancient relic?
에너지 드링크 찾으면은
Energy Drink Find
If you are looking for an energy drink
왠지이 근처에 캐나다 줄 것 같지않아 인간적으로
Somehow Near Canada Give Something Not the same Humanly
For some reason, it doesn't seem like Canada will be around here, personally.
안에 고양이 적으로왠지 내가 봤을 때 캐나다 같은 거
inside cat somehow I saw  Canada like stuff
As a cat enemy inside, somehow it's like Canada when I see it
얻을 수 있을 것 같아
get get get get get
i think i can get it
저칼을 막는데 도움이 되는이 물건들이있어서 다행이야 슬럼의 위협 요소의
that knife is blocking helps is has stuff Glad Slum Threat Elements
Glad you have these items to help keep that knife out of the slum menace.
대변하는 것은 필수지
represents is required
Representation is essential
이 쓰레기통에 잔뜩 들어있는 숨겨진보석을 봐 하늘에서 떨어진 돈이야
this trash bin a bunch contains hidden gem [ W5@@ look from the sky fell money
Look at all the hidden gems in this dumpster, it's money from the sky
하늘이 아니라면 다른 곳에서 왔겠지울던 홀던 냄새가 난다
sky if not other from would have been crying [ W5@@ Holden smells smells
If it wasn't for the sky, it would have come from somewhere else.
뭔가 좋은 냄새가있을 것 같은데
something good would be smelly would be would be nice
Something must smell good
분명 뭔가 있을 것 같은데 여기하나 꽁으로 주지 않을까
sure something something something something here Hana  I'll give you
I'm sure there must be something, but I'll give you one here
없으려나 이렇게 뭔가 많은데
Is there any like this something there are a lot
There are so many things like this
분명히 있어 내가 봤을 때 없을 수가없어
obviously got got got got got got can't count
It's definitely there, when I see it, there's no way it's not there
밟고 올라가는게 왜 있을까암만 생각해도
[Stepping on W0@@ Going up Why I'm sure there is I think
Why do I step on it? Even if I think about it
그냥 떨구기 위해서 정말로 장난치기위해
just drop for really just kidding
Just to drop, to really play around
고양이 게임이다 그냥 장난치려고 있는요소인가
cat it's a game just just kidding is an element
It's a cat game. Is it just a playful element?
아 여기서 뭔가 꽁돈 하나 나올 것같은데
ah here something don't pay one come out [Looks like W6@@
Oh, I think something is going to come out of here.
일단 아까 그거옷가게 한번 가보죠 옷가게
Once Earlier That clothing store Once Let's go clothing store
First of all, let's go to that clothing store.
여기 뭐지
here what
what is here
이상한 일은 항상 너한테서일어나는구나 나 무서워서 마을을 안
weird things always it happens to you me scared village not
Strange things always happen to you.
떠나 너무 위험해 게다가이 문을 열수 있는 건
leave too dangerous besides this open the door open number in thing
It's too dangerous to leave, besides, the only thing that can open this door
뿐이야
only
너도 허락하면
You too with permission
if you allow
그걸 거리에 놓아뒀었는데 다음날저크가 전부 먹어버렸어
on the street I left it next day jerk all I ate it
I left it on the street and the next day the jerk ate it all up
정말 말도 안 되지 않아 다먹어치우잖아
not really not even not not not everything You eat it up
It's really nonsense, you eat it all up
뭔가 좀어디 있을 것 같은데 돈
Something Somewhere Something Something Looks like Don
Money seems to be somewhere
아줌마전선 가져왔어요
Auntie Frontline I brought it
I brought the auntie's wire
[음악]옷 주세요 옷
[Music] Clothes Please Clothes
[Music] Clothes, please.
궁금하다 그죠 어떻게 될지
I wonder That's right How will be
I'm curious, that's how it will be
판초 새로운 아이템 매트잘 어울릴 거야
Poncho New Item Matte Fit It's
Poncho new item mat will look good
어디 있어이거다
Where is this
where is this
이건 정말 따뜻해 보여 추운 로봇에게딱 좋겠지
this is really warm looks cold robot Perfect for would be nice
This looks really warm, perfect for a cold robot
로봇
robot
어 내가 입는 거 아니야어
uh I wearing that no
oh that's not what i wear
새워서 마음에 드네아 내 옷 아니야
New I like Denea My Clothes no
I like it because it's new, it's not my clothes
추운 놈한테 줘야 돼너 춥니
Cold  You should give it You Cold
I have to give it to a cold guy. You are cold.
뭘 원하는 거지야 이거 잠깐만 이거
what want beggar this wait this
What do you want?
[음악]뛰어난 재능이야
[MUSIC] Excellent Talent
[Music] What a talent
내가 더 인사하는 거아니
I more say hi no
I'm saying hello more
고영희입히려고 열심히 해놨던 건데 어
Trying to wear Ko Young-hee working hard I did is uh
I worked hard to wear Ko Young-hee.
모모다 여기가 빠구나
Momoda This is is missing
Momoda is out of here
아 조심 좀 하지어 비켜주는거
ah be careful a little bit don't do it get out of the way
Oh, be careful, get out of the way
뭘 원하는 거지 이거 어디다 쓰는지알아
what want beg this where write I know
What do you want? I know where to put this.
모르는구나여기 앉으라고
You don't know, here Sit down
You don't know. Sit here.
여기 수건 좀 줘봐 어
here towel some give me uh
give me a towel here
있을 것 같은데
would be would be would be
I think there is
넌 처음 왔구나 뭘 도와줄까
You First time You're here What Can I help you
You're here for the first time. How can I help you?
너희들 프로그래밍 되어 있니어
you guys programming being being
you guys are programmed
[음악]이거 뭐야
[MUSIC] This is what
[MUSIC] What is this
음악 변경[음악]
Music Change [Music]
change music [music]
안 되는데
not but
I can't
지금 뭐 이벤트 중이라 그런 건가이거
now what event busy that Gungeiger
Is it because there is an event going on right now?
[음악]이게 자동 하는지 볼까
[Music] This is Auto  Let's see
[MUSIC] Let's see if this is automatic
뭐야거의 됐어
almost okay
what's up
여보세요 누구 내 말 들리나 어 그래당신의 말이 들려 우리는 슬럼에 있어
Hello Who My Say Can you hear me uh yes your say hear we in the slum [there is W11@@
Hello can anyone hear me uh yes I can hear you we're in the slum
우리는 출구를 찾고 있고잠깐
we have exit looking for wait
We're looking for an exit, wait
지발 타자 아니야 모모
Late Batter No Momo
I'm not a late batter, Momo
믿을 수 없어 집 앞 타자목소리를들을 수 있어 정말 기뻐
Unbelievable Can No House Front Batting Hear the voice can got really glad
I can't believe it, I'm so glad I can hear the voice of a batter in front of my house
어디야 다들 괜찮아친구 중에 한 명이 있다 그치
Where are you Everyone It's okay friends in one Name there is that's right
Where are you, everyone is fine, one of my friends is right
그래 우리 안전해 위로 가는 방법을찾았어
yes we safe up going I found a way
Yes, we're safe. I found a way to the top.
여보세요 내 말이 들리나 우리한테오려면 하수도를 통과해야 해
hello my say can you hear me come to us sewer must go through do
Hello can you hear me You have to go through the sewers to get to us
매우 위험해아기들
very dangerous babies
걱정엄마 걱정 마
Worry Mom Worry Don't
don't worry mom
수도는 슬럼에서 가장 위험한 곳이지만
capital slum the most dangerous but
The capital is the most dangerous place in the slums,
성공했다면 방법이 있을 거야
@@W0 if successful] method would be would be would be
If you succeed, there must be a way
하수는
sewage is
sewage
통과할 수 없을 거야 거긴 저크가득실 되거든 바로 잡아먹힐걸 특히 너
will pass can will not be will pass there will be Full of jerks  right away you'll be eaten especially you
You won't be able to get through it, if it's full of jerks, you'll be eaten right away, especially you
말이야 꼬마는 많은 자들이 과거에도전했었어 다들 끝이 좋지 않았지
I mean kid is lots of guys challenged in the past everyone the end good didn't
I mean, a lot of kids have tried in the past, everyone didn’t end well
어쨌든 너의 일은 내 일이 아니니까야 그 벙거지 뭐 더 줘봐 어 마음에
anyway your things my things Because no that stupid what more give me uh like
Anyway, your job isn't mine. Give me something more.
드네
Dne
come
거의 아버지인 떡은 훌륭한 과학자였어저칼을 상대할 새로운 무기를 개발하고
almost father tteok great was a scientist deal with new @@W7 weapons] develop
Rice cake, almost the father, was a brilliant scientist, developing new weapons to counter the knife.
있었지 몇 년 전에 그가 무기를시험하러 갔는데 다시 돌아오지 않았어
was few years before he weapons To test went again never came back didn't
Yes, years ago he went to test weapons and never came back.
무기 얘기 아까 보긴 했었어 그치집에서
weapon talk earlier saw did that's right At home
I saw the weapon story before, but at home
제 말 듣지만 나처럼 겁을 먹은 거야딱이 떡이 무기를 만들었다면 우리는
my say listen but like me scare ate it's perfect rice cake weapon if you made it we
Listen to me, but you're scared like me.
아웃사이더와 합류 가능해노트에서
outsider and joining @@W2 in the possible note]
It is possible to join the outsider in the notebook
덕은 비밀 연구실을 몇 번 언급했어그거 작업했을 거예요
Virtue Secret Lab Few times I mentioned that would have worked would have
Duck mentioned the secret lab a few times. He must have worked on that.
[음악]이거 어떻게 하지 어
[Music] this how not uh
[Music] How do you do this uh
[음악]얜 누구야
[MUSIC] That's who is
[Music] Who is he?
야[음악]
Hey [Music]
hey [music]
쓰레기통에 버려진 훌륭한 물건들을보라고 보물이 잔뜩 있어
trash bin abandoned great look at stuff treasure [ A bunch of W5@@ [There's W6@@
There's a lot of treasure to look at the great stuff that was dumped in the trash.
물물교환자를 방문해 봐아니
barter visit look no
Visit the barter. No
근데 고양이가 좀훔치기도 하고 해야지 어
but the cat stealing and should uh
But the cat steals a little and has to do it uh
아까 훔치긴 했지만
@@W0 earlier] stole but
I stole it earlier
이거 어디다 쓰는 거지
this is where writes is
Where are you writing this?
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
분위기를 더해줄 기타 연주에 대한악보를
mood add guitar play sheet music
Sheet music for guitar playing to add atmosphere
필요한 악보를 찾고 있음 찾아오면찾아오면
needed sheet music looking found found
I am looking for the sheet music I need. When I find it, when I find it
찾으면 가져오도록엘리베이터 근처에 살고 있어 아 얘가
find bring the elevator near live got Ah this is
If you find it, bring it to me. I live near the elevator.
이제 악보
now sheet music
sheet music now
너 아버지가 우리를 도우려했단 말이야
you my father us tried to help I mean
I mean your dad tried to help us
예상을 했어이 상황은싱어스한테 아주 힘든 일이니까 더
I expected I did this The situation is for singers Very Tough because more
I expected this situation to be more difficult because it is very difficult for the Singers.
이상 아웃사이더에 대해듣고 싶어 하지 않더라고 나를
more than outsider hear about wanna not I didn't say me
Even if you don't want to hear about the outsider anymore
도와주지 않겠지만 너라면 좋은 생각이있어
I'll help I wouldn't, but if it were you good I have an idea
I won't help but you have a good idea
어디 들어갈길이 있나 보네
Where Way to go  I see
I see a way in
노트를 가져가서쟤한테 보여 줘
note take it to him show give it
Take the note and show it to him
시몬스터한테 보여줘
@@W0 to Simonster] Show me
show it to simmonster
[음악]그래 그래 좀 이따 보자
[Music] Yes Yes Some Later See you
[Music] Yeah yeah see you later
얘구나 맞지 아까 얘 아 맞네 얘였지가래 여기서 뭐 해 내가 말했지
Hey That's right Earlier Hey Ah That's right said it was him here what do I said
Hey, that’s right, he said earlier, hey, hey, that’s right, he said, what are you doing here?
하수를 통과하는 거 자살이나마찬가지라고 날 내버려도
sewage pass through go through go through suicide me Even if I leave it alone
Even if you leave me alone saying that going through the sewer is like suicide
야아이템 보여줄게
Hey item I'll show you
Hey, I'll show you the item
아빠의 물건인가우와 전에 몰랐어 우리 아파트에
Daddy's stuff before didn't know we to the apartment
Is it Daddy's thing? Wow, I didn't know it before. In our apartment.
비밀방이 있었어 대체 어디에이제 알았지 가져와
secret room was there Substitute where now okay bring it
There was a secret room, now I know where it is, bring it
길 안내비밀 연구실이 바로 내 앞에 있었다니
Road Secret Lab Right My before was there
The secret laboratory for directions was right in front of me.
여기 어디인가에 단사가 숨겨져 있는것은 아닐까 내가 찾아야 돼
here somewhere injective hidden is [ Maybe W5@@ I find can
Maybe the single thread is hidden somewhere here, I need to find it
뭐야아 이런 식으로 찾는 건가 보다 맞지
What is like this like looking for is than right
What is it?
어단서 있다
clue there is
there is a clue
시간이 많을 것이다 시계다답은 시계다 저거다
time is is a lot will be clock is is clock [ W5@@ That's it
There will be plenty of time. The answer to a clock is a clock. That's it.
여기도 뭐 있지 않을까
here too what there maybe
what could be here
어 나이스키패드도 있어
uh Nice Skipad there
Oh, there's also a nice ski pad
시간을 입력하는 거구나2시네 2시
time typing that's 2 o'clock 2 o'clock
You're entering the time. It's 2 o'clock. It's 2 o'clock.
[음악]비밀번호가 뭔지 전혀 모르겠어 내가
[MUSIC] The password is what at all I don't know I
[Music] I have no idea what a password is
풀어줄게 자 2시면 뭐야 1400오케이
I'll let you go now 2 o'clock what is it 1400 ok
I'll let you go, what's up at 2 o'clock
1 2511 25112511 2511
[음악]이런 방을 본 적이 없어 아빠가
[Music] Gee Room Saw Never Not [ W5@@ My father
[Music] I've never seen a room like this
그동안 나한테서 이걸 숨길 수있었다니 믿을 수가 없어 이건 아빠의
In the meantime from me this hide could you Unbelievable count no this is dad's
I can't believe you were able to hide this from me all this time.
저크 무기에 설계도야 아빠는 항상일을 비밀스럽게 진행했거든
Jerk Weapons Blueprints Dad Always Working secretly proceeded
Blueprints for jerk weapons. My dad always kept things secret.
무기가 이런 상황으로는작동하지만 실제 시험이 필요하다고
weapon is this works but real tests required
The weapon works in this situation, but needs real testing.
했어 그리고 돌아오지 않았지
did and didn't come back didn't
I did and never came back
무기 빨리 줘봐 내가 다 죽여줄게그 쓰레기 같은 젤리들 죽여야지
Weapon Quickly Give Me I Everything Kill Julgeug Garbage Same Jellies Gotta kill
Give me your weapon quickly, I'll kill them all. I have to kill those trashy jellies.
내려가도 좀 어 여기도 번역하겠네
Even if you go down A bit Uh Here too I'll translate
If you go down, I'll translate here too
저크는 공식적으로 더 이상 통제해볼까이젠 금속까지 먹어 치우는 지경
jerk is officially more more than control now [ W5@@ up to metal Eat Eliminate Jigyeong
Jerks officially out of control Now they're eating metal
[음악]여기에서
[MUSIC] @@W0 here]
[Music] From here
뭔가 흥미로운 걸 찾았어[음악]
Something Interesting Something Found [Music]
Found something interesting [Music]
아니 아직 못 찾았어어디 있을까
no not yet not found where is
No, I haven't found it yet. Where is it?
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아 귀엽게 들리지만 결코 우호적이지않다
ah cute sounds like never not friendly
Ah, it sounds cute, but it's never friendly.
인류 시대에 오래된 박탈이야 모든종류의 물질을 먹는다 어둠 속에서
humanity age old deprivation all sorts of [ W5@@ Matter Eat Darkness in
Old deprivation in the age of mankind. Eats all kinds of substances. In the dark.
완전한 시야를 가지고 있다 강한 빛의반응한다
complete field of view have have strong Responds to light
Has full vision Responds to strong light
강한 빛의 반응한데[음악]
Strong Light reacted [Music]
Responding to strong light [music]
어 그냥 눈뽕 하면 되는 거야 나이제까지
uh just blind  becomes  age limit
Uh, it’s just a matter of blindfolding, even at my age
야
Hey
hey
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아이템이 없으면 얘기도 안 해주겠다뭐 이런 건가
item is if not can't even talk won't I'll do it for you [ W5@@ like this [Is that W6@@
I won't even talk to you if you don't have an item. What is this?
이거다답은 이거다
This is the answer This is the
this is the answer
뭐 없나
What [Is there any W1@@
is there anything
뭐 없는 거임
what [@@W1 without W1@@] is
what's missing
아 빈통이었네 어책상 아래가 아니었고
Ah It was empty The desk is below wasn't
Oh, it was empty, it wasn’t under the desk
없는데 친구야 왜
doesn't exist he's my friend why
no friend why
아 저 위에 것도 없애야 되나 이거
Ah That on  should be removed  this
Oh, should I get rid of the top one too?
어 있다 안에 있어 안에 있어
uh in in in in in
I am in, I am in
고장난 추적기
Broken Tracker
broken tracker
야 나 사 왔어야
ya me ya should have been
hey i should have bought it
얘기하자응 찾았어
Let's talk [I found W1@@
Let's talk. I found it.
이거
this
참고 그거 기억 나빠요 추적기잖아아빠는 항상 그 추적기를 사용해서
Note That Remember It's bad It's a tracker, Dad is always that tracker using
FYI I don't remember that. It's a tracker. My dad always uses that tracker.
내가 어디에 있는지 살펴봤어 그것을여기 이용하면 아빠가 어디로 갔는지
I where  I looked at it here If you use Dad Where went
I took a look at where my dad went if he used it here
너무 보고 싶어 아빠가
too see wanna Daddy
I miss you so much Dad
[음악]오케이 이거 수리하면 된대
[Music] ok this repair done
[Music] Okay, they said you can fix this
근데 가는데 아빠 시체만 있을 듯그리고 거기서 무기만 챙기는 거지
but I'm going dad corpse only there And then there weapons only carrying beggar
But when I go, there seems to be only my father's corpse, and I'm only taking weapons there.
미안하지만친구야 어쩔 수 없다 이제 게임 많이
I'm sorry, but I'm a friend What can I do can no now Game a lot
I'm sorry but friend, I can't help it. Now I play a lot
잤네 나 게임이지 않니응
I slept I It's a game Isn't it
I slept, isn't it a game
돌아올 수 있으면 진작에 돌아오지않았겠어 친구야 미안하다
will come back can if there is long ago would not have come back [ W5@@ My friend Sorry
If I could come back, I wouldn't have come back a long time ago, my friend, I'm sorry
냉정은
Calmness
calmness
아마 너의 솜씨라면 아마 더워줄 자를찾을 수 있을 거야
Maybe Your If you're good at it Maybe It's hotter @W5 find be be be
Maybe with your skill, you can find someone to warm you up
그래아 이거 화가 많이 나셨네
Yes This Angry A lot You got it
Yeah, this made me very angry.
이거를 수리해줄만한 사람이라
@@W0 this] can fix it people
Someone who can fix this
나는 식물 돌보는 일을 해 인간들이식물을 많이 개당했어 이제는 아주
I Plant Caring Work Do Humans planted a lot got 1 now very
I took care of the plants, so humans took a lot of plants, now it's very
적은 빛만 있어도 돼물을 조금만 더 해도 엄청나게 커지지
little only light even little little More but so much it gets bigger
Even a little bit of light makes it huge
정말 굉장히 기술이야
really very technology
it's really very technical
트 엘리어트엘리엇이라는 로봇이 있어 그가 도와줄
Eliot Robot Got He to help
There's a robot named Elliot who can help him.
수 있을 거야엘리엇이 어딨지 엘리엇
be be be Elliott where is Elliott
You can do it. Where is Elliot, Elliot?
엘리엇
Elliott
노래가 없어
no song no
no song
악보 보여주면 되나 이거 악보보여줘도 돼
Sheet Music Show me Can I This Show me the sheet OK
Can I show you the sheet music? Can I show you the sheet music for this?
킹 잡건 안 걸려 막 이게 걸었는데막
King Miscellaneous Not Hang Just This is it just walked
It won't take the king, I just bet this
노란 딱지 붙는 거 아니지악보 해도 돼
Yellow Tag Attached Thing Notation Even if can do
You don't get a yellow label, you can score
다 들어봐도 되는 거임안 걸려 확실해
everything listen become I’m not going to caught sure
It's okay to listen to everything, I'm sure it won't get caught
약간 중요한 정보 이것은 유명한알고리즘이 작곡한 거야
little important info this is famous algorithm Composed by by
Some important information This is composed by the famous algorithm
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]아 로테이션 돌았다
[Music] Ah rotated rotated
[Music] Oh, it rotated
스타피 스타필 다른 노래이 양반아짧으면 잠을 잘 수 있겠어
Starfie Starfeel Another Songyi Short [ W5@@ sleep well be stay
Staphy Stafil Another song, man, I can sleep if it's short
노이로제 걸리지 어[음악]
Neurosis Caught Uh [Music]
I'm getting neurotic [music]
야 로봇아취했나
Hey Are you crazy about robots
Hey, are you a robot?
그만그래
That's right
stop it
다른 것도 들어야 된단 말이야
else also should listen should be
I need to hear something else
어 악보 고마워 연습할게그래
uh Score Thank you I'll practice
Uh thanks for the sheet music I'll practice
그럼 이건가 맞아이거들은 건네준거야 아니면 남아 있는
Then Is this Yes, these are I gave you or [ W5@@ remains remains
Then this is right Are these handed over or remaining
거야 아까 몇 번째도 악보 들어왔지이거 한번 해볼까 오늘 밤 너가
that's earlier a few th sheet music I came in once should I try today night you
I've been listening to sheet music several times before. Let's try this. Tonight you
계산하는 방식멋진데 뜯어봐
calculates method is cool try it
The way it counts is cool, try it
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
이거 살짝 어 나비 보배따우 저격한거구만
this a little bit uh butterfly baby You shot me
This is a little bit like a butterfly.
자 그 다음에 또다른 거 돌려줘
now that then another that give it back
Well then give me another one
연습할게
I'll practice
건네주는 거였구나
handing over was it
It was handed over
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어 노래 괜찮은데 이거[음악]
uh song ok this [music]
Uh, the song is good, but this [music]
오예오콜 대우
Ohyeohcall Daewoo
Oh yeah call Daewoo
콜 대우
call treat
call treatment
콜 대우[음악]
Call Daewoo [Music]
call treatment [music]
멜로디 괜찮다 그렇지[음악]
Melody OK That's right [Music]
Melody is fine, right [music]
이게 제일 좋다쿨다운
this is best cool down
this is the best cooldown
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]아주 좋았어
[Music] Very Nice
[Music] It was great
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
이제 없어
now no
not anymore
개이득두 개만 더 찾으면 아까 이제 그거
two only more find earlier now that
If you find two more gains, that's it
가능곳곳에 있나 본데
wherever possible is there seen
I've seen it everywhere
참 이런데 안 해도 막 들어 있는 거아니야
true like this not even just heard is is not
It's like this, but even if you don't do it, you're just listening to it
아 이러면 큰일 나는데 이거 방향감각이 바뀌어버려서
Ah This is Big deal I'm this direction My senses changed
Oh, it would be a big deal if I do this, but my sense of direction has changed
컨트롤하기 힘들단 말이야 아잠깐만요
Control It's hard I mean Wait a minute
It's hard to control, wait a minute
앞으로 봐봐앞으로 봐 빨리
look forward look forward look quickly
Look forward, look forward, quickly
물어봐어 뭐야
Ask What is
ask me what
금고에 기묘한 비밀번호 없기
@@W0 in safe] weird password no
No weird passwords for safes
숫자를 따라가라라고 쓰였지만 영과1로 이루어진 이진법으로 보여
number follow was written zero and 1 made up of @@W5 in binary] show
It says follow the numbers, but it looks like a binary system consisting of zeros and ones.
이 코드를 어떤 식으로든 해독해야아마도이 금고와 관련해 있을 거예요
any should decode maybe this [ W5@@ safe and related would be would be
I need to crack this code somehow. It's probably related to this safe.
[음악]숫자를 따라가나
[Music] Numbers Follow
[Music] Follow the numbers
아 이거 무조건 열고 싶다 그치열고 싶어
ah this unconditionally open want that’s right Open wanna
Ah, I want to open this unconditionally, I really want to open it
숫자를 따라가라
number Follow
follow the numbers
이렇게 뭘까
like this what is it
what is this
쩐을 더 나가라
More Get out
go out for more money
어디 단서가 숫자가 어디 있나
where clue number where
where is the clue where are the numbers
저크의 확산으로 인해 하수도는 접근이금지되었습니다
jerk spread caused sewer access denied
Sewers are off-limits due to Jerk's spread
여기가 하수도 들어가는 입구인가 보다맞지
this is sewer entrance entrance is more correct
I guess this is the entrance to the sewer.
옆에 숫자 이런 거 말하는 거야 이런거 아닌 거 같아 이것저것
next to number oh thing talking It's like this not like like this and that
I'm talking about the number next to it. I don't think it's like this.
숫자를 따라와라숫자를 따라가라
follow the number follow the number follow the number
follow the numbers follow the numbers
쩔을 따라가라
Dopeul Follow me
follow the shit
어디 막 가다 보면 뭐가 나오지않을까
where just go see what come out Maybe
Wherever you go, what won't come out?
이건 뭐야
This is What is
What's this
이것도 메모리인가 보다
Is this also memory than
I guess this is memory too
굉장히 캠페니온은 많이 진화했어초기에는 그들의 단순한 ai가 인간의
very campenion is a lot evolved @@W3 in the beginning] their simple ai human
Very Campenion has evolved a lot. In the early days, their simple ai was human
예술을 모방했을 뿐이었어 이젠그들만의 예술 세계가 있지
Art imitated was only now their own Art world is is
They just imitated art, now they have their own art world
인간은 절박한 상황에서 예수를 만드는것이 중요하다고 종종 말했어 지금이
Human Desperate situation Jesus making [ W5@@ It's important often said now
Humans have often said that it is important to make Jesus in a desperate situation.
바로 그 절박한 시기예요
right that desperate it's time
It's that desperate time
메모리 복구했음
Memory Recovered
memory was restored
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
일단은
for now
얘도 아니고
this one too not
Not even him
너였냐얘도 아니고 왜 이렇게 기운이 없어
Was it you? not Why like this cheery [ W5@@ no
Was it you? It wasn't him. Why are you so low?
보여요내 친구가 나는 서로한테 양동일
I see you my friend I am to each other Dongil Yang
You see, my friend and I are diversionary to each other
던지는 거 좋아해 깔끔한 재미가 있지
throwing stuff likes neat fun ITZY
I like to throw, it's a neat fun
야 뭐냐 너 그냥 노는 거였어일하는게 아니라
hey what is it you just playing was it Working not
Hey, what is it? You were just playing, not working.
그러니까 민폐지
So Abolished
So it's a wasteland
난 또 무슨 뭐 작업하는 줄 알았네
i also what what working line ok
I thought I was working on something else
어트
Ert
att
프로그래밍 여기로 가는 거 아님프로그래밍 얘잖아 생각해 보니까
programming here going going not programming That's it [Think of W6@@ see
Programming I'm not going here. It's programming. Come to think of it.
너 춥네추워 보인다
You It's cold, it's cold I see
you look cold
맞지 아니
right no
덜덜 떠는 중
trembling trembling mid
shaking
어디로 가야 되지 저 표지판 따라서가면은
where go not that signs therefore The mask is
Where should I go, if I follow that sign
잠깐만
Wait a minute
wait for a sec
[음악]여기 왜 오른쪽에 있다고 나오는데
[Music] Here Why Right says appears
[Music] Why does it say it's on the right?
건너서 오른쪽에도 길 있나
across to the right road there
Is there a road to the right after crossing it?
여긴 아닌 거 같아 위쪽인가
This is is not is looks like is above
I don't think it's here, is it upstairs?
여길려나[음악]
I wonder if this is the case [Music]
Let's go [Music]
어 여기 설마 여기어 스탑 나이스
uh here no way here stop nice
Oh no way here stop nice
돈 하나 더 얻은
Don One More Got
got more money
개이득하나만 더 찾으면 고대 유물 얻을 수
Only one gain More Find Ancient Artifact get [w6@@ be
If you find one more gain, you can get an ancient artifact.
있어
is
there is
인류의 명복을 빕니다인류는이 지역의 첫 번째 거주자였어
Humanity Blessings Humankind Region First th was a resident
Humanity was the first inhabitant of this area.
지금 모두 죽은 거 같지만죽는다는 거 어떤 기분일까 내가 이런
now all dead almost same but dying that what feel like I like this
It seems like everyone is dead right now, but how does it feel to die?
말을 하는게우습겠지만 그들은 정말 평화를
say would be funny they really peace
It's funny to say, but they really make peace
찾았을까 내가죽으면 평안해질까 aia에게 죽음이란
Did you find it If I die Will it be peaceful to aia What is death
Did I find it? If I die, will it be peaceful? What death means to aia?
어떤 느낌인지 모르겠어미안해 기분을 망치고 싶지 않았는데
What kind of feels like I don't know, I'm sorry the mood ruined I don't want I didn't
I don't know what it feels like. I'm sorry, I didn't want to ruin your mood.
계속하자콘센트 빼줄게 올라 배터리 빼줄게
Let's go on. Outlet Unplug Up Battery Unplug
Let's continue.
일로 와그다음 다시 끼워주면 죽음을 느낄 수
work and then again insert death feel can
Come back to work and then put it back in and you'll feel death
있을 거 아니야[음악]
be be no [music]
It won't be [Music]
어디지 근데 그거 찾아야 되는데
where is but that find should be
Where is it? I need to find it.
[음악]할머니한테 물어보자고
[Music] Grandma Let's ask
[Music] Let's ask grandma
그래 노련한 할머니한테 물어보자
Yes Experienced Grandma Let's ask
Okay, let's ask the old granny
자극 마우스처럼 전자제품을 다루거든바로 저기에 살고 있어 어
Stimulus Like a mouse Electronics I'm dealing with over there live live uh
I treat electronics like a stimuli mouse. I live right there.
어디
where
여기에 살고 있다고어디에
is here lives is where
I live here
담요 덮었네 옆에
blanket covered [next to W2@@
Covered with a blanket next to me
아
ah
여기어쩐지 여기 갔더라니
Somehow here Here I heard you went
Somehow I went here
아니 근데 왜 할머니손 가르치는 곳이 왜 낚시한 거지
No But Why Grandmother Teaching Where is Why Fishing Beggar
No, but why is the place that teaches grandma's hands fishing?
괜히 여기다 이거이 방향인 줄 알았네어
for nothing here this is direction line Okay
For nothing, I thought this was the direction
[음악]너냐 아
[Music] Is that you ah
[Music] Is it you?
찾기 힘든 곳에 살고 있네 이거 왜안 떠
find hard where live there this Why not
I live in a place that is hard to find
대화하기 왜 안 되냐
Talking Why Not
why can't we talk
야
Hey
hey
안눌러지잖아
You can't press
야[음악]
Hey [Music]
hey [music]
임마들어가자
dude, let's go in
dude let's go
우리는 노예로 프로그래밍 되었지만많은 세월이 지난 후 우리는 영혼을
We as slaves programming but many years [ W5@@ last after we soul
We were programmed to be slaves, but after many years we lost our souls
가지게 됐다 언젠가이언젠가 아웃사이더들이이 지옥의 출구를
have it got it someday someday these outsiders hell [ W5@@ exit
Someday, someday, outsiders will find an exit from this hell
줄 수 있기를 바란다 뭐 뭐
give be wish wish what what
I wish I could give you what what
아 저기 있어 그래 그럼 건방지 자고있네 문지기인가 봐
ah there there yes then Prevent Sleeping Is the gatekeeper Look
Oh, there you are. Then you're cheeky.
여기 왜 올라오게 된거임
Here Why Come up It's done
why did you come up here
고양이라서 그런 건가
Because it's a cat that's is it
Is it because it's a cat?
아니 뭔가 훔칠 만한게 없네
no something steal nothing nothing
no, there's nothing to steal
이래도 안 일어나네
not wake up
It doesn't even happen
너냐 프로그래밍 하는 놈
you programming doing bastard
Are you a programming guy?
응 뭘 도와줄까 이거어 우와 좋은 추적기잖아이 모델 알아
Yes What Can I help you This is Whoa nice tracker model know
Yeah, what can I help you with? Wow, that's a good tracker. I know this model.
br2000이 작은 장치도 누구든지추적할 수 있지 좀 봐도 될까요
br2000 small device also whoever @@W3 can track]   a bit
Anyone can track a device this small as 2000. Can I have a look?
이렇게 떨고 있으면 키보드 쓸 수없어 내가 아픈지 아닌지 모르겠지만
like this shaking if keyboard write be No I'm I'm sick or not I don't know
If I'm shaking like this, I can't use the keyboard. I don't know if I'm sick or not.
확실히 좋은 느낌은 아니야야 담요 담요 이거 이거네
definitely good feels like nope blanket blanket this this
Definitely not a good feeling Blanket Blanket This is this
이 자식한테 하는 거였구나
doing was it
You did it for this kid.
추웠냐어
Was it cold
was it cold
그래 그래
Yes Yes
yes yes
창백해 보여요 이거 한잔할래
Pale I can see This I want a drink
You look pale. Would you like a drink of this?
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
이 나무는 놀라운 과학적 현상이야인간의 독창석도
This Tree Amazing Scientific Phenomenon Human [ W5@@ Dok Chang-seok also
This tree is an amazing scientific phenomenon. Human ingenuity is also
인간의 독창석동창
Human Dok Chang Seok alumni
Human's unique stone alumni
동창성 독창성 독창성인간의 독창성이
Alumni Originality Originality Human Originality
Alumniness Originality Originality Human originality
햇빛 없이도 식물이 잘 자라는 방법을발견했다는게 놀랍지
sunlight without plants well growing Found a way I'm surprised
It's amazing how plants can grow without sunlight.
유기체를 위해서는 도시의 공기를정화하는 나무가 필요해
organism  city purify the air trees [I need W5@@
Organisms need trees to purify the city air
로봇에게는 필요하지 않지만 어쨌든 덜보고 있지
@@W0 for robots] don't need but anyway look less Hey
Robots don't need it, but they're looking less anyway
인간들이 그러길 원했을 거야창성 독창성 독창성
Humans I hope wanted I'm going to create Originality Originality
Humans would have wanted that. Creativity originality originality
독창성
originality
왜 이렇게 뭐지 왜 이렇게 순간발음이 얼었지
why like this what why like this moment pronounced frozen
Why is it like this, why is my pronunciation so frozen?
동창성
Alumni
alumni
여기도 뭐 있나
Here too What is there
what is here
없나 보네 야 이거발톱 스크래치 난 거
Is there any I see Hey This claw Scratch I'm is
It looks like there is none.
가자
let's go
나가야 될 거 아니야
Go Become Go No
you don't have to go out
열어 줘
Open Give
open it
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
이제 됐고 그 다음에
now done that then
now and then
아 이거 하나만 더 찾으면 지금 유물먼저 할 수 있을 것 같은데
ah this only one more find now relic first do be be be looks like
Ah, if I find one more of these, I think I can do the artifact first.
맞지 노래 먼저 들으러 갈까 그래노래만 더 듣자 노래 듣는 데가
Right Song First To listen Shall we go Yes Only song more listen song listen dega
That’s right, shall we go listen to the song first? Yes, let’s just listen to the song more.
[음악]그 저기 누구한테 줘야 되는 거
[Music] That over there to whom should be given being [ W5@@ Geo
[Music] I have to give it to someone over there
아닌가
isn't it
is not it
무제
Untitled
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
뭐 하냐
what do
what are you doing
[음악]맞냐 이거
[Music] Is that right This
[MUSIC] Is this right?
어[음악]
uh[music]
uh [music]
이게 맞아
This is That's right
Is this right
어 연습 좀 해어
uh practice uh uh
uh do some practice
연습 좀 해라 인마 어기대하는 마음에 좀 들고 갔더니
Practice Do it Do it Dude Overbearing I like kinda carrying went
Do some practice.
이 쓰레기 같은 녀석어
this crap like bastard
this piece of trash
나 한 바퀴돌아보면서 자판기 하나만 더 찾아버려
or one turning around vending machine one More [Find W6@@
I look around and find one more vending machine
자판기 자판기 자판기 자판기 자판기자판기가
vending machine vending machine vending machine vending machine vending machine
자판기
vending machine
자판기가져왔다
I brought the vending machine
I brought a vending machine
진행될 것 같은데잠깐만 진행되기 전에
going on going on like wait a minute going on before
I think it's going to go ahead, wait a minute before it goes on
자판기 좀 쳐다봐야 되겠어[음악]
vending machine little bit I have to look at will be [Music]
Gotta look at the vending machine [Music]
맛조개도
Flavor clams
Flavor clams too
자판기 예야 꺼져봐
vending machine yea go away
Turn off the vending machine
[음악]여기 위에 한번 올라가볼까 건물
[Music] Here on top once Let's go up building
[Music] Shall we go up here? Building
위쪽에는 자판기탑 뭐 하긴 했거든요 잠깐만
Above is Vending Machine Tower What Actually I did Wait a minute
There's a vending machine upstairs. I did something. Wait a minute.
정말 이걸 먹나 그들의 원래 설계는소화기가 없어
really this eat their originally designed There is no fire extinguisher is not there
Do they really eat this? Their original design has no fire extinguisher.
인간은 모방해서 어떻게든 진화한 건가나도 시도해볼까 그들의 방식을
Humans are imitate somehow evolved or something let's try their method
Did humans somehow evolve by imitating them? Should I try their way?
존중하고 싶어뭐
Respect What do you want
What do you want to respect
뭔데 이거
What is This is
what is this
아 뭐야 이거 무슨 뭐 커피 아생각해보니까 얘네들 뭐 이렇게 뭐지
Ah What This What What Coffee Come to think of it these guys what like this what
Ah what is this what what coffee
기름 밖에 뭐 하지 않나 주의 못하는거 아니야 이거 뭐 차로 만든 건가
oil outside what not isn’t it be careful can't do it no this what car made by made by
It doesn't do anything but oil. It's not that you can't pay attention. Is this made of tea?
어딜 가나 이런게 있네
Where Ghana Something like this is there
There's something like this everywhere
어 이게 뭐 있다어 악보 있다 나이스
uh this is what there sheet music There is Nice
Uh what is this, there is sheet music, nice
이건 저 위에 레벨 2에 사는 이들의신문이야 몇 년이 지났지만 읽을 만해
this that on level 2 I live these are their newspapers how many years have passed has passed Read Manhae
This is the newspaper of the people who live on level 2 up there. It's been a few years, but it's worth reading.
너 혹시 고양이 아주 자유로운 뭐지
you maybe cat very free what
Are you a cat, very free?
그럼 위로 가서 자판기 한번만
then up go vending machine only once
Then go upstairs and vending machine once
해보자 있을지도 모르니까
Let's try Might be I don't know
Let's do it, maybe
어 뭐야 너
uh what you
uh what are you
이 불쌍한 녀석도 위로 올라가고 싶어했나봐
this poor guy up up I must have wanted it
I guess this poor guy wanted to go up too
그래 기억나슬럼의 모든 쓰레기와 질병에서 멀리
yes @@W1 of the slums] all crap and disease away
Yeah I remember Away from all the crap and disease in the slums
떨어진 저 위쪽에 미드타운이 있어
Fell That Up Midtown Got
Down there is Midtown
끔찍한 시대에도 인간들은 스스로를사회의 계급으로 나눴어
Terrible [Even in the era of W1@@ Humans are themselves in society class split
Even in terrible times, humans divided themselves into social classes.
당시 대다수의 슬럼 주민들은 이곳에서벗어나 위로 올라가기 위해 무엇이나
@@W0 at the time] majority of slum residents get out of here [ W5@@ up up up whatever
At the time, most slum dwellers would do anything to get out of here and upward.
할 준비가 되어 있었지로봇들도이 행동을 복사한 것 같아
do ready be be robots action copied would be would be like
Ready to do it. I think the robots also copied this behavior.
어디 있는 거야 자판기일단 나의 심신 안정을 위해서 악보
where is is vending machine once my Mind and Body Stability For Sheet Music
Where is the vending machine, for the sake of my peace of mind and body
찾은 거 한번 들려주자
Found Something Once Let's hear it
Let's hear what you find
내일은 안 할
tomorrow is not do
not tomorrow
것도[음악]
Also [Music]
Also [music]
괜찮은데
It's okay
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
빠 옆에 자판기 기대고 있는 로봇비키게 하고 뽑아보세요
sucker next to vending machine leaning on Get out of the way of the robot and [Choose W7@@
Get out of the way of the robot leaning on the vending machine next to the bar.
뇌피셜이야 아니면 뭐야[음악]
Brainficial or What is it [Music]
Is it brainficial or what? [Music]
연습할게
I'll practice
꺼져[음악]
Get off [Music]
get off [music]
안 꺼지는데
not turns off
won't turn off
여기 맞아여기 상자 올라가라고 여기서 상자
here right here box go up here box
That's right here. Box here. Go up. Box here.
올라가 이거
go up this
뭐냐 이거 여기야와
What is it This is Here it is
what is this here
야 이거 위에서도 잘 안 보이게막혀져 있네
hey this above well not look Blocked there
Hey, it's blocked so you can't see it from above
이거 좀 사자 이거밖에 안 남은 거지그래
this little lion only this not Remaining That's right
Let's buy this, this is the only thing left, right?
내가 3
i 3
아 그냥 메모리구나맞지
Ah It's just It's memory, right
Oh, it's just a memory, right?
가치가 있기를이건 캠페니언의 초기 모델이야 그땐
worth this is campaign initial model then
For what it's worth, this is an early model of the campaign, then
인격도 없었고 자동 청소 로봇일뿐이었지
No personality didn't exist Automatic Cleaning It was just a robot
He had no personality and was just an automatic cleaning robot.
결과적으로 보자면 인간의 흉내를 낸건 잘했다고 생각해 이들은 인간을
As a result see human imitate what well done think these are humans
As a result, I think they did a good job of imitating humans.
그리워했던 것 같아 어떤 면에서 보면보자면 그래서 멸종되지 않았던 거
missed thing like which in terms of If you look at it so not extinct didn't that
I think I missed it. In some ways, that's why it didn't become extinct.
착한 로봇들이야
Kind Robots
they are good robots
인격을 갖기 전에 그냥 로봇그냥 이제 메모리 중에 하나였나
personality have before just robot just Now memory out of was one
Was it just a robot before it had a personality, or was it just one of the memories?
보네요 메모리 중에 하나이제 그러면
I see memory during one now then
I see one of the memories now then
어 수리했어 자
uh repaired uh
oh i fixed it
이제 여기 마을 퀘스트는 다 깬 거같은데 맞지 뭐 다
Now Here Village Quest Everything Awake [Looks like W6@@ right what everything
I think I've completed all the town quests here, but that's right.
했고[음악]
did [music]
아 금고 안 했네 금고 금고는 뭐지금고 단서 핑이 잡혔어
Ah Safe Not Did Safe Safe is whatsoever clue ping got
Oh, I didn't do the safe.
압박 정말 살아있는 거야 믿을 수없어 따라가자
pressure really alive going unbelievable be No Let's follow
The pressure is really alive, I can't believe it, let's follow it
아 이거 진짜진행은 맞네
Ah This is The real progress is That's right
Oh, this is true
금고 단서 아는 사람 금고 빨리 열게어 가기 전에 빨리 금고 제끼고 가게
vault clue know person vault fast Open Go Before Quickly Vault Skip Shop
Someone who knows the clue to the safe, open it quickly. Skip the safe before leaving.
금고 숫자를 따라가는게 뭔 말이야금고 숫자를 따라가라는게 뭔 말이지
safe numbers follow what you mean safe the numbers follow what you mean
What does it mean to follow the number of the safe? What does it mean to follow the number of the safe?
숫자를 따라가라[음악]
numbers Follow [Music]
follow the numbers [music]
고양이 지나갈 때만 궁시렁대는
cat passing by [Only when W2@@ moaning
Only grumbles when a cat passes by
빠 액자 치우면 비번 있어빠
Dad Frame Get rid of Off Stay Dad
Bar, if you clear the frame, you have an off-duty bar
야 어이 잠깐만금방 갈게
Hey Hey Wait a minute I'll be there
Hey hey wait a minute I'll be there soon
이건가는 아니고[음악]
This is going not [Music]
It's Not Going [Music]
이건가보다 이거 이거 이거 이거 이거이거
This is more than This is This is This is This is This is this
This one this this this this this this this
다1283
Da1283
da1283
1283[음악]
1283[Music]
근데 숫자를 따라가라는게뭔 단서였지
But the number Follow me was a clue
But follow the numbers was a clue
숫자가 뭔 의미야 숫자를 따라가라나맞지
number is what means number is Follow me right
What does the number mean? Follow the number, right?
숫자를 따라가라는게어디에 숫자가 있길래 숫자를
number follow where number  number
To follow the number, where is the number?
따라갔는데 저기로 안내하는 거임
followed over there guiding is
I've followed you, but you're guiding me there
전단지에 있었어[음악]
on flyer was there [MUSIC]
It was on the flyer [Music]
악보다[음악]
Music]
than evil [music]
악보야
sheet music
아 근데 좀 잠깐만 친구 이미 한참간 거 아니야 나 노래 듣고 가야
ah but a little bit wait a minute friend already for a while that no me song listen go
Oh but wait a minute friend, it's not been a while already
되는데읽을 수 없나
can read can can read
I can't read it
가독성은 좋지 않은데
readability is is not good is not
Readability is not good
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
뭔 어디서 많이 들어본 거 같은느낌이네
what where a lot heard what It feels the same
I feel like I've heard it a lot somewhere.
[음악]좋구만
[Music] Nice
[MUSIC] Nice
연습 열심히 해라
Practice Work hard Do
practice hard
근데 이제까지 악보 몇 개 줬지얘한테
but ever notation several pieces To him
But I gave him some sheet music so far.
정말로 슬럼을 나간 거야 가끔 위험한맞지만 확실히 알아야 해 난 알아야만
really go slum go out go sometimes It's dangerous, but definitely you should know do I'm you should know
I really left the slum. Sometimes it's dangerous, but I need to know for sure.
해 가보자고일단 가봐
do let's go go
Let's go, let's go at once
진행해야지 그렇지 너도 할만큼 다했을 듯 금보도 열고
Gotta go That's right You enough I've done seems like Geumbodo open
You have to proceed, as if you did your best, open up the gold report
[음악]뭔가 나무가 있다
[Music] Something there's a tree there's
[MUSIC] There's something in the tree
여기서 아빠의 흔적을 아빠의 위치를찾아야 돼
where dad's trace dad's locate ok
I have to find my father's traces and his location here.
눈치 없게 이제 야호 가기[음악]
Noticed No Now Yay Go [Music]
Go Yahoo now without notice [Music]
저크 알이 잔뜩 있잖아 우리 잡아먹고말 거야
Jerk Unknown A lot You know We Eat and eat is
There are a lot of jerk eggs, we will catch and eat them
난 못해 나는 느리거든 분명 척하기에잡히고 말 거예요이 뱃지 받아 우리
I'm I can't I'm I'm slow I'm sure Pretend to be caught say get this badge take we
I can't, I'm slow, I'm sure I'll get caught pretending, take this badge, let's
아빠가 보시면 내 친구라는 거 아실거예요 아웃사이더 배치 뭐 열어줄게
My dad is If you see My is my friend is You'll know Outsider Arrangement What I'll open
If dad sees it, he'll know he's my friend. I'll open the outsider batch.
아악보도 다 찾으면 배지죠
A score everything find badge
It's a badge if you find all the music scores.
나 지금 악보 몇 장 줬는지 어디서확인 가능해
Me Now Sheet Music Few Chapters Gave ji check where is possible
Where can I find out how many sheet music I gave you?
아
ah
[음악]스 나중에 또 올 수 있겠지 뭐
[music] s ya again come be There must be what
[Music] I think you can come back later
볼 수 있을 거야
see be be be
you can see
이 벽은 정말 거대하구나 기억나슬럼가 미드타운 사이에 분열이
This The wall is Really That's huge Remember me [ W5@@ Midtown Between Cleavage
I remember this wall is so huge.
상징이었어 그리고 그들이 여기로쓰레기를 계속 던졌다는 사실도
was a symbol and then they here trash continued [ W5@@ threw actually
It was a symbol and the fact that they kept throwing trash here
기억났어정말 끔찍한 짓이지 그래서
I remember really Terrible that shit so
I remembered, it was so terrible, so
실패했는지도 몰라
I don't even know if it failed I don't know
I may have failed
귀여운 고양이
Cute Cat
Cute cat
막다른 걸 뭐 여기 보니까 처크들이많이 있네요 만반의 준비를 해야겠는데
dead end gal what here see A lot of chucks there full prepare should be done
There are a lot of chucks when I look at the dead end. I need to be fully prepared.
어 저 그가 많아서 빨리화장실 금방 갔다 올게요 자 이제
uh that he too many quickly go to the bathroom Soon went I'll be back now now
Uh, there are a lot of him, so I’ll go to the bathroom soon. Now,
가보자갔다 왔구요
went and went came
let's go
[박수]형 좋지 않은 곳으로 내려간 것
[Applause] hyung no good not where went down [ W5@@ thing
[Applause] Hyung, going down to a bad place
같은데 아 잠깐 맞다아 여기 뭔가 스펙타클한 시간이 될
looks like ah wait that's right here something spectacular time is become
It's like, wait a minute, that's right. It's going to be a spectacular time for something here.
것 같은 느낌이랄까
like feel like
I wonder if it feels like
빠른 판단이 필요하겠네요 여기 뭔가
Quick Judgment I guess you need here something
You'll need to make a quick decision. Something here
어 개 많아무빙 무빙
uh ea moving moving
There are many moving moving moving
무빙 무빙 안 넘어가지 무빙 무빙무빙 무빙 무빙 무빙 무빙 무빙 무빙
moving moving not not going over moving Moving Moving Moving Moving Moving Moving Moving Moving
Moving moving moving I won’t fall over moving moving moving moving moving moving moving moving moving moving moving
무빙 가로랑
Moving Garolang
moving street
바로랑무빙 무빙 중간
Barorang Moving Moving Middle
어 좀 위험했다어 뭐지 여기 아랫길이야
uh kinda that was dangerous what here Down the street
Uh, it was a bit dangerous. What is it? It's down here.
왼쪽
left
넘어가고 넘어가고 올라가고그렇지
goes over goes over goes up like that
It goes over and over and goes up and that's it
휴 박스 했다 빡셌어
Phew box did was tough
Hugh box was tough
다시 한번 반동
again once recoil
recoil once again
이렇게 넘어가는 거 아닌가
like this goes beyond that isn’t it
Isn't it going like this
다시 반동
again recoil
rebound again
반동 시스템이구만
recoil system
It's a recoil system.
야 근데 고양이들은 진짜 이런 뭔가가좋은 거 같아 중심 잡는가 그렇지
hey but cats are really like this Something is good something like center catch right
Hey, but I think cats really like something like this.
어 꺼져 다뒤져라
uh go away search everything
Go away, look around
어 어 어 이런
uh uh uh uh
uh uh oh no
근데 은근히이 고향에 중심 잘 못잡는 거 같은데 떨어질 때
but softly home center well Can't catch that's looks like will fall when
But secretly, it seems that I can't center myself well in this hometown, but when I fall
근처에 있을 거야 다 왔어이렇게 딱 바닥에 딱 떨어질 때
is near will be will be all is here like this  on the floor just fall when
I'll be near you, it's all here, when you fall right on the floor like this
이렇게 착지져 원래 잘하는 동물아닌가
like this landed originally good at Isn't that an animal
Aren’t they originally good at landing like this?
착지를 잘 못하네 친구가아 또 뒷다리 아픈가 봐
landing well can't do it my friend again [ W5@@ Back leg Does it hurt Look
You can't land well, my friend, your back leg hurts again.
하트만 치료되나어 됐네 아주 나도 다쳤을 때
Heartman Healed Got it Very Me too wound when
Only the heart is healed, that's it, when I was hurt
고양이한테 핥아 달라 해야겠다 아니올라가야지
Cat Lick Different I have to No, I have to go up
I have to ask the cat to lick it. No, I have to go up.
여긴가
Is this place
여기도 뭐 있을 것 같아
Here too what would be would be would be like
I think there's something here too
쳐다보죠
look at
건너가는 길도 있고 건너가기 전에여기 먼저
crossing road and crossing before here [ W5@@ first
There is a road to cross, and before crossing, here first
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아이템 사요
item buy
buy an item
뭐 찾아서 이거 전력 같은 거복구시키는 건가 보네
what find this power same stuff Recovering Is that looks
It looks like you're looking for something and restoring something like power.
다른 부품이 필요할 것 같아 건너가서가져오는거다 바로 가자
different parts needed would be same I'm going to go and get it right away let's go
I think I need another part. I'm going to go get it. Let's go right away.
잘 둘러볼 필요가 있어
well look around need got
I need to take a good look around
올라가는 길올라왔지만 여기다
going up I've been going up here
I came up, but here it is
뛰어난 안무 아주 칭찬해
Excellent Choreography Very Praise
Excellent choreography, highly praised
어 뭐야 저기 뭐 있다
uh what over there what there
uh what is there
어 얘네들은 하얀색이네
uh these guys are they're white
oh they are white
야 주지를 알아야지 너네들 뭐 하려고얘는 왜 하얀색이야 태타입인가
Hey  I need to know you guys what This kid is Why It's white Is this the dark type
Hey, you need to know the master. What are you guys doing? Why is he white?
[음악]다른게 생겼어 그럼 공격적인 건 아닌
[Music] Something else looks like then Aggressive thing [W5 Not @@
[Music] I got something different, so it's not aggressive
거 같은데맞나
that is the same, right
I think that's right
달라붙어서 막쭉쭉이 안 하네
sticking to Jagged not do
It sticks so it doesn't stick
[음악]응
[MUSIC] Yeah
[Music] Yeah
쭉쭉이 안 해[음악]
goo no do [music]
Don't go straight [Music]
얘 같은데DOC
hey looks like DOC
Looks like a boyDOC
K
잠깐만 저크가 아니잖아 넌 누구지넌 배치지 않아 어디 찾은 거야 내
wait Jerk Isn’t that You Who are you Placement Not Where Found Got My @
Wait, it's not a jerk, who are you?
아들이 널 보냈나 아들내미가[음악]
son sent you sent my son [Music]
Did your son send you? My son [Music]
걱정하고 있는데 인마연락이라도 해주던가
I'm worried about is there Even if you contact me Will you do it
I'm worried, can you contact me in person?
[음악]계획대로 되지 않았어 집으로 돌아가고
[MUSIC] As planned didn't didn't go home go back
[MUSIC] Didn't go as planned, going back home
싶구나 아 못 가는 거야
Wanna Ah Can't Go Go
I want to, I can't go
빠져나가는 걸 모르나 봐
getting out girl don't know look
I guess you don't know how to get out
너 무기 때문에 무기
you weapon because weapon
weapon because of you
이건가 무기
Is this Weapon
this is a weapon
이거 같은데
This is [It looks like W1@@
looks like this
완전히 충전되면 저크를 폭발시켜서산산조각 낼 정도라고
Fully Charge Jerk Explode to shatter  [ About W5@@
It's said to be enough to explode Jerk to pieces when fully charged.
이거 작동하려면1.21gb의 전력이 필요한데
this requires 1.21gb of @@W1 to work] requires power needs
It requires 1.21gb of power to operate.
발전기 뿐이야 아까 그거다
generator only earlier that's it
It's just a generator. That's it.
퓨즈 찾으면 돼
Fuse Find Can
You just need to find a fuse
오케이
ok
okay
자 나만 믿어라너 혹시 악보 있네
Now Only Trust You Maybe Score Yes
Now trust me, do you have sheet music?
허문가 봐라 이거 나도 도와줄게 이거다 찢을 거지
Heommunga Look This Me too I'll help you This is it tear it up beggar
Tear it down, I'll help you with this, I'll tear it all up
다른 거떠올리기
another lifting
another lift
12라고 적혀 있네인간들이 이런 의상을 입은 것을 본
says 12 is written there are humans like this outfit [ W5@@ wore saw saw
It says 12. I've seen humans wear these costumes.
적이 있어크기는 작았고 많은 소음을 내며
never got the size was small made a lot of made noise exhale
It was small in size and made a lot of noise
뛰어다녔는데 아 그래 이제 기억나어린애들 아이들 덕분에 거리가 더
I ran around Ah Yeah Now I remember little kids kids thanks distance more
I ran around, but I remember now, thanks to the children, the distance is longer
활기찼지 아이들 때문에 힘들긴 했어도어른들은 그들을 무척이나 사랑하는 거
Lively Children [Because of W2@@ It was hard but adults [ W5@@ them very much love that
They were lively, even though it was difficult because of the children, adults love them very much.
같았어
[It was like W0@@
It was like
닭은아들을 그리워한다고 말했어 그게 같은
The chicken misses said that's same
The chicken said it misses its son, it's the same
의미인가
[Does W0@@ mean
does it mean
소음 때문에 저크가 나타날 거래
noise because jerk appear deal
Transactions that will jerk because of the noise
그래행운을 빌어줘 나 믿지
Yes, good luck Wish me Me Trust me
yes good luck believe me
잽싸게 갔다 올게[음악]
quickly went I'll come [Music]
I'll be back soon [Music]
응
yes
huh
여기 좀 빡셀 것 같은데
here kinda paksel thing looks like
I think it's going to be a bit tight here.
왠지 애들 많이 나올 것 같아
somehow kids a lot come out things looks like
I think there will be a lot of kids
자
now
ruler
충전 중뭐야이 진동 소리
Charge Whats Vibrate Sound
What is this vibration sound while charging?
애들 개머리 나오는데 어 나이스야 개사기 템인데 개 좋은데
kids dog head appears uh nice Open [It’s a W6@@ item pieces I like it
Kids come out with dog hair, oh nice.
야 여기도땡큐 땡큐 땡큐
Hey Thank you here too Thank you Thank you
Hey here too thank you thank you thank you
도와줘야지 인마 어도와달란 말이야
I have to help dude Help me I mean
I have to help, man, ask for help
어 꺼져 올라가야 돼빨리 꺼져 봐
uh go off go up go up go go see
Go away, you have to go up.
아죽을 뻔했네
I'm dying It was obvious
I almost died
지원사가 제대로 안 해
support properly not do
Supporters don't do it right
멋지구나 너가 발전기를 다시작동시켰어
cool you generator restarted
That's cool. You turned the generator back on.
얼마나 강력한지 봤지 이걸 이용하면여기서 나갈 수 있을 거야 너의
how is powerful saw this use here go be be be be
I've seen how powerful it is. If you use this, you can get out of here.
드론에 어 나이스 드론
drones uh nice drones
Drone Air Nice Drone
[음악]업그레이드된
[MUSIC] Upgraded
[Music] upgraded
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
너무 많이 사용하면 안 되나 봐
too a lot use not become see
Guess I shouldn't use too much
자 어떻게 사용하는 거임 오른쪽이면왼쪽
now how uses is is right then left
Now, how do you use it? Left if right
오른쪽왼쪽은 이거 불 켜는 거고 아래쪽인가
right left is this light light go Is it down
The right and left are turning on this light, is it down?
이제 디플렉스가 있잖아얘네 죽이고 가자
Now Deplex You know what [Kill W3@@ Let's go
Now you have a diplex, let's kill these guys and go
서버원다
ServerWonda
I want a server
죽이고 녹여버리고 가게
Kill Melt Shop
Kill, melt and go
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
야 사용 방법 알려줘야지 근데친구야
hey use method I have to tell you but he's my friend
Hey, I need to tell you how to use it, but my friend
[음악]어 이거다 오
[Music] uh this is it oh
과열될 위험이 있대
Overheating Danger There is
There is a risk of overheating
아 이거 많이 못 쓰니까 아껴서침착하게 써야겠네 그치
ah this a lot can't because Save and stay calm [I should use W6@@ That's right
Oh, I can't use this much, so I'll save it and use it calmly, right?
게이지가 올라가잖아 이렇게 하면
Gauge goes up like this
The gauge goes up.
끊어서 막 써야겠다 그지
cut off just I need to write that's right
I'm going to cut it off and write it, right?
문 열어봐 다터 들어줄게
Door Open it Darter I'll listen
Open the door, I'll listen to you
아 작동하지 않는데
oh doesn't work doesn't work
oh it doesn't work
어떻게됐어
How did it go
how was it
[음악]이걸 뭐 하는거
[Music] this what doing
[MUSIC] What are you doing with this
아 이거 치우고 그 다음에 여기넘어가서 내려간 다음에 여기 들어가서
ah this get rid of it that next Go over here go down then here go in
Oh, get rid of this, then go over here and go down, then go in here
밀어줘저기 위에 올라가는 건가요 뭐지 뭐
Push over there on top go up is what what
Push me, are you going up there, what is it?
용도가 있으니까 이거 하는 거 같은데
uses  this doing stuff Looks like
I think I do this because it has a purpose.
아 저기 틈 있다
ah over there gap there
Oh there's a gap
막힌다고 막 했을 듯그렇죠
says it's blocked just would have done just like that
It's as if you just said it's blocked
잘 파악해야 돼
well should figure it out okay
I have to figure it out
온다 온다 그들이 온다 그들이 온다100%다
comes comes they come comes they come comes 100% all
They are coming, they are coming, they are coming, they are 100%
[음악]야
[Music]
[music] hey
[박수]
[Applause]
[clap]
쁨 아마테라스
Pleasant Amaterasu
[박수]
[Applause]
[clap]
야 너무 많아 너무 많아 너무 많아
hey too much too much too too much too much [There are a lot of W6@@
Hey too many too many too many
잠깐만
Wait a minute
wait for a sec
아슬아슬했네 집으로 돌아가자가자
It was close Home Let's go back
It was close, let's go back home
달려가라 로봇은 빨리
Run robot is quickly
Run, the robot is fast
달려가란 말이야
Run I mean
I mean run
빨리 열어
quickly open
open quickly
야 이거 너네들 많다 아니구나아니구나
hey this you guys a lot no no
Hey, this is a lot of you guys. No, no.
이거 여는 동안 또 끼리끼리
this opening while again with each other
While I'm opening this, with each other again
여기서부터인가
From here
from here
뭐야아 무사히 나왔네에 뭐야
What is Safely is out What is
What is it? You came out safely. What is it?
마음의 준비했는데
heart I prepared
I prepared my heart
감동의 재회 순간 아빠야 아빠야아들아
Touching Reunion moment Daddy Daddy son
The touching moment of reunion Father, father, son
나를 용서해라
Forgive me Forgive me
forgive me
어 뭐야 어로봇 로보텔
uh what Arobot Robotel
What is Arobot Robotel
감동적인 대회구만 아 나 방금 눈물1리터 쏟을 뻔했다 진짜로
Touching Competition Ah Me Just 1 liter of tears spilled almost really
It's a touching tournament, but I almost shed a liter of tears for real
훈훈한 장면이었어[음악]
heartwarming scene [Music]
It was a heartwarming scene [Music]
작은 친구야닭을 구해줘서 고마워 아들은 이제 더
small my friend for saving thank you son [ W5@@ now more
Thank you for saving the chicken, my little friend. My son is better now.
이상 혼자가 아니게 되었어이제 우리는 저크와 맞서 싸울 수
or more alone not now we are jerk and fight fight be
You're no longer alone. Now we can fight Jerk.
있어 모모가 하수구 옆에서 널기다리고 있어
there Momo Sewer next to waiting for you yes
Yes, Momo is waiting for you by the sewer
[음악]우리가 좋은 일을 한 거 같아
[Music] We Good Work One Thing looks like
[MUSIC] I think we did a good job
자 이제 악보 찾자다른 거 다
Now Now Sheet Music Let's Find Another Something all
Now let's find sheet music, everything else
집어치워야 모모는 안 돼악보 지금 어 이거네
Fuck it Momo is Not Notation Now Uh This is it
Fuck it, momo can't.
6장 찾은 거 같은데 이거 아님 두개만 더 찾으면 돼
Chapter 6 Found Something looks like this Or just two more find can
I think I found Chapter 6, but I just need to find two more
우리 여기서 못한게 뭐 있어요테이블 아 이거
we @@W1 here] didn't get it what has table Ah this
What did we not do here? Table Ah this
어 어 나이스 여기 있다이제 하나만 더 찾으면 돼 하나만 더
uh uh nice here now One more find one one one more more
Uh uh nice, here you go, now you just need to find one more one more
어 하나만 더 찾으면 돼 하나만모모의 아파트 욕실에서 먹었냐고
uh only one more find only only one Momo's Apartment In the bathroom Did you eat
I just need to find one more. Did you eat only one in Momo's apartment bathroom?
모모의 아파트 욕실에서그건 당신 마음 안에 있어요
Momo's Apartment In the bathroom that's You Mind is in is in
In the bathroom of Momo's apartment, it's in your mind
여기가 모모 집이잖아
This is Momo This is your house
This is my mother's house
욕실에도 있나
Even in the bathroom is there
is it in the bathroom
여기다야 다 찾았어 어 생각보다 빨리 차
Here it is Everything Found Uh More than I thought fast car
I found everything here, it fills up faster than I thought
좀
little
a little
난 한 20분 10분 예상했거든 다찼는데
I 1 20min 10min I expected It's full, but
I expected 20 minutes and 10 minutes, so it's full
금방 찾았다
right away found
just found
고독한 로봇에 발라드
Lone Robot Ballad
Ballad to the Lonely Robot
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어 이것도 좋다
uh this is good
oh this is good
[음악]근데 기억 떠올리기 다 떠올렸냐고요
[Music] But Remember Recall Everything Did you remember
[Music] But did you remember all the memories?
그건 모르겠는데 여기서 100%채우는 건가
That's I don't know what here 100% filled is
I don't know about that, but am I filling it 100% here?
어 이거 살짝 운율이 어디서 많이들어본 거 같아
uh this slightly rhyme where I've heard of it a lot that [It's like W7@@
Uh, I think I’ve heard a lot about this rhyme somewhere
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
서울의 달이었나기억이 안 나
Seoul's I don't remember if it was the moon not me
I don't remember if it was the moon in Seoul
자 이거어 뺐지
now this is omitted
Now here it is.
작은 왈츠
Little Waltz
little waltz
[음악]스폰지밥이라고 뭔 스폰지밥이야
[Music] It's Spongebob What It's Spongebob
[Music] Spongebob, what SpongeBob?
살짝 비키니시티 느낌이 나네
Slight Bikini City Feeling Nice
It feels a bit like bikini city.
[음악]좋아
[MUSIC] Okay
정말 고마워 나는 이제 뛰어난뮤지션이야
Really Thank you I am Now I am an excellent musician
thank you so much i'm a great musician now
그래 나 뺐지
Yes I I left out
yes i took it out
아 가까이에서 못 보나 일단 얼굴모양 뱃지랑
ah close can't see once Face shape badge and
Oh, I can't see it up close, but first of all, with a badge in the shape of a face
밝은 데서 봐야겠다
Bright  I need to see
I'll have to see it in the light
어 보이지 뺐지 음표 뺐지가까이서 보고 싶은데 대충 보이지
uh I can't see removed note close up Report I want Roughly Can't see
I can't see it, I missed the note, I want to see it up close, but I can barely see it
걔 두 개 얻었네근데 기억 떠올리기는 웬만하면 보이는
he two two got it but remember Reminds me of if possible looks like
I got two of them
것들 다 하긴 했는데여기에서 몇 퍼센트까지 채우는 거예요
things everything did did @@W3 from here] a few Percent up to fills is
I did everything, but I'm filling it up to what percentage here
나 지금 몇 퍼센트 채웠지48% 채웠거든 여기서 한 50%까지
me now few percent filled 48% I filled it up here one up to 50%
I've filled in a few percent now, I've filled it up to 48%, up to 50% here
채워야 되나
should be filled in or
should i fill it
근데 그거는 또 찾기 빡셀 것 같은데여지껏
but that is and search Paksel Thing Same as ever
But I think it will be hard to find again.
돌아다니면서 너무 많이 봐가지고어디 거 놓쳤는지 찾기 힘들잖아
walking around too a lot look where go Did you miss it [Find W6@@ It's hard
You look around so much, it's hard to find where you missed something
몰라 아쉽다 아쉽다하고
I don't know I'm sorry I'm sorry
I don't know, I'm sorry, I'm sorry
넘기자 나머지 하나 찾는 것 좀 빡셀것 같아
pass remainder one find thing some It's going to be tough [It's like W7@@
Let's pass it on. Finding the other one is going to be tough
은근히맨 윗줄칸에 비어 있는 거 같다고
coy man top line blank with big Same as
It seems to be empty in the top row
근데 메모리는 어디서 확인할 수 있어
but memory is where check can Yes
But where can I check the memory
아 여기서 볼 수 있구나 아 여기이렇게 단서가 있네 자 잘 봐 잘 봐
ah ah see ah ah ah like this here clue there now well look look look
Ah, you can see it here Ah, there is a clue like this, look carefully.
이거 어디야이런 식으로 대충 위치들 파악
this where is this way roughly locations Grasp
Where is this?
가능하네
is possible
it's possible
여기 어디지윗줄에 하나는 아까 아빠 구출할 때
Here Where is the top line One is Earlier Dad Rescue [@@W6 when W6@@]
The one in the top row is when I rescued my dad earlier.
지나쳐서 다시 못 구해
too much again can't save
I passed by and can't find it again
아 못해 아
Ah Can't Ah
ah can't ah
말랑이도 엄청 만나기 전에 갔어야했어요 아 지났어
Even the little ones So much [Meet W2@@ before should have gone Ah passed
I should have gone before I met a lot of mollusks. Oh, it's over.
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
이거 뭐 여러분들의 잘못이라고 하고넘어가겠습니다
This What Everyone said it was wrong and I'll move on
I'm going to say that this is your fault
진즉에 알려줬어야지
right away should have told you
I should have told you right away
챙겼을 텐데
would have taken it would have taken it
I would have taken it
모모가 배에서 널 기다리고 있어 지금그쪽으로 가도 되지만 여기에서 볼일은
Momo @@W1 on the boat] you waiting got That way now can go but here business
Momo is waiting for you on the boat. You can go there now, but there is nothing to do here.
다 마친 거야너가 가면 문 닫을 거거든
da done you go door Close
I'm done. I'll close the door when you go.
그래닫아라
Okay, close
yes close
미련 없다리셋하자 스타 인생 오게티랑 남길 수
Regret Let's reset it Star Life Ogetti Nam Gil Wed
No regrets, let's reset it
없다 뭔데닥쳐 말 같지 않은 소리 하고 있어
no shut up say not like not sound and got
I don't have anything, shut up, I'm talking nonsense
근데 놓쳤는데 다시 아예 못 가게만들어 놨을까 나중에 또 갈 수 있지
but missed it again at all not Make a store put it later again go be ITZY
But I missed it, so I can't go again. I can go again later.
않을까 못 가려나
Couldn't Can't Can't hide
I wonder if I can't cover it
어
uh
여기 느낌도 여기 느낌 나는데 아닌가
here feeling here feeling feeling Isn't that
I feel the feeling here too, but I don’t feel it
아 여기서도 이제 몇 개 찾을 수있나 보다
ah here now few  found Can I
Oh, I guess I can find a few more here too
아 이제손상돼 가지고 못 챙기네 아닌가
oh now damaged got it couldn’t got it Isn’t that
Ah, now it's damaged, so I can't take care of it, isn't it?
맞는 거 같은데
fits fits looks like
I guess you're right
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악] [박수]
[Music] [Applause]
아 하수구에서 카트 탈 때
ah down the drain cart ride when
Ah, when riding a cart in the sewer
하수도
sewer
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
그러게 막 이렇게 보면서 신경 쓰면서한 것도 아닌데 거의 다 챙기긴 했다
like that just like like this watching mind writing One nothing but not almost all take was
It wasn't like I was paying attention while looking at it like this, but I took care of almost everything.
그치 하나 빼고
That's right one minus
Except for one
아싸리 그냥 한 6개 못 찾았다하면은
Assari Just One 6 Not If you find it,
Asari, if you can't find 6 of them
[음악]그냥 했을 텐데
[MUSIC] Just would have been would have been
[MUSIC] I would have just done it
하나라고 하니까 아쉽네
One  Too bad
Sorry to say it's one
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
뭐라고
what
으스스한 곳인 걸
spooky gal gal
It's a spooky place
[박수]
[Applause]
[clap]
바닥에 물 색깔 봐
on the floor water color look
look at the color of the water on the floor
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
왜 안 열어 내가 해야 돼뭐지
why not open i should What is it
Why don't you open it, I have to do something
[음악]여기서 내가 뭐 해줘야
[Music] here me what gotta do
[Music] What should I do here
에일리언 나오겠는데
Alien will appear
Alien is coming
덩치가
big
알맹이 크기 보소1년 나오겠네
Content Size Boso 1 year Coming out
Look at the size of the grain, it will come out in a year
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
까먹었어 아
I forgot Ah
I forgot ah
키 버튼 누르는거
key button [press W2@@
pressing the key button
나[음악]
Me [Music]
me [music]
태워줘
Give me a ride
give me a ride
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
난 슬럼에서 이렇게 멀리 나왔던 적이없어 하지만 여기에서 너와 함께라면
I'm from the slum like this away came out Never but here with you together
I've never been this far from the slums, but here with you
두렵지 않아이녀석
I'm afraid I'm not afraid
I'm not afraid this guy
응 나를 많이 신뢰하는구먼
Yeah me a lot I trust you
Yes, you trust me a lot
여기 파이프 많았던 곳에서도기억이 있었어 그치
here pipe there was a lot I also remember where was That’s right
There was a memory even here where there were a lot of pipes, right?
이거 두 개 이거 하나
this two one this one
two of these one of this
얘기했던 거잖아
@@W0 you talked about] that's
that's what i was talking about
안 탔을 때 얘가 그냥 지나가진않겠지 당연히 난 태워주겠지
not rode when he just It won't pass Of course I'm I'll give you a ride
When I'm not riding, he won't just pass by, of course I'll give him a ride
빨리빨리 운전해응
Hurry up Drive
drive fast
너 빈 맞을래[음악]
You Empty I'm sorry [Music]
Will you be empty [Music]
처신 똑바로 하란 말이야[음악]
Behavior Straight Haran I mean [Music]
I mean do it right [Music]
위에도 저커들이 있네[음악]
above jerkers there [Music]
There's jerkers up there too [Music]
잘 안 듣나
well not do you hear
I can't hear you
뭔데
What is
What
이 오래된 기계장치들은 모두 고장난상태야 수동으로 열어야겠는데
this old mechanisms all out of order [ W5@@ Manually [I need to open W6@@
All these old mechanisms are broken. I'll have to open them manually.
어떻게 하려고
How to to try
how to
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아 이걸로가능
Ah This is possible
oh this is possible
딱 내가 들어갈 틈만 있네 아 너가계속
just me  only there Ah you continue
There's only room for me to go in, ah you keep going
갈 수 없지만방법을 찾아볼게
go can but no way I'll look for
I can't go but I'll find a way
[음악]애들을 찾으면 내가 이렇게 용감했다고
[Music] Kids Find Me Like this Brave
[Music] I was so brave when I found the kids
전해 줘내가 너 용감하지 않을까 친구야
Tell me Give me You Aren't you brave Wouldn't my friend
Tell me, I wonder if you're brave, my friend
야 잠깐만 야나 기억 찾아야 되는데
Hey Wait Yana Remember Find
Hey wait, Yana, I need to find my memory.
넘어간 거 아니지 아니라고 해줘 빨리
passed that no no do it quickly
It's not over, tell me it's not, quickly
가다보면 나와
As we go and
Come with me as you go
어 이거 물 좀 극혐인데
uh this water kinda I hate it
Uh, I hate water.
그래
yes
okay
야 잽싸게 달려
hey quickly run
hey run fast
와
and
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
야 들어와 야들어와
hey come in come in
hey come in hey come in
들어와 들어와 들어와넘어가면 그만해
come in come in come in stop
Come in, come in, stop if you pass
여기 살이 틈이 있었거든
here turned gap was there
I had a gap here
뭐 하면 될까
what [If W1@@ will it be
what can i do
[음악]아 여기네 여기서 기억이 있겠네
[Music] Ah Here it is here I remember must be
[Music] Ah here, I must remember this place
떠올리게 여기다 여기
reminds me of here here
remind me here
하스토 시스템 그래 이제 기억나깨끗한 물이 부족했어
hasto system yes now remember clean water was not enough
Hasto System Yes I remember now I ran out of clean water
땅을 깊숙이 파내는 거대한 기계가도시에 물을 공급했어
ground deep digging huge machines in the city [ W5@@ water supplied
A gigantic machine that digs deep into the ground supplied water to the city
다른 모든 저항과 마찬가지로 가뭄이났을 때 인간들의 삶을 유지하기 위해
other all resistance and like drought When Humans Life Maintain To
Like all other resistances, to sustain human life in times of drought
백업이었어과학자는 나에게 물탱크의 청사진을
was a backup. Scientist to me of the water tank blueprints
It was a backup. The scientist gave me the blueprint of the water tank.
보여주었어 건물이 들어갈만큼 큰규모였지
showed me building  was big enough
It was big enough for a building to fit in.
이런 거 찾아 줘야 좋아 어 내가지금 많이 놓쳤으면 안 했을 텐데
Gee Go Find Go Ok Uh now a lot missed not would have would be
It's good if you find something like this I wouldn't have missed it a lot right now
놓치지 않은 이상 아니 하나밖에 안놓쳤잖아 뭔가 아쉬움
miss not more than no only one You didn't miss it something sorry
Unless you missed it, no, you only missed one thing, it's a pity
99%의 남자라고 해주세요 아시겠어요
@@W0 of 99%] man please Do you know
Say 99% of men, okay?
이거 괴물들이 있는 곳이었습니다
this monsters  was where
This is where the monsters are
애들이 많네
kids there are a lot
there are many kids
많이 꿈틀꿈틀하네
a lot wriggling
You wriggle a lot
애들이 잠깐만
kids wait
wait guys
근처에 가지 말자
near branch let's not
let's not go near
아 미리 그냥 지금 저기서 머리사냥하고 올까 그냥 어
ah in advance just now over there head After hunting will come just uh
Oh, in advance, should I just head over there and come back?
여기서 이거 하면은 100% 뭔가불안한데
@@W0 here] this is 100% I’m worried about something
If I do this here, I am 100% uneasy.
잠깐만
Wait a minute
wait for a sec
아 잠깐만괜찮아 괜찮아 굳이 지금
Ah Wait a minute, it's okay It's okay You don't dare Now
Oh wait, it's okay, it's okay
빔 같은 거 안 써도 될 수도 있어
beam same as will be not will be  might be got
You may not need to use a beam or something.
이게 바로 모리사냥의 음이 아니겠어
this is is right Mori hunting sound isn’t it
Isn't this the sound of Mori hunting?
주제를 알란 말이에요 주제를
Subject Alan I mean Subject
To know the subject, the subject
주제를 알아야지
topic I need to know
need to know the subject
아 들어와 컴온 아마
ah come in come on probably
Oh come in, come on, maybe
테라스
Terrace
아 자꾸 기가 먹어 이거 은근히눌러야 되는 키들이 다 달라서
Ah Keep Giga Eat This Secretly You have to press becomes keys are all is different
Oh, I keep getting nervous because the keys I need to press are all different
[음악]헷갈려
[Music] Confused
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
야눈 깔아 인마 어
Lay down dude uh
Lay down your eyes man uh
대기 대기 유인이 필요해 유인이섬세한 작업이 필요한 순간머리
Waiting Waiting Yoo In-i Need Yoo In-i Delicate work is needed moment hair
Waiting Waiting Need manned The moment manned delicate work is needed Hair
검은 머리검은머리
black black hair
black hair black hair
온머리에
all over the head
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
야 다 나와 다 나와 상대해
hey da me me me relative year
Hey, everyone with me, everyone with me
너희들도 나와야 다 나오세요 자 피지낭종들 전부
You guys should come out everyone please come out now sebaceous cysts all
You guys have to come out too. Come on, all the sebaceous cysts
다 오세요 자 다 들어오세요 와우 자다 들어오세요 다 들어오세요 예 예
da come in now da come in Wow go to sleep come in da come in yes Yes
Everyone come, everyone come in, wow, everyone come in, everyone come in, yeah yeah
다 들어오세요 오시면 됩니다 자오세요 자 오세요
All Come in come in will be Come in Now Come
Everyone come in, you can come, come now, come now
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
뭔가 아주아주 좋아
something very very good
something very nice
이러다 죽으면 꿀잼이라고
This is If I die It's fun
If you die like this, it'll be fun
이런 건 다 터트려줘야 제맛
like this things everything I have to explode I like
I have to explode all of these things for the best taste
여기는 단서 아니겠지 여기 뭔가생긴게
Here Clue I guess not Here Something happened
This isn't a clue, there's something here
얘를 다 죽인 이유가
this guy everything killed the reason
Why did you kill him
여기 아니겠지 여기 아닌 거 같다
here probably not here not that Same
It's not here, I don't think it's here
애들 엄청 많다
kids a lot a lot
so many kids
쓰레기 같은 너와 함께라면 뭐 두렵지않아 했던 그
crap same you and together what I'm not afraid did that
The one who wasn't afraid of anything if I was with you, who is like trash
어디 갔어 그 친구싸가지 없는 어 난 두려운데
Where went that sluts no Uh I'm I'm afraid
Where did that friend go? I'm afraid
그러니까 못 먹어 개꿀 빠는데 지금
So I can't eat gag suck now
So I can't eat, I'm sucking honey now
건너편에 것도 해줘야 되나 보다
on the other side  should do become more than
I think I should do something on the other side
에라 몰라 넘어가
oops I don't know go over
I don't know what to do
넘어가 넘어가 넘어가
over over over
pass over pass over
지금
Now
now
스겜 스겜 해킹해킹
Sgame Sgame Hacking Hacking
Sgam Sgam Hacking Hacking
너무 쉽고
too easy
바로 넘어가
immediately over
skip right over
여기다 여기가 그 단서 있는데야
here here that clue there
here and here is the clue
여기에요근데 징그럽다 여기도
Here, but This is disgusting Also here
It's here, but it's disgusting here too
이쑤시개 하나 갖고 오고 싶네
Toothpick One I got is coming I want
I want to bring a toothpick
[박수]
[Applause]
[clap]
뭐야 너 뭐 너가 와야 뭐 하지 어
what you what you come what not uh
What are you, what are you doing, what are you doing?
야 그렇게 낭비하면 안 돼과열된단 말이야
hey like that waste not overheat I mean
Hey, you can't waste it like that. It's overheating.
어떻게 이제 그럼
how now then
아 이제 못 쓴다는 그런 의미네그렇지 못 쓴다는 거 같은데
ah now can't write that mean Yes, that's right can't said  looks like
Oh, that means I can't write anymore. I don't think I can write.
어 근데 저기 아니었나 내메모리
uh but over there wasn’t it my memory
Uh, but wasn't it there? My memory
[음악]아니겠지 아
[Music] I bet ah
[Music] No, ah
꺼져 좀 제발
get off get please
turn off please
[음악]아 방금 넘어갔어 하나
[Music] Ah just passed one
[Music] Oh, I just passed one
다 죽을 수도 없고 이거 그냥
da die might no this just
Everyone can't die, this is just
[박수]아 뭐야 너무 어려서 죽었다
[Applause] Ah What is it Too young So young is dead
[Applause] Oh, he died too young
아 뭐야 이거
ah what this
oh what is this
아 너무 어려서[음악]
ah too too young [Music]
Oh so young [Music]
이거 진행되기 전에 했었어야 됐어
this going on before should have done done
Should have done this before it went on
[음악]보이는 것만
[Music] Visible Only
[Music] What I see
메모리 읽을게요 여러분들계속 그 신경 쓰니까 안 되겠어
Memory I'll read Continue that care  not will be
I'll read the memory.
[박수]98% 남자라고 해주세요
[Applause] 98% Man please
[Applause] Say 98% male
바로 왼쪽
Right Left
right left
바로 오른쪽
Right Right
just right
오케이 아슬아슬
OK Barely
ok close by
고양이 말고요 저 괴물들 좋거든
Cat [Not W1@@ That Monsters I like
Not cats. I like those monsters.
일어나어
wake up
이 쓰레기 같은 놈 그냥 개꿀 빨고있었던 거네 어두운 곳에 나 혼자
this crap like bastard just gag sucked that dark where me Alone
This trash guy was just sucking honey. I'm alone in the dark
있었어 네트워크로 돌아간 기분인 것같은 느낌이었지 하지만 네가 날
was there network returned feeling like [W5 It felt like @@ but you me
I felt like I was back on the network, but you me
구했어 고마워 친구 그 정도의 전력을끌어내면 내 코에 무리가
got it thank you friend that about If you draw power my nose group
I saved it, thank you, friend.
완전히 파괴됐어
completely destroyed
야이 쓸모없는 놈 그거 파괴되면
yay useless bastard that when destroyed
Hey useless bastard, if that thing gets destroyed
얼마나 개고생해서 얻은 건데
how much worked so hard got but
How much did you work hard to get?
응이 양반아
Yep man
좋지가
I like it
good
진짜 개썩은 내 말 듯
really rotten my say like
Like my really rotten words
상상 그 이상의 냄새날 때 진짜냄새 맡는 순간에
imagine that more than smelly when The real smell smells at the moment
When you smell beyond imagination, at the moment you smell the real smell
코 자르고 싶을 때
nose cut want when
When you want to cut your nose
하수를 타고 온 여행 잘하네 너 같은녀석 오랜만에 보네 전에 우리에게
sewage ride come travel well done You same guy It's been a while I see you before to us
Traveling on the sewer is good. It’s been a while since I saw a guy like you.
연락했던게 너야 작은 아웃사이더맞아 맞아 맞아 아 저기 아웃사이더
I contacted It's you Little That's an outsider That's [ W5@@ That's right ah over there outsider
You're the one who contacted me, little outsider, right, right, ah, over there outsider
자발 아무튼 걔가 기다리고 있어 우리마을 꼭대기에서 명상하고 있다 오케이
voluntarily anyway he is waiting is there Our village at the top meditating there ok
Voluntarily, he's waiting for me. He's meditating on top of my town. Okay.
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
이 기계 내가 도왔던 과학자가 이런걸 썼는데
This Machine I Helped Scientist Something like this [I wrote W6@@
This machine The scientist I helped wrote this
그냥 병에 걸렸어 이게 그의 마지막희망이었지 그냥 기계 안으로 걸어
just ill got caught this is his It was my last hope just machine inside walk
Just got sick, this was his last hope, just walk into the machine
들어갔어하지만 나는 그와 함께 있지 않았고
went in but I got with him with got didn't
He went in but I wasn't with him
그는 혼자였어 그가 원하고 있었던거지 그는 컴퓨터에 자신 업로드했고
he was was alone he was wanted was there he uploaded to computer himself uploaded
He was alone, he wanted to, he uploaded himself to the computer
그 후로 모든 것이 달라졌어 하지만업로드가 뭔가 잘못됐었어 그는 수백
that after all things changed but Uploaded Something Wrong He Hundreds
Everything changed after that but something went wrong with the upload he
년 동안 갇혀 있었지작은 고양이가 나타난 때까지
while stuck was little cat appeared [until W6@@
I've been locked up for years, until the little cat showed up
나 아님날 기다렸던 거구나
I or else I've been waiting for that's it
You were waiting for me or me
그랬나 그랬어 내가 내가 그과학자였어 어 뭐야 너가 아 정신을
I did I did I was I was I was the scientist uh what you ah spirit
I was like that I was that scientist
이제이 로봇에다가 이렇게 한 건가
Now this robot like this one is
Now did you do this with this robot?
난 잠시 시간이 필요해
I'm for a moment time is I need
i need a moment
큼지막한 거 복구된
Big Big Recovered
The big one has been restored
미안해 나는
I'm sorry I'm
sorry i
잠시 시간이 필요해 지금 말하고 싶지않아요 말 안 해도 돼 꺼져 나 이거
for a moment time is up need now say I don't want to say don't do ok go away me this
I need some time I don't want to talk right now You don't have to talk Go away I'm this
메모리 볼 거야
memory see go
I'll look at the memory
야 메모리 가져와야
hey memory fetch
Hey, I need to bring a memory
나와
me and
come out
메모리 보고지금까지 3개 놓쳤다고
memory so far 3 missed
Memory report I've missed 3 so far
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아 실례합니다
Ah Excuse me
ah excuse me
아 저기 죄송한데 대화 좀
ah over there sorry conversation kinda
Oh, I'm sorry, talk to me
대화가 안 되네
conversation not is
I can't talk
아 그래도 웃고 있네고양이를 좋아하시는군요
Ah Still Laughing There's a cat You like it
Oh, you're still smiling. You like cats.
그래도 대화하기가 안 되네
Still can't talk not works
I still can't talk
이것도 다 해줘야 돼
This is also Everything should be done should be done
I have to do this too
열심히 해줘야 된단 말이야
work hard you have to do it done I mean
I mean you have to work hard
할 거면 없으려나
I wonder if there is anything to do
아 반갑습니다 얼굴이 카메라 같이생겼다
Oh Nice to meet you Face Camera looks like
Oh nice to meet you, your face looks like a camera
신기하네
Amazing
that's interesting
아 맞네 아 맞아 얘기야 못하는이유가 그거구나 얘가 지금 파업해
Ah That's right Ah That's right That's Why not that's it he's now go on strike
Oh that's right that's right that's why you can't talk, he's on strike right now
가지고
has
have
아 맞네 부모님도 친구도 있었을 텐데다들 무슨 일이 있었던 거지
Ah That's right Parents Friends would have been  what happened was beggar
Oh right, there must have been parents and friends, but what happened to them?
도시를 개방하고 싶지만 구할 사람이남아 있을까
city open want get people stay [ Will there be W5@@
I want to open the city, but is there anyone left to save?
맞네 너 이제 기운 찾았어 아 지금도안 되나 보다 뭐 아무것도 눌러도 안
That's right you now cheer up found Ah Not even now now more than what nothing press not
That's right, you've found your energy now.
돼
ok
okay
아니 기분에 따라서인마
no in the mood so man
No, depending on your mood
얘기해 줘야지npc랑 얘기해야 되는데
talk should talk to npc talk should be
I need to talk to the npc.
어 여행가보다 맞지
Uh More than a traveler Right
I'm more like a traveler
이게 뭐지[음악]
this is what [music]
what is this [music]
이봐
Hey
hey
초월 명상을 하는 자를 방해하면 안된다는 거 모르나 아 너구나 이전에
Transcending Meditating   Interfering No that I don't know ah you're before @@W9 @W10]
You don't know that you shouldn't disturb those who are doing Transcendental Meditation.
연락을 받았을 때 넌 모모와 함께있었지 드디어 만나서 반갑구나 작은
Contacted Received When You Momo We were together Finally Nice to meet you Nice to meet you little
When I got the call, you were with Momo. Nice to meet you at last. Little
아웃사이더넌 모모와 닭을 알고 있으니까
Outsider you Momo and The chicken know [Because W4@@
Because you're an outsider, you know momo and chickens
아웃사이더에 대해서 익숙하겠지 그들이그리워 그들을 떠올리면 내 마음이
Outsiders About You should be used to I miss them They [ When I think of W5@@ my mind
You must be familiar with outsiders. I miss them. When I think of them, my heart
편하죠슬럼에 있는 모모에게 너가 닭을
In a comfortable slum in to Momo you the chicken
It's convenient. You gave chicken to Momo in the slum.
찾는데 도움을 줬다고 들었어 그리고있는 지금 미드타운에 있어 지금도
looking for help gave heard and Now in midtown there now
I heard you helped me find it. I'm in Midtown right now, even now
아웃사이드를 보고 싶다면 그녀가그곳으로
outside see if you want she goes there
If you want to see the outside, go there
데려다줄 수 있을 거야도시를 떠날 계획이었던 것 같거든 자
will take you be be will be leave It was planned thing [It's like W7@@ now
I can take you there. I think you were planning to leave the city. Come on.
이거 받아 사진 뒷면에 주소를 써놨어가려면이
take this take picture back address Wrote this
I got this and wrote the address on the back of the photo.
작은 마을에서 위로 올라가야 해너처럼 재주가 좋으면 간단할 거야
small in town up go up like Haner Skill good simple will
Gotta go up from the little town
너가 성공한다면 최초로 아웃사이드에도달한 자가 될 거야 행운을 빈다만
you if successful first reached outside person will be will be good luck only
If you succeed, you'll be the first to reach the outside. Good luck.
너에게는 필요가 없겠지 너를 너를믿어
you you need you don’t have you I trust you
You won't need it, believe in you
그래요 좀 전에 전을 꺼버려서 미안해난 인간이야 아마도 세계의 마지막
yes some before before off I'm sorry I'm human maybe @@W8 of the world] last
Yes, I'm sorry I turned off the light earlier, I'm human, maybe the end of the world
인간이겠지 내게 남은 건 이게 전부야기억이 많이 돌아왔어 내가 잊은 것은
must be human to me remaining thing this is I remember everything a lot I'm back I I forgot
I must be human, this is all I have left. A lot of memories have come back, what I forgot
얼마나 될까만약 그 녀석을 찾으면 내 메모리를
how much would be if that  find My memory
How long will it be if I find him, my memory
복원해서 너를 집으로 데려다줄 수있을지도 몰라 다시 내려와서
restore you home will take you might be able to [ W5@@ I don't know again come down
Maybe I can restore it and take you home
컴패니언에게 더 많은 정보를 얻거나위로 가면 미드타운으로 갈 수 있어
Companion More More Info Get Up [ W5@@ go midtown go go go
Get more information from your companion or go upstairs to get to Midtown.
[음악]컴패니언
[Music] Companion
가야지
Gotta go
그거 우리에게 그녀를 찾으려고 말했어
that us her to find told
that told us to find her
번호가 쓰여 있어[음악]
number is is written is [Music]
There's a number on it [music]
뭔데 이거
What is This is
what is this
하나는 여기서 찾을 수 있겠는데이렇게 문양 생긴 거
one is where find could be would be like this glyph looks like looks like
You can find one here. It's patterned like this.
왼쪽에 빨간 뭔가
left red something
something red on the left
전등이다 전등 소파랑 아까 거기같은데
lights lights sofa and earlier looks like there
It's a light, it's like there before with the light sofa.
어디 쪽에서 봤던 거 같은데
where [@@W1 from the W1@@ side] saw that [Same as W4@@
I think I saw it somewhere
반갑습니다사실이 음식은 끔찍하지만 여기서 먹을
Nice to meet you Food Terrible but here eat
Nice to meet you actually this food is terrible but eat here
거니 이것밖에 없어이 쓰레기를 계속머무는 내 전면 케이스에 나사를
Gurney Only this No this Garbage Staying my front case screws
That's all there is to it
푸는게 낫지나도 하나
Solve It's better one
It's better to solve it
양철 셰프라고 불렀더군 남은 음식을업사이클링 하는데 전문가진 오늘의
Tin Chef called Leftovers Upcycling food  expert photo Today's
He called me Chef Tin. He is an expert in upcycling leftovers.
요리 비밀 재료가든 라멘
Cooking Secret Ingredient Garden Ramen
[음악]요리 방해하자고
[Music]Cooking Let's interrupt
[MUSIC] Let's interrupt the cooking
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
엘리베이터
Elevator
elevator
아까 내려가서 뭐 하거나 위로올라가거나 둘 중에 하나는 네가
just before go down what or go up or two out of one you
Go down and do something or go up, one of the two is you
원하는 대로 하라 이렇게 했잖아그게 이거다 이거 맞지 메모리
what you want as do like this you said that This is This is Right Memory
Do what you want, you did this, that's this, this is right, memory
이 언어 캠페인은 로보트 로봇이완전히 처음부터 만든 거야 정말
this language campaign is robot robot is totally from scratch made will really
This language campaign was made entirely from scratch by robot robots. Really.
대단해 내가 네트워크에 있을 때생겼던 일이 기억나요 정확히 언제인지
awesome I network be nice  remember exactly when
Awesome I remember what happened when I was on the network Exactly when
모르겠지만 어느 순간부터 모든통신이이 기호로 전환되기 시작했어
I don't know what which from the moment all communication is symbol [ W5@@ transitioned started
I don't know, but at some point all communication started to switch to this symbol.
난 오랫동안 혼자 컴퓨터 안에 갇혀있었어 그래서 나는 모든 것을 이해할
i long alone computer inside trapped Was So I All That Understand
I've been stuck inside my computer alone for a long time so I understand everything
수 있을 때까지 모든 기호와 단어를하나씩 번역했지 이제 난 자율고
to be to be until all symbols and Word by word translated now I am self-regulation
I translated every sign and word one by one until I could
그들의 언어도 알고 있으니 그들이하는 모든 말을 듣고 싶어
know their language know so they are all say hear wanna
I know their language too, so I want to hear everything they say
자 그럼초반부터 한번 얘기 한번 다 나눠볼까
now then from the beginning once talk once Everything Shall we share
Now then, let's talk about everything from the beginning
얘네가 첫 번째였나
these guys the first the second
Were these the first
맞네 하나씩 대화 좀 해볼게요여러분들
That's right one by one conversation a bit I'll try everyone
That's right, let's talk one by one, everyone
흰색 페인트 종류가 900개가넘는다는 걸 알고 있어 아무한테도
white paint types over 900 girl [ W5@@ knows has to nobody
I know there are over 900 types of white paint.
말하지 마 지금 나만의 페인트색을만들고 있거든
say don't now make your own paint color [ Because W5@@ exists
Don't tell me, I'm making my own paint color right now
쓰레기 갈색이라고 부를 거예요그렇구먼
Garbage Brown Call That's right
I'm going to call it trash brown.
게임옷 9,536승 6패 와
Game clothes 9,536 wins 6 losses and
Game clothes 9,536 wins 6 losses
사실 내가이 게임에서 이기도록프로그래밍 되어 있지만 아무한테도
true I have in game programmed to win becomes but to nobody
Actually I'm programmed to win this game, but no one
말하면 안 돼
say don't you can
can't say
통계적으로 내가 최소 여덟 번을이겼어야 하는데
Statistically I Minimum Eight Must have beaten times [ W5@@ but
Statistically I should have won at least eight times
어떤 이들은 이걸 쓰레기라고 하지만나는 보물이라고 부르지
which these are these are crap but I'm It's a treasure [I don't call it W6@@
Some call it trash but I call it treasure
나는 열어주기 전에는 나는 열어주기전에는 배봇이었지만
I open before I before open It was a boatbot, but
Before I opened it, I was a boatbot before I opened it.
몸을 헌터로 용도를 변경했어 그소리에 속지마 방금 찾은이 팔처럼
Body As Hunter Usage Changed That's what Don't be fooled Just Found this like an arm
I repurposed my body as a hunter. Don't be fooled by that sound, like this arm I just found.
딱딱하고 끔찍한 걸지도 몰라불쌍한 친구의 평화로의 녹슬기를
Hard Terrible I might bet I don't know how pitiful friend's [ W5@@ to Peace To Rust
It might be hard and terrible. A poor friend's rust to peace.
여기 온 이유가 있지 않을까
here here why there maybe
Maybe there's a reason you're here
뭔가 여기
something here
빨간색 식물 얻었어
Red Plant Got
got a red plant
이 꽃들 좀 봐 이쁘다 아마도 이걸좋아할 로봇이 있을 거야
this flowers some look pretty probably would love this robot would be would be
Look at these flowers. They're pretty. Maybe there's a robot that will like them.
꽃을 좋아할
flowers like
love flowers
로봇이 있을 거라
robot be be
there will be robots
나 안 자냐구요 이거 켠왕 해야지이것도 하다 말면
I not Are you sleeping This  Should do this too do or not
Am I not sleeping?
수많은 집사 분들께서
Countless Butler
Many homeowners
너 뭐라 합니다
you what do
what do you say
이거 해줄 때까지도징징댄단 말이에요
This will do it for you [Winning even until W2@@ I mean
I'm whining until you do this
메인은 해체주의 기간이래 보는 스스로그러더군
Main is Deconstructionism since the period watching said it himself
Since Maine was in the period of deconstructionism, the viewer himself said so
메인은 분명 훌륭한 예술가가 될 거야다른 곳에서 연습한다면 말이지
main is obviously great become artist be It's another  if you practice I mean
Maine will definitely be a great artist if she practices elsewhere.
나는 신선한 페인트 냄새가 너무좋아이 냄새를 맡으면 떠오르는 아
I Fresh Paint Smell I love this Smell [Smell W6@@ comes to mind ah
I love the smell of fresh paint
잠깐난 냄새를 맡을 수 없잖아 이거 참
Wait Smell Smell Can No This true
You can't smell it for a while, this is so
슬프네그러니까 인마 너 냄새를 알아 어
You're sad, so dude you smells I know uh
It's sad so man I know what you smell
냄새를 안 한 말이야
smell not one
I mean it didn't smell
그거 전기 저 그 사방에 없냐
that electric that that everywhere Isn't it
Isn't that electricity everywhere?
뭐 안녕 누군가 방문한 건 정말오랜만인걸 물론 그 망할 빼고 말이지
what hi someone visited thing really Long time no see of course that damn [Except W9@@
Well hello, it's been a while since anyone visited, except for the damn thing, of course.
녀석들의 힘을 이용할 수 있다고상상해 봐 바퀴 같은 걸 타고 달리기
Guys Power Utilize Can [Imagine W4@@ Look Wheels Like Girl Ride Run
Imagine being able to use their power. Run on something like a wheel.
하는 거지 지금은 가능성을 낭비하고있다고
now @@W3 possibilities] wasting
You're saying you're wasting your potential now
나는 크면 그 녀석 아 이모처럼 되고훌륭해지고 싶어 나도 이모처럼 탐험을
I when I grow up that guy ah aunt Like become great wanna be me too like aunt explore
When I grow up, I want to be like his aunt and be great. I also explore like my aunt.
하고 싶었지만 어른들은 우리가엔터빌리지를 떠나지 못하게 했어
and [I wanted to do W1@@ but Adults are We leave the entertainment We don't leave didn't let me did
We wanted to, but the adults wouldn't let us leave the Enter Village.
어려서 안 돼 위험해
I'm young I'm not I can do it It's dangerous
I can't because I'm young, it's dangerous
아 클레멘타인쓰레기가 떨어지는 아늑한 소리
ah clementine crap falling cozy sound
Ah Clementine, the cozy sound of garbage falling
반짝이는 폭포 위험 없음시를 쓰기도 없이 행복한 곳이야 자
Sparkling Waterfall Danger No Poetry Write [ W5@@ without happy that's where now
A sparkling waterfall, no danger, no poetry, no poetry, a happy place now
들어봐 그 자궁 안에서 나를 보호하는강력한 콘크리트 나의 무덤도 되어줄
listen that womb inside me Protecting strong concrete my tomb also will be
Listen, the strong concrete that protects me in that womb will also become my grave
수 있을까 너무 엄숙한 분위기인가
be be too solemn mood
Is it too solemn?
넌 안 되겠다포기해
You are I am not I will give up
You can't do it, give up
여기도 꿀이 있다 이거 얻을 수 있지않을까
here too honey there this get Can
There is also honey here. Can I get this?
어 맞네 보라색 식물
uh that's right purple plants
oh right purple plant
얻었어 이것도 뭔가 단서가 있을 듯
got this is something clue be seems like
Got it, this seems to have some clues
색깔별로 이렇게 막 모아서 뭐 이렇게조합 같은 거 나중에 할 수 있나 봐
by color like this just put together what This combination like ya ya do be Is there look
I think I can do something like this after I collect them by color like this
이 마을 꼭대기에서 미드타운으로 가는길을 찾아 이거 꼭 혹시 누구
This Village Top Midtown way to find this sure maybe anyone
Find your way from the top of town to Midtown This must be someone
[음악]가 더 있을 것 같은데
[music] is more would be would be looks like
I think there'll be more [music]
느낌이
feeling
the feeling is
얘네들도 아니야[음악]
These guys no [Music]
Not even these guys [Music]
더 올라가다 보면 나올 것 같긴 한데
more go up look come out go up look like together
It seems to come out if I go up more
여기 왜 왔을까넘어갈 수가 없는데
here Why came?]
Why did I come here? I can't get over it
그냥
just
올라가려고 있는 건가
going up going up going up
are you trying to climb
꽃집이잖아
It's a flower shop
안녕 친구 잘 지내니 이모가 햇빛없이도 살 수 있는 특별한 식물을
hi friend well how are you aunt Without sunshine live   special plants
Hello friend How are you My aunt has a special plant that can live without sunlight.
키우는 방법 우리에게 가르쳐준 거알아 나 많이 가지고 있거든 볼래
raised how to taught us taught us I know me a lot [I have W7@@ [I have W8@@ [I want to see W9@@
I know you taught us how to grow it. I have a lot.
그런데 몇 가지 색은 없어 어노란색만 찾으면 되겠네 노란색 자
but few kind of color no Only yellow if you find it will be yellow
But there aren't many colors, you just need to find a yellow color.
이거 일단 하나 줄게어 자 이것도 줄게
this first one  now This too I'll give you
I'll give you one of these, now I'll give you this too
노란색 찾아서 올게 대신 나 좋은 거줘야 돼 알았지
yellow find I'll come instead of me good should go should go okay
I'll find yellow and come back. Instead, I need something good, okay
후 심심해 이모가 이곳에서 수업을진행했었어 우린 멋진 걸 많이
After I'm bored My aunt @@W3 here] I had class we cool girl a lot
After I got bored, my aunt taught classes here. We did a lot of cool things.
배웠는데
learned
I learned
노란색은 왠지 어디 있을 것 같아
yellow is somehow where would be would be Same
The yellow seems to be somewhere
위쪽에 있을까
@@W0 on top]
is it on top
좋은 아침이에요잠은 좀 주무셨나요
Good It's morning. Sleep A bit Did you sleep
Good morning. Did you get some sleep?
아방금 심장이 좀
just now heart beat little
A little heart
아 방금 누가 데스노트에 내 이름적은 거 같은데
ah just who Death Note my My name is is [Same as W7@@
Ah, I think someone just wrote my name in the Death Note.
면역 있어서 좀 지금산 거 같거든
Immunity in little now almost It's the same
I think I live now because I have immunity
방금심장
Just Heart
just heart
찌릿했어
I was thrilled
여기다
here
It's here
다 찾았다 다 찾았어 여러분차 좋겠다 나처럼 이렇게 꼼꼼한
all found all found everyone I wish like me like this meticulous
I found it all, I found it all
사람이 이거 해줘가지고
person this give me
someone do this
비록메모리는 몇 개 놓쳤지만
even though the memory is several  missed but
Although I missed a few memories
얘기했지만 누군가 나를 위해 가져왔어내가 정말 좋아하는 색이야 고마워
told me someone me  brought me Really I like color Thanks
I told you, but someone got it for me. It's my favorite color. Thank you.
친구 모두 찾았네 정말 고마워
Friends Everyone Found Really Thanks
Found all my friends thank you so much
[음악]내 머리에서 다 찾으면 메모리 뺏지
[Music] My in my head everything find memory [ W5@@ take away
[Music] If I find it all in my head, I'll take the memory
같은 거 주는 거 아니야 어 그런 건없어 봐 제발
like something giving something no uh that nothing look please
I'm not giving you the same thing, there's no such thing, please
외모를 전부 다 너 덕분에 기억을전부 다 찾았어
look all all you thanks All my memories all found
My appearance, everything, thanks to you, I found all my memories
고마워 메모리 뺏지 줄게 이렇게 하는거 아니겠지
Thank you memory take away I'll give you like this  I guess not
Thank you, I'll take away the memory.
여긴 어디지[음악]
This is Where is it [Music]
Where are you? [Music]
여기에 그 이모가 있다는데 아님 이모
here that my aunt said said not aunt
I heard that the aunt is here, or the aunt
만나러 간다
to meet go
I'm going to meet you
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어지하철인데
It's a crazy subway
It's a subway
여기가 지하철역이야 이런 교통수단이있다는 걸 까맣게 잊고 있었어 이걸로
This is This is the subway station This is There is transportation Girl charred forgot was there with this
This is the subway station. I completely forgot that this type of transportation existed. With this
도시 어느 곳이라도 갈 수 있어사람들은 일하러 갈 때
City Any Any Go Be There are people go to work go when
You can go anywhere in the city. When people go to work
타고 냈어 나도 마찬가지고매일 아침 집에서 가족들과 작별
Ride I paid Me too Same every day morning At home with family farewell
I rode it, so did I. I say goodbye to my family at home every morning
인사하고 나서 말이에요
say hello then I mean
After saying goodbye
기억나 나는 가족들을 위해이 일을하고 있었어 하지만 이제 그들은 없어
remember i family doing this doing [ W5@@ was but now they are are not
I remember I was doing this for my family but now they're gone
아주 오래전 일이야[음악]
very a long time ago that's a thing [music]
It was a long time ago [Music]
가족들은 아웃사이드를 보고 싶어했지만 이제 그게 의미가 있나
families outside saw wanted now [ W5@@ is that means is
Families wanted to see the outside, but now does that mean anything?
그들에게 무슨 일이 일어났지 모두에게무슨 일이 일어났지
to them what happened to happened to what to everyone happened happened
what happened to them what happened to everyone
잊어 어쨌든 우리는 지금 미드타운근처에 있어
forget anyway we are now near midtown [ There is W5@@
forget it anyway we're near midtown now
클레멘타인을 찾아보자그네 사진이 있으니까 여기 있는
Clementine Let's find a swing has a picture  here in
Let's find Clementine. There's a picture of him here.
캠페니원들에게 보여줄 수 있겠어 아마단서가 있을 거야
@@W0 to the campaign members] @@W1 to show] number there is Maybe you have a clue will be will be
Can you show it to the campaign members? Maybe there's a clue.
[음악]여기도 한번 좀 둘러보자
[Music] Here too once a little bit Let's look around
[Music] Let's take a look around here
스탑이에요꽃은 전부 다 찾았어요 내가 누굽니까
Stop. The flower is All All I found I [ W5@@ Who are you
Stop. I found all the flowers. Who am I?
예 아늑한 뭔가 보라색 불빛 느껴지는방인데
yes cozy something purple lights felt It's a room
Yes, it's a cozy room where you can feel the purple light
[음악]그 다음에
[MUSIC] That then
[MUSIC] Then
[음악]뭔지 모르겠고
[Music] What I don't know
[Music] I don't know what
빨간색 뭐 낙서도 있는 거뭔지 모르겠고
Red What Graffiti  What I don't know
I don't know what the red graffiti is.
뭔지 모르게 여기 뭔가블루스크린 뜨는 거
what don't know here something blue screen floating ger
I don't know what it is, something blue screen pops up here
테이블 끝 끝 끝 끝 끝[음악]
table end end end end end [Music]
Table End End End End End [Music]
어[음악]
uh[music]
uh [music]
아닌가
isn't it
is not it
서적
book
books
여기는 없는 거죠 올라갑니다
This is is not is goes up
It's not here, it's going up
메모리 혹시 놓친 거 있으면알려주세요 내가 놓칠 것 같으면
memory in case missed something let me know if you have I would miss would be would be
Memory Let me know if I missed anything If I think I'm missing something
적어도 97%의 남자는 유지해야지여기다 여기 하나 있을 것 같은데
at least 97% of men should keep here here one one one one
At least 97% of men should keep it. I think there might be one here.
이거는
This is
this is
여기는 책이 아주 많아튜링 테스트 유산 인공지능의 윤리
This is This is a book Very A lot Turing Test Legacy Artificial Intelligence Ethics
There are so many books here. The Turing Test Legacy The Ethics of Artificial Intelligence
내가 아는 것도 있어 내게 서지가있었나
I I know nothing I got me Serge Was there
There's something I know, did I have a bibliography
책 냄새와 페이지 넘기는 느낌 아주독특했던 걸로 기억해 거의 편안한
Book Smell Page Turn Feel Very unique stuff remember almost comfortable
The smell of the book and the feeling of turning the pages I remember it as very unique, almost comfortable
느낌 같은 느낌이었어책은 누군가와 시간을 보내는 것과
feeling same feeling a book someone time sending and
It was like a feeling. A book is like spending time with someone.
같았어
[It was like W0@@
It was like
말이 없네 이거 알고 있는 거 있어말을 못 하나
say no this know in stuff got to say couldn't one
I have no words, I know this, I can’t say it
[음악]말 못 해
[music] say don't do
[Music] Can't talk
[박수]그리고
[claps] and then
[Applause] And
시끄러워 전세 냈어어
noisy reserved paid
It's noisy, I paid a charter
전 세는 거야
ex counting counting
I'm counting
길목에다가 이렇게 노래 틀고 있는거야 이거
At the corner of the street like this song playing is there this
They're playing songs like this on the street corner
경찰 로봇도 있나 봐
Police Robot  Look
There must be police robots too
경찰로고
police logo
반갑습니다[음악]
Nice to meet you [Music]
nice to meet you [music]
이미 다섯 번이나 말했잖아요시
already five once you said
I already told you five times
그렇게 뛰어다니면 안 된다니까 위험해이봐 이런 로봇은 처음 보는 걸
like that running around no  It's dangerous [ W5@@ Gee Robot First time Seeing Girl
They said you shouldn't run around like that. It's dangerous. Hey, I've never seen a robot like this before.
북치북 시대 보이네아이 수배 화면에 나오는 여자 다른
Bukchibuk Era Seeneye Wanted on screen Coming Out Female Another
Bukchibuk Era Boineai Wanted The woman on the screen is different
자에게 물어봐 여기 요시 때문에바빠서 아무것도 몰라
Ask Here Yoshi [I'm busy because of W4@@ nothing don't know
Ask me, I'm busy here because of Yoshi, so I don't know anything
쓰레기는 걱정하지 마세요 여기서 모두처리해드립니다
Garbage Don't worry Don't do it here we'll take care of everything
Don't worry about the garbage, we'll take care of it all here
배치 혹시 다 먹을 예정이라고요그냥 뭐 진행하는데도
Batch Maybe Everything Eat It's scheduled. Just What progressing
If you plan to eat all of the batch, even if you are just doing something
신문을감옥으로 이송하고 재부팅 하겠습니다
Newspaper to jail transfer reboot I will
I'll transfer the newspaper to jail and reboot
나를 내버려도 너가 나는 네가 찾고있는 자가 아니야
me leave me alone you me you Looking for is not is not
Even if you leave me alone, I'm not the one you're looking for
클레멘타인을 찾고 있다면 주거구역에숨어 있을 거야
looking for Clementine looking for  hiding in the residential area there is
If you're looking for Clementine, she'll be hiding in the residential area.
어렵게 자세히 알려주시나요
Difficult Details Can you tell me
Can you tell me in detail
괜히 이런 장소가 있을까 아니나였으면 여기에 뭔가 숨겨놨기
for nothing like this is the place is if not Here something hidden
If I didn't know if there was a place like this for no reason, I hid something here.
때문이지
[Because of W0@@
because
아무것도 없나
Nothing Anything
is there anything
개발자 에바인데 여기 아무것도 없음
Developer Eva Here Nothing None
Developer Eva, nothing here
괜히 공감 만들어놔서 사람 헷갈리게만들었는데
No wonder I agree with you made it person made me confused
I made empathy for no reason, so I made people confused
저 층은 위험한 유기생명체로 인해접근이 제한되어 있음이 지역에
low layer dangerous organic life due to access is limited to is in is in
Lower floors have restricted access due to dangerous organic life.
적반하지 마시오난 이미 갔다 왔었지
It's not right I don't know Already went came
Don't tell me, I've already been there
이 아래 소리 들려 썰물 밀물도시가 나를 괴롭혀 나를 조롱해 어
this down sound hear ebb ebb The city bully me tease me make fun of me mock me uh
I can hear the sound down here
클레멘타인 그래도 예전에 함께어울리곤 했지만 그런 떠나고 싶어
Clementine Still Before used to hang out together but [ W5@@ like that leaving wanna
Clementine: We used to hang out together, but I want to leave.
했어 마치 산들바람 같아서 날아가버리고 말았어 이젠 수배 중이고
did like breeze [like W3@@ flew away I did now Wanted in progress
I did it, it was like a breeze and it flew away, now I'm wanted
나한테는 너무 무겁지들렸어
@@W0 for me] too sounds heavy
Sounded too heavy for me
썰물 밀물
low tide high tide
ebb and flow
요쪽에 메모리 하나 있다고요
this side memory one there
There's a memory on this side.
말 안 해도 알아어디쯤에 있는지
say not even I know where is
Even if you don't tell me, I know where you are
얘기하지 마세요
don't talk don't
don't talk
안에 뭐 나가야 되나
in what go out become
what to do inside
와 미드타운여기도 뭐 자판기처럼 찾는 거 있어
and Midtown here too what like a vending machine looking for there there
Wow, Midtown is also looking for something like a vending machine
근데 꼼꼼히 먹으면 돼찾을 수 있을 거야
but carefully eat get it can There will be will be
But if you eat carefully, you'll find it
놓치는 거 없이 잘 보면은
missing thing without well look
If you look closely without missing anything
아 여기 청소 회사에서 일하나 봐
Ah Here Cleaning At the company Working see
Oh, he must work for a cleaning company here.
어 뒤에 주소가 있는데첫 번째 기호는 거리 이름이고 그
uh followed by address is is the first th [W5@ The @ sign is is the distance is the name that is
There is an address after uh, the first symbol is the street name and then
다음은 층과 문 번호야거리 층 문 번호
next is floor and door number street floor [ W5@@ statement number
Next is the floor and door number. Street floor door number.
찾기 쉬울 거야
find would be easy would be
it will be easy to find
아 내가 말고
Ah I not
oh not me
거리 층 번호 아니 아까 뭐라고 했지거리
Street Floor Number No Earlier What
Street floor number No, what did you say earlier? Street
파란색 저 거리 층 3층5는 아까 뭐라고 했지
Blue Low Street Floor 3 Floor 5 Earlier What did you say said
What did 3rd floor 5 on the blue street say?
[음악]문 번호
[Music] Moon Number
[MUSIC] Door number
파란색인데 3층에 문 번호가 5번이야오케이
It's blue on the 3rd floor door number is No. 5 okay
It's blue, but the door number is 5 on the 3rd floor. Okay
많을 수도 있고
may be may be may be
may be many
이 사기꾼이 결함이 있는 배터리를팔았어
cheater defective  sold the battery
This scammer sold a defective battery
따지려고 하면 내 말을 못들은척한다니까
trying to argue  my  pretending not to hear
If you try to argue, you pretend not to hear me
순혈중에 센티넬이 아니었던이 사기꾼은부포로 해체되었을 거야
in pure blood sentinel was not swindler disbanded is
This swindler, who was not a Sentinel in pure blood, must have been disbanded as a bupo
어들어갈 수 있어
where can got
I can get in
애들이 들어가도 뭐라 안 한다 여기는그렇지
kids go in what don't do It is like that here
Even if the kids go in, they don’t say anything, that’s the case here
어 금고 뭐야디지코드
uh Vault What DigiCode
uh safe what is digcode
비번비번
password password
off-duty off-duty
2458 이거구만[음악]
2458 That's it [Music]
개낚시야아
Dog fishing
dog fishing
코드
code
85 사이 그럼 8542인가 8호사이
85 [between W1@@ then 8542 [between W4@@ 8
Between 85 then 8542 or between No. 8
[음악]아
[MUSIC] Ah
코드구나854에
code @@W0 to 854]
to code 854
[음악]고양이 뱃지 나이스 배지 어 여기
[Music] Cat Badge Nice Badge Uh here
[MUSIC] Cat badge nice badge uh here
이거 야광이다 야광노이즈까지 있어 노이즈
this luminous even luminous noise there noise
This is luminous, there is even luminous noise, noise
완전 레어 레전드 리그도 있음
Perfect Rare Legend Rig Yes
There is also a completely rare legend league.
글리치 효과도 들어가 있어
Glitch Effect Enter Got
It also has a glitch effect.
멋쟁이 고양이든
Cool Cats
a handsome cat
여기 먼저 들어가야 되려나 여기가초입 부분인가
here first must go in to be this is the beginning [W5@ Is the @ part
Should I go in here first? Is this the beginning?
이런데 또 뭐가 있을지도 몰라
It's like this Again What might be I don't know
I don't know if there's anything else
미안해 꼬마 여기서 놀면 안 돼 여기공장은 너 같은 자금 털뭉치를 위한
I'm sorry kid here play no okay here is the factory you like funding hairball [@@W11 for W11@@]
Sorry kid you can't play here this factory is for money hairballs like you
곳이 아니야적군이 제한되어 있지만 잠시동안만
no place no enemy restricted but only for a while
It's not a place. Enemies are limited, but only for a while.
그런 거야 몇 년만 기다리면 바로열릴 거야 몇 년
like that that's a few years only wait right away open will several year
That's it, if you wait a few years, it will open right away. A few years.
거리이고
is the distance
숨어서 진입하는 건가지금 바빠 왜 불러 이거 꺼져
Hiding Entering Is it now Busy Why Call This Get lost
Are you hiding and entering? I’m busy right now, why are you calling me?
나중에 쫓길 때 이거숨어서 뭐 하는 건가 보네
later will be chased  hide this what Do Do Do
Later, when you're being chased, I'll see what you're doing in hiding
맞지
right
Right
숨어서 뭐 하는 건가 보다
hiding what doing is more than
What are you doing hiding?
넌 뭐야
You What is
What are you
넌 뭔데 경찰 죄다 그날 잡고 있어그럼 여기 오지 않았다고
You What is it Police Everything That day Grab got it then here don't come didn't
Who are you? All the cops are holding you that day. Then you didn’t come here.
여기 메모리 냄새나는데 아닌가
here memory smells like isn’t it
It smells like memory here, isn't it?
[음악]아래 도시에 가본 적 있어 거기에
[Music] Under In City Been Ever Got [ W5@@ there
[MUSIC] I've been to the city below, there
친구가 있는데pp라고
has a friend says pp
I have a friend called pp
글을 오랫동안 보지 못했어PP 우리도 봤던가
wrote for a long time didn't see didn't get PP us too Did you see it
I haven't seen the article for a long time PP Did we see it too?
PP pp가 누구지
pp pp WHO
who is pp pp
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어 여기 뭐 있겠구만
uh here what I guess
oh what is here
아래층에서 대체 뭐라는지 모르겠어계속 윙윙거리는 소리와 망치 소리가
downstairs what the hell what I don't know more buzzing [ W5@@ sound hammer sound
I don't know what the heck they say downstairs.
들려
I can hear you
I can hear
이거 들으려고 여기 왔어
this to listen here here
I'm here to hear this
어 이거 뭐야
uh this what
uh what is this
귀신
ghost
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어 여기 있다 나이스
uh here there nice
uh here it is nice
여기 마음에 드네베개에 부드러움이나 시원한 음료에
here like on the pillow soft or cool [ W5@@ to drink
I like it here, on the soft pillow and on the cool drink
맛을 실제로 느낄 수 있다면 얼마나좋을까요이
taste actually feel can if How good is this
How nice it would be if I could actually taste it
드론 유용하지만 내 몸이 그리워느낌이 그리워 아픈 것도 배고픈 것도
drone useful but my body I miss feeling [ W5@@ miss sick nothing hungry nothing
The drone is useful, but I miss my body, I miss the feeling, being sick and hungry
그리고별 소용없다는 거 알지만 여기 조금만
and then useless  I know here little bit
And I know it's no use, but here's a little bit
더 머물 수 없을까요
More Stay Can No
can't you stay longer
어려운 거 없지
difficult hard no
Nothing difficult
기저귀도 펴고
Even diapers Unfold
Spread the diaper
아 나도 고양이처럼 살고 싶다 진짜
ah me too like a cat live want Really
Ah, I really want to live like a cat too
부러운 친구
Envious Friends
envious friend
나는 빠를 운영한 적이 있어 여기서가장 아늑한 곳이었지 내 무릎에
I got I got I got I got I got The most @@W5 here] Cozy It was a place my on my lap
I've run a bar, it's the coziest place here on my lap
드라이버를 박을 때까지 말이야 지금문 닫았어
driver until until  now [ W5@@ closed
Until I put the screwdriver in. Now the door is closed.
나를 화나게 하지만 내 유일한손님이야 쫓아버리지만
makes me makes me angry but my is the only guest I chase you away, but
Makes me angry, but my only customer drives me away
너희들은지금 너무 멋지지 않아 정말 괜찮아
you guys are now so cool not really It's okay
You guys are not so cool right now, it's really okay
해롭지 않을 것 같아
not harmful would not be would be would be like
I don't think it's harmful
담배 피는 뉘앙스 안에 아응 아는로봇이야 자주 봤어이 근처에 살고
cigarettes bleed nuance inside ah knowing I'm a robot often saw this near live
Inside the nuance of smoking, it's a robot I know. I've seen it often. I live around here.
있을걸 항상 도시를 떠나는 것에 대한이야기를 하던게 기억나 이해가 안
should be always city leaving being Talking about Korea  I remember I don't understand I don't
I don't remember how you always talked about leaving the city.
돼요 좋은 곳이잖아 왜 떠나지
OK Good That's where Why Leave
It's a good place, why are you leaving?
오 여기 뭔가홀로그램도 있고
oh here something like a hologram and
Oh, there's a hologram here too
자 일어나 아 뭐야
now wake up ah what is
wake up oh what
느닷없이 올라가서골골송하고 있네
Unexpectedly Goes up and down there
I'm suddenly up and screaming
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
내가 그럼 여기로 나왔고 그 다음에
I then here came out that Next
I then came out here and then
여기가 식당 빠 같은데
This is Restaurant Bar [It looks like W3@@
This looks like a restaurant bar
[음악]이 게임에서 1등 하려고 애인봇을
[Music] is in game 1st place try bot
[Music] I'm trying to win first place in this game
다운로드 하려고 했는데 악성코드가생겨버렸어 이유는 모르겠지만 지금은
download tried tried malicious code was created reason I don't know, now
I was going to download it, but there was a malicious code. I don't know why, but now
모든게 이상해 보여
everything weird shows
everything looks weird
나는 존재하는 모든 게임을마스터했지만 이것이 어떻게 작동하는지
I exists all mastered the game but this is [ W5@@ How works
I have mastered every game in existence but how this works
이해할 수 없어 내가 큰 그림을 보지못하는 거야
understand can don't I big picture don't see will
I can't understand. I can't see the big picture.
고대 기계에 대한 정보를 모으는 거같아서 별난 여자야 아 너도 이거
ancient machine  information gathering It looks like Weird It's a girl Ah You too This
You seem to be gathering information about ancient machines, so you're a weird girl. Ah, you have this too
아니야 혹시
no maybe
어이 노래가 훨씬 좋구만캐주얼 나는
hey the song is much nice casual I'm
Hey, the song is much better, but I’m casual
톤인을 모르는데 뭐 나는 거의 모든것을 좋아해
Tone in I don't know what I'm almost Everything [I like W6@@
I don't know ton-in, but I like almost everything
사진 잘 나왔네얘는 다 똑같은 얘기야
photo well came out everything the same I'm talking about
The picture came out well, it's all the same story
[음악]나 뭐 요리라도 해주는 줄 알았네
[Music] or What Cooking @@W3 serving] lines [ W5@@ Okay
[MUSIC] I thought I was cooking something
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
내가 가장 좋아하는 음료는 오일이야넌 뭘 좋아해
I the most favorite drinks oil you [ W5@@ what [I like W6@@
My favorite drink is oil. What do you like?
[음악]그렇게
[MUSIC] Like that
도 왠지 뭐 있을 것 같아
also somehow something something something like
I think there is something
뭐 있지 않을까
What Yes I guess
what could be
[박수]
[Applause]
[clap]
여기는 뭐 하면 되지어 여기가 이발소인가 아까 거기가
this is what is is this is Is it a barber shop earlier there
What can I do here? Is this a barber shop?
이발소 아닌가 보네 이런 일일 뿐이야그
Barber Shop Isn’t it I see Oh no Daily Only that
It looks like it's not a barber shop, it's just that
친구 여기 한번은 온 적이 있어 왜물어보는 건데
Friend Here Once Once Never Got Why are you asking is
Friends, I've been here once. Why are you asking?
내 가게를 나가면 바로 오른쪽에 거주구역이 있어
my shop go out right right The residence is is
When you exit my store, there is a residence area to the right.
오른쪽 나가면 오른쪽에어 저 위에 올라갈 수 있다
right go out right air that on top go up be be
If you go right, you can go right up there.
어떻게
how
아 뭐야순간이동함
Ah What is teleportation
Ah, what is it? Teleportation
아 여기다
ah here
Oh here
이발소는 사람들이 모이는 사교의장애였어 이야기하고 농담하고 비밀을
barber shop people gathering social disorder talking kidding secret
The barbershop was a social block where people gathered to talk, joke, and tell secrets.
나눴지 재밌는 곳이었어인간들이 사라진 후에도 캠페인들은
We shared Fun It was a place where humans disappeared even after [ W5@@ campaigns are
We shared. It was a fun place. Even after the humans disappeared, the campaigns continued.
가게를 계속 올려놨어 이발소가성공하면 머리카락이 꼭 필요한 것은
store continue put it on if the barbershop is successful hair must must must
Keeping the shop up
아니라는 사실을 뭐머리 뭐 다르는 거야
is not is true what what is different it's
What's the difference between the fact that it's not
생각해 보니까
Think See
Come to think of it
아 뭐 나사 같은거
ah what screw something like
Oh what a screw
느낌은 뭐지
feels like what is
what is the feeling
면봉귀 파주는 거 같은데 여기
cotton swabs Paju that's looks like here
It looks like they're selling cotton swabs here
나가서 오른쪽으로 가면 거주지역저기가 거주지역인가 보다
go out go to the right go to residence area over there residence area [than W5@@
If you go out and go to the right, you will see that the residential area is the residential area.
아 반갑습니다
Ah Nice to meet you
ah nice to meet you
오늘 밤에는 뭘 만들까 셰프아 혹시 이거 아세요
Today At night What Should I make Chef Maybe This Do you know
What should I make tonight Chef, do you know this?
진짜 돈을 지불할 순 없어돈이라니
real money pay net no money
You can't pay real money. Money.
[음악]야
[Music]
[music] hey
말도 안 되는 소리 했으니까 이거 어뭐야 이거
say not become sound  This What is this This
Because you said nonsense, what is this?
아 여기도 있네
Ah here too there
oh here too
야 이거는 좀진짜 그냥 돌아다니다 보면 나오겠다
Hey This is It's kinda real Just Go around See will appear
Hey, this is a bit real, it will come out if you just walk around
그렇지로봇이 인간의 일과 행동을 모방한다는
robots human work and actions emulate
That's right, robots imitate human work and behavior.
건 흥미로운 일이야 여기에서 버거와길거리 음식을 파는 거 같아 내가
stuff interesting stuff here burger and street [ W5@@ food selling stuff like i
It's interesting, I think they sell burgers and street food here
인간이었을 때 가장 가고 싶었던 곳이기억나요
was human when most went wanted Do you remember the place
Do you remember where you most wanted to go when you were a human?
작지만 친절하고 웨이터 이름은 기억안 나 m으로 시작하는 이름이었던 거
small kind waiter name is don't remember me m starting was the name was
It's small but friendly, I can't remember the waiter's name, it started with m
같은데
looks like
[음악]전환해줄까
[Music] Switch to
[Music] Should I switch?
친구 센티넬은 마주치지만 그 사악한놈들은 내 친구 파블로를 잡아갔어
Friends Sentinels are encounters Those Evil guys My Friend Pablo took
My friend Sentinel runs into it, but those evil guys took my friend Pablo.
지금 350년형의 지역 역사회를 하고있지
Now 350 year old Region Historical Society is doing
I'm doing a 350-year-old community history meeting.
근데 어차피 얘네들 안 죽지 않아지루한 시간은 똑같나
but anyway these guys not don't die It's not boring time is is it the same
But these guys don't die anyway, are the boring times the same?
엘리베이터 근처에서 걷기만 했는데센티는 소리 질렀어 수년 동안 우리는
elevator near walking only but centi sound [ W5@@ screamed years while we
All I could do was walk near the elevator, but Centy screamed. For years we were
표면에 살 수 없다는 말을들고 살았어
surface live can no say I lived
I lived with the saying that I couldn't live on the surface
우리는 그것을 사실로 받아들였고그런데 왜지
we it as fact accepted but why
We accepted it as fact, but why
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
한번 가볼까 어떤 식으로 나오는지
once should I go which way coming out
Shall we go once? How will it come out?
지금은 갈 필요 없을 것 같아
now will go need will not be will be Same
I don't think I need to go now
클레멘타인이랑 얘기하는게 더 우선일듯
with Clementine talking about more should come first
I think it's better to talk to Clementine.
자판기 요소 같은 거 없어 보이는데
vending machine element like thing no looks like
There doesn't seem to be any vending machine elements.
실납니다 여기 옷가게군요너도 하루 종일 시끄러운 음악을 트는
I'm bored Here A clothing store, you too all day all day loud music
I'm sorry, this is a clothing store. You also play loud music all day.
듣는 녀석들과 한 패는 아무것도만지지 마 시끄럽게 굴지도 말고
hears with guys one loses touches nothing Don't loudly might be cool [Not W8@@
Don't touch anything with the guys who listen Don't be loud
예상도 안 돼
Expected Not Yes
Unexpected
까칠하게 고르기는
Tough Picking
to choose harshly
탈의실인가 보네
Is it a changing room I see
Looks like a locker room
아이템 삽입은 뭐야
item insert is what
what is insert item
테이프 같은 거 있으면 할 수 있나보다
Tape Like Thing If Do Be I guess
I think you can do it with some kind of tape
어 그냥 여기로 나오는 거구나 뭐야난 뭐라도 있는 줄 알았네
uh just here coming out that's What am I Anything in give okay
Uh, you're just coming here, what, I thought there was something
여기 왠지
here somehow
here for some reason
어디까지 올라갈 때야여기다
How far go up It's time here
How far do you go?
지렸다
I'm tired
tired
깜빡인데
blinks
I blink
어경찰 뺐지 나이스
Police Officer Removed Nice
Nice
간지 어디 갔어경찰 패치 아 이건가
kanji where gone police patch ah Is this
Where did you go? Police patch Oh, is this it?
맞지 그 방금 얻은 거 네온사인 옆에거
right that just got got that Neon Signed [next to W6@@
That's right, the one I just got next to the neon sign
금 색깔 하나 있네
Gold Color One Yes
there is a gold color
그 다음에 여기 구석에는갈 필요가 있나
that then here corner need [ Is there W5@@
Do I need to go to the corner after that?
못 들어가네
can't goes in
I can't go in
피눈물 흘리고 있다[음악]
tears of blood shedding there [music]
I'm shedding bloody tears [music]
센티넬은 지옥에 가라 아웃사이더 만세
Sentinel Hell Go Outsider Hooray
Sentinel go to hell Long live the outsider
내가 못 참지고양이 밥 좀 주라고 나도 고양이에
I Can't Cat Bob Some Give me me too cat
I can't stand it. Give me some food for the cat.
밥 먹여주고 싶은데뭐 먹을게 없는데
Food Feed me I want something I'll eat [I don't have W4@@
I want to feed you, but I have nothing to eat
미드타운에서 가장 트렌디한 가겠지만가게의 주인이 꽤 심술궂어 맞아
Midtown Most Trendy @@W3 of the store] Owner pretty nasty right
It's the trendiest store in Midtown, but the owner of the store is pretty nasty.
쓰레기더라고
It's garbage
It was trash
쓰레기더라
It was garbage
It's trash
어 미안 어 이거 뭐 이거 되네 뭐임
uh sorry uh this what this works what
uh sorry uh what is this what is this what is it
아이고 아이고 주머니 뭐 있나 없는거 같은데
oops oops pouch what is is not That's [It looks like W6@@
Oops, oops, I don't think there are pockets or anything.
아 미안하다 미안하다[음악]
Ah Sorry Sorry [Music]
Oh sorry sorry [music]
미안하다
Sorry
sorry
아 너 아까 꺼지라고 했던 거
ah you earlier told you to stop said huge
Oh, you said go away
여기지 거주 지역 3층으로 가야 돼
here residence area 3rd floor go OK
I have to go to the third floor of the residential area here.
이거 멍청이 우리도 너희를 볼 수있어
this idiot us too ye see I can
this asshole we can see you too
아CCTV 보고 얘기했던 거예요
Ah CCTV reported talked about was
Ah, I was talking about watching CCTV.
센트레는 우리 집에 카메라 설치한이후로 삶이 지루해졌어
Center We Home Camera After installation Life is I'm getting bored
Life has become boring since Centre installed a camera in our house.
감시하나 보네어
Watch Bonaire
Watch one Bonaire
훔치면 안 돼 너가
steal no can you
you can't steal
땡땡과 미코를 그리고 날 위에 뭔가해준다면 하나 줄 수 있어 보안
Dink and Miko and me on Do something one give be be security
If you do something with Tintin and Miko and something on me, I can give you one security
카메라 세대를 설치했어 아그래 오케이
camera gen installed ok ok
I installed the camera generation, ok
오케이 오케이충분 충분
ok ok enough enough
okay okay enough enough
충분하지
not enough
보안카메라 3대만 꺼주면테이프 하나 준대 아까 하나
security camera 3 units turn off the tape one Jundae [ W5@@ earlier one
If you turn off the 3 security cameras, they will give you a tape.
트는 거 어디에 있었지 아까 봤었잖아어느 가게에 있었지
was was where was was was Which one at the store was there
Where was it? I saw it before, which store was it at?
아까 무슨 가게에 있었는데
@@W0 earlier] what at the store was there
What store were you in?
아웃 가게캐릭터 시트를 잃어버렸다는게 무슨
out shop character sheet lost what
What does it mean to lose an out shop character sheet?
소리야 나는 일주일 내내이 세션을준비했다고
I'm talking I'm a week this whole prepared a session
So, I've been preparing for this session all week.
미안해 어디 뒀는지 잊어버렸어 그러다해보자 내가 그거 돈 벌러 갈게 가자
I'm sorry Where I put it I forgot Let's do that I That Money Earn I'll go Let's go
I'm sorry, I forgot where I put it. Let's do that.
똑바로 하란 말이야 일을
Straight Harran I mean Do
I mean do it right
이거다맞지 아까 그거 3이라고
this is all right earlier that 3
This is all right, that was 3 earlier
역삼각형 3이랑 5 35 오케이 여기2층이라는 거네 3층 맞네 3층에
Inverted Triangle 3 5 35 ok This is the 2nd floor that's 3rd floor that's right 3rd floor
Inverted triangle 3 and 5 35 OK, this is the second floor. That’s the third floor. On the third floor.
5호실이네 3층에5호실이야
Room 5 Room 5 on the 3rd floor
It's room 5. It's room 5 on the 3rd floor.
알았지어 마음에 들어
Okay Like Listen
ok i like it
얘도 했잖아
said
he did it too
어 나이스
uh Nice
A Nice
마음에 드네
I like I like
I like it
이제 두 개만 더 해주면 돼 두 개만더
now two only more   two gamander
Now I just need to do two more, just two more
좀 숨는 거 내려가는 길 올라가는 길올라가기 전에
little hide go go down way go up up the road [before W7@@
On the way down, on the way up, before going up
조금만 더 조사하고 뭐가 있는지
little bit more looking into what what
Do a little more research and see what
여기도 올라가는 길
here going up road
The way up here too
CCTV 두 개만 더 찾으면 되는데아 저쪽에 하나 있다
CCTV two only more find Ah over there one there
I just need to find two more CCTVs. There's one over there.
발판을 밟아서 넘어가야 되는데
step on the footrest step on it you have to go over it can do it
I have to step on the steps to get over it.
여기도 하나 있네
here too one there
there's one here too
오케이근데 이런 거 막 제거해도 되는 건가
ok but like this stuff just removed Become Become
Okay, but can I just remove this?
그다음 적어 남았어 이거는
then write down left this is
Then I wrote it down, this is
찾아오는 거 아니야
is coming is is not
I'm not coming
알았다 가져와
Got it [Bring W1@@
okay bring it
[박수]카세트 테이프
[Applause] Cassette Tape
[Applause] Cassette tape
얻었어[박수]
Got it [Applause]
우리 노래 즐겨줘 마음에 들 거야
We Songs Enjoy I like guys will
Enjoy our song, you will like it
춤추고 있네가기 전에
dancing stay and go before
You're dancing before you go
옷가게 먼저 갔다가 노래 한번 카세트테이프 끼워보자
clothing store first then song once cassette Tape Insert
Let's go to a clothing store first and insert a cassette tape for a song
[음악]뭐냐 이거 어
[Music] What is it This Uh
[Music] What is this?
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
뭐야
What is
what
젠장 이거 어떻게 끄지 어 지금 얘가한눈팔았을 때 뭐 하는 건가
Damn this how turn it off uh now Replying to @@W5 @W10]
Damn how do you turn this off uh what are you doing when he's looking away?
[음악]어 자켓
[Music] uh jacket
[Music] A jacket
훔치기 어 나이스[음악]
Steal uh Nice [Music]
Steal A Nice [Music]
가게에서 우리가 훔친 재킷이야나중에 뭐
at the store we stole jacket later what
This is the jacket we stole from the store.
잠입할 때 쓰는 거겠구먼 어 이제클레멘타인 만나러 가자
infiltrate when write I guess uh Now Clementine to meet let's go
It must be used when infiltrating. Now let's go see Clementine.
3층 5호실
3rd floor Room 5
3rd floor room 5
3층 2 3
3rd floor 2 3
딱 고양이 들어갈 수 있는 길인데
Just Cat Go In Be In Way but
It's the only way for cats to enter.
여기에 있나 클레멘타인
Here Is there Clementine
Are you here Clementine
어 뭐야어디 조심해
uh what are you watch out
What is it, be careful
어 너가 센 아니야 신경 쓰지 마 넌누구지
uh you sen no care  Ma Who are you
Uh you're not strong, don't mind who you are
뭘 원해 이거
what want this
what do you want this
잠깐 드디어 그 녀석이 누군가를보내기로 한 거야 너가 내 신입인가
wait finally that guy sent someone [ W5@@ is is you are is my is new
Wait, he finally decided to send someone. Are you my new recruit?
보구나난 별로 안 크네 하수오 어떻게
I see Not so much Not That's great Ha Suo How
You see, I'm not very tall, how can I?
통과한 거지 꽤 재주가 있구나 나는엔트빌리지를 떠난 이후로 줄곧
Passed Beggar Quite Got Got I left [Since W7@@ all the way
You passed, you're quite talented. Ever since I left Ent Village,
아웃사이드로 가는 길을 찾고 있었어하지만 센티넬은 항상
outside going way looking was but [ W5@@ sentinel is always
I've been looking for a way to the outside but the Sentinel is always
감시했지어
watched
I watched
따라오렴
Follow me
follow me
여기에 뭐 있을 것 같아여기서 나온 이유가 있을 거야
here what would be would be would be here came reason be be
I think there must be something here. There must be a reason why it came out of here
[음악]어
[Music]uh
[music] uh
아니야[음악]
no [music]
뜨는데포인트
floating point
여기 많은데
here there are many
there are many here
아지트인가
Is it a hideout
is it a hideout
아니고 아니잖아
[It's not W0@@ [It's not W1@@
no it's not
뭐라도 있는 줄 알았네
anything in give ok
I thought there was something
그냥 힐링 공간이었네
Just Healing It was a space
It was just a healing space
어디 갔어야
where should have gone
나는요즘이 오래된 지하철을 이용할 계획을
I have these days old subway available plans
I plan to use this old subway these days
세우고 있어 시동을 위한 키도 있어필요한 건 전원을 공급하는 원자
set up got start for key also @W5] thing power supply atom
I'm standing up. I've got a key to start it. All I need is an atom to power it up.
배터리 뿐이야그
battery only that
It's just the battery
이름은 몰라 부머즈키가 금사슬을 걸친로봇이야
The name is I don't know Boomerzkey is A robot wearing a gold chain It's a robot
I don't know the name, Boomerzki is a robot wearing a gold chain.
너처럼재빠르면 공장에 몰래 들어갔는데
If you're as quick as you to the factory secretly went in
If I was quick like you, I would sneak into the factory.
문제가 없을 거예요
problem no would be
there will be no problem
목걸이
necklace
아까 나한테 꺼지라고 했던 놈인가걔가 좀 힙하게 생기긴 했었는데 걔
@@W0 earlier] told me to go away said is he kinda hip looks like [I did W8@@ he
Is he the guy who told me to quit earlier? He looked a bit hip, but he
아닌가
isn't it
is not it
너 맞지 이거어디서 구했지 어 너 아웃사이 내지
you right Where is this I got it uh You outsider to
You're right, where did you get this from?
어쩐지이어서싸가지가 없더라
Somehow it's so cheap didn't exist
For some reason, there was nothing cheap
배터리가 바로 저 공장에 전력을공급하고 있지만 전체가 제한 지역이고
battery is right that @@W3 to factory] supply power but full restricted local
The battery is supplying power to that factory, but the whole is a restricted area.
철저하게 부어 받고 있어직원이 아니면 돌려보냈지
thoroughly poured received got an employee or I sent it back
I'm pouring it thoroughly, I sent it back if it wasn't an employee
하지만 내가 누구
but I who
but who am i
아 작업자 헬멧도 가져와야 되네재킷이랑
Ah Worker Helmet I need to bring with jacket
Oh, you should also bring a worker's helmet. A jacket and
헬멧나 재킷은 있어도 헬멧은 없는데
helmet jacket but helmet but no
I have a helmet or a jacket, but I don't have a helmet.
중앙 사거리 쪽 잘 보라고 아 여기있네 여기 안 들어갔었구나
center range side well see ah here here not went in
Take a good look at the central intersection. Oh, it's here.
재입고 되는 동안 아무도 가게가들어갈 수 없어 저 녀석이 얼마나
restocked being while no one entering can no that that guy how much
No one can enter the store while it is being restocked.
무능한지 생각해보면 아무래도 한참걸릴 거예요
Is it incompetent If you think about it I guess It will take a while will be
If you think about incompetence, it will probably take a long time
어허
uh huh
Uh huh
얘도 아니고얘도 아니고
and this one [Not W1@@ and this one [Not W2@@ but
It's not him, it's not him
이름 안 뜨고아 여기도 공간이 있었구나
name not  here too no space There was
I can't remember the name, there was a space here too
얘 같은데 얘 깨워야 되나 보다올라가서 뭐 떨어뜨리는 거 같은데
kid looks like kid wake up is See go up what drop that thing looks like
It looks like him. Should I wake him up? It looks like he's going up and dropping something.
야 일어나 어 너 찾잖아 애들이
hey wake up uh you you're looking for Kids
Hey wake up I'm looking for you guys
빨리 가서 일해야지
quickly go I have to work
I have to go to work soon
나간다
goes out
I'm going
야 친구 데려왔다
hey friend brought me
hey i brought a friend
시간이 몇 시야 시간이
time few time time
what time is the time
제정신이야 아 미안해술 좀 마시느라고 그랬어
I'm crazy ah sorry kinda I was drinking That's right
I'm insane, I'm sorry, I was drinking a little
오케이 나이스
OK Nice
okay nice
들어가자 들어가자
Let's go Let's go
let's go in let's go in
모자가 어디에 있을까
hat where
where is the hat
나가 나가 나가
out out out
go out go out
오케이 나이스나왔어
Okay Nice came out
ok nice came out
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
잠깐 뒤돌아볼래
wait I want to look back
I want to look back for a moment
어 아주 청소부 같구만
uh very janitor looks like
Uh, you look like a janitor
그래 가자
Yes Let's go
yes let's go
나 목걸이는 빼야 되지 않을까 너무플렉스인데 어 청소부가 금목걸이를
or The necklace is should be removed would be wouldn't it be Too flexy uh Janitor Gold necklace
Shouldn't I take off the necklace? It's too flex.
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]목걸이는 빼야지
[Music] The necklace is I have to take it off
[Music] Take off the necklace
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
상자 안을 봐야 되지 않을까겉에 상표만 보나 봐
box inside must see not outwardly trademark only look look
Shouldn't I look inside the box? I guess I only see the label on the outside
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
안전할 때 나가야 돼 뭐가 지나갈지도
safe when go out go what It might pass
You have to leave when it's safe, don't know what will pass
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]좋아 좋아
[MUSIC] OK OK
[Music] Alright alright
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아 하필 반대로 넘어가야 되나
Ah I must say on the contrary I have to go over or
Oh, must I go the opposite way?
[음악]그림자 따라서
[Music] Shadows So
[MUSIC] Follow the shadows
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아주 천재 고양이가 따로 없구나
very genius cat apart no
There is no such thing as a very genius cat
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
중앙에 있는가 원자 배터리였나 저게
@@W0 in the center] is atoms was the battery that was
Is it in the center, is it an atomic battery, is that
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
하나의 배치시키는 건가
one placing or
Are you placing one
아 이거 데려오는거다 이리
Oh This I'm bringing you Come here
Oh, I'm bringing this here
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
하나는 내가 밟으면 되겠네 아직
One is I step on will be yet
I can step on one yet
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아 좋아 너 가져오면 되지
ah okay you bring not
oh ok you can bring it
너 가져와야지 어외계 물체야 너 가져와야 될 거
You You should bring it Extraterrestrial world It's an object You should bring would be would be
You should bring it. It's an alien object. You should bring it.
아니야 이걸로 밟아주면 되나
no with this stepping on it will work
No, can I step on this
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
오케이
ok
okay
[음악]튕겼다 이제 잽싸게 튀면 되나
[Music] Bounced now quickly bounced now
[Music] It bounced, can I just bounce quickly?
[음악]여기 이제 시설 멈춰 버렸어
[Music] Here Now Facility STOP Abandoned
[MUSIC] Here the facility has stopped
배터리 챙겨가지고 해냈다빨리 센트를 나타나기 전에 나가야 돼
battery take it done it quickly cents appear Before Go Go
I did it with my batteries. I need to get out before the cents show up.
클레멘탈한테 가야 돼
To Clemental Go Go
We have to go to Clemental.
아 퍼즐 너무 가볍게 풀어버렸네 좀헤매기도 했어야 되는데 그죠 여러분들
Ah puzzle too much lightly solved it Even wandering around [Should have done W6@@ can do it That's right everyone
Oh, I solved the puzzle too lightly.
나가는 길은 좋다 그렇지 들어가는길은 빡세는데 나가는 길 빠르게 좋네
out the way is good right the way in It’s tough goes out way quickly nice
The way out is good, the way in is tough, but the way out is fast.
센티넬이 막아놨네
Sentinel blocked
Sentinel blocked it
나가서도 춤추고 있냐너희는 우리의 자리를 훔칠 수 있어도
go out dance are you guys our seat Steal Can Even
Are you dancing even when you go out? Even if you guys can steal our place
우리의 움직임을 훔칠 수 없어
us move steal can don't
Can't steal our moves
춤을 출 수 없다 아무런 의미가 없어
dance out can no no Meaning no
I can't dance, there's no point
입어 너희가 우리 구역을 막는다고전부 해결될 거라고 생각해
put on you guys we zone blocking everything [ W5@@ will be solved would be think
Put it on. I think it will all be solved if you block our block.
범죄자가 내 빈티지 카드 컬렉션을노리고 있을까
Criminal My Vintage Cards Targeting the Collection Will there be
Are criminals targeting my vintage card collection?
이 모든 일이 허무하게 되어버렸어
this all things meaningless became
All of this has become futile
난 고향이다 들어갈 수 있는 방법은늘 있지
I am is home is is is The way is always there
I'm home, there's always a way to get in
킹냥의 힘을
Kingnyang's Strength
king's power
그냥 들어가도 될 것 같다고
would just be would be would be would be would be like
I think I can just go in
어이가 없네
Wow doesn't exist
It's absurd
어이가 없어 버리네
Wow doesn't exist throws it away
I'm dumbfounded
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
반대쪽으로 가야 된다
opposite go become
have to go the other way
여기
here
[박수]
[Applause]
[clap]
깜짝 놀랐네저기 건너편에도 있을 줄 몰랐네
surprise surprised over there on the other side will be there line I didn't know
I was surprised, I didn't know you were on the other side
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아 그만해라 한 명씩 뭐 구경만 써
ah stop one one what Just look at write
Oh stop, just watch something one by one
어
uh
[음악]여기인 거지
[Music] Here beggar
[Music] It's here
[음악]안녕
[Music] Hi
[MUSIC] Hi
여기로 가면 가만히
Go here go stay still
Be quiet if you go here
오케이 어이
ok hey
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
Where are you
너 위에 숨었구나 여기 이제야 가는길이었구만
you on top hid here now It was the way to go
I hid above you. I was finally on my way here.
클레멘타인 어디
Clementine where
where is clementine
어디 갔지
Where went
where did you go
화장실 똥 싸고 있나
Toilet Poop Cheap Is there
Are you pooping in the bathroom?
클레멘타인 어디 갔어
Clementine Where gone
where did clementine go
이만 이거 뭐야단서보드 보기
Iman This What is the clue board View
Look at the clue board
답은 내 물건에 있다 그리고 4개의기후가 있음 답은 내 물건에 있다
the answer is my stuff is and 4 climates have answer my stuff There is
The answer is in my stuff and there are 4 climates The answer is in my stuff
4개의 기호가 있습니다
has 4 has has
There are 4 symbols
오케이화분 보석
OK pot Jewel
OK potted jewelry
화분 보석꽃병
Planter Jewel Vase
planter jewelry vase
이것도 하나인데 이거 아닌가
This is is one This is isn’t it
This is one too, isn't this?
[음악]뭔가 찾았어 아무것도 보이지 않는데
[Music] Something Found Nothing I don't see I don't see
[MUSIC] I found something, I can't see anything
확실히
definitely
surely
첫 번째 거화분 세
first second big pot three
three first pots
번째 거 꼬깔모자 해 아닌데 뭐 두번째 보석 마지막 저거는
th big cocked hat year not what second jewel last that's
The second one is not a conical hat, but what is the second jewel and the last one?
이거 아님완전 비슷하게 생겼는데
This or not similar to looks like
It looks exactly like this
내 센서는 기체 상태에 무해한화학물질만 감지할 수 있어 내가
in sensor is gas [@@W3 in W3@@ state] only harmless chemicals Detect Can Got I
My sensor can only detect chemicals that are harmless in the gaseous state.
기억하는 편안했는지는 느낌은 제한할수 없어
remembers is comfortable feels can't limit doesn't exist
I can't limit the feeling of whether it was comfortable to remember
캠페리언도 나처럼 냄새를 맡지못하는데 왜 그런 걸까
Camperion like me smell can't smell it why @@W5 like that] I guess
The camperion can't smell like me, so why?
용기 아래에도 메시지가 숨겨져 있어나는
container also under messages hidden got me
A message is hidden even under the courage
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
집안에 뭐 힌트 단서가 있다고 하니까
in the house what hint clue said Because
Because there is a hint clue in the house
뭐야 뭔데어 아파트에 있다네 정말 이상하네
what what in the apartment there really That's strange
What is it? It's in an apartment. It's really strange.
뭐가좀 없겠네
What's up I don't think there is one
I don't have anything
아 여기 뭔가 남아 있어나이트클럽 어 이거구나
oh here something stay there night club uh this is it
Ah, there's something left here Nightclub Uh this is it
꼬깔콘나이트클럽
Kkokkalkon Night Club
Kkokkalcon Nightclub
나는 나이트클럽나이트클럽으로 여기 위에도 있을 듯
I'm nightclub nightclub here above be [ Looks like W5@@
I'd be up here as a nightclub nightclub
뭔지그렇지 않고서야
What is it
unless it's something
위에 공간이 있을 리가 없어
on no space no no no
There can't be room above
이거다
This is
this is it
[음악]아
[MUSIC] Ah
블레이저랑 있어 나는
with blazer [I have W1@@ I am
I'm with the blazer
다 찾으면 이제 순서 조합 다해주겠지
all find now order combinations all I'll give it to you
If you find them all, I'll put together the order now.
아 이게 첫 번째 건가 그러면은 이거맞지
ah this is first second is then is this is right
Oh, is this the first one then this is right
향 나는 거 향을 표현한 거였구나
incense incense incense incense incense That was it
I guess it was the expression of incense.
마지막 이거다안 뜨는 거 보니까
The last This is all rises is looks
I saw that the last one didn't open
이거 다 위에 이거 아님
this everything over this not
Above all of this, not this
오케이나이트 클럽
OK Night Club
내려가는 것 좀 편하게 못 내려가나요빌어먹어
go down go down go down go down go down go down Fuck me
Can't you go down comfortably?
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어 고생들 하고[음악]
uh troublemakers and [Music]
Oh, you're having a hard time [Music]
응
yes
huh
너랑 관계 없는 곳이야 저리가
with you relationship without is where go away
It's a place that has nothing to do with you, go away
뒤로 올라가야 될 것 같다고뒤
go back go up go back go back go back
I think I will have to go back
뒤로 올라가야 될 것 같아뒤
go back go up go back go back go back
I think I have to climb back
[음악]클럽을 들어갈 수 있는
[Music] club get in be in in
[MUSIC] I can get into the club
길이 여기에 이렇게 꼬마야
length here like this kid
Gil is such a kid here
너 뭐하나
You What are you doing
what are you doing
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
뭐 하나
what one
안녕 잘 지냈어
hello well how are you
hello how are you
나 얘 본 적 있나
I I I saw I I
have i seen him
욕은 나는 척을 하세요
swear I pretend do
Pretend you're cursing
클럽 들어가는 길을찾아야 되는데
club enter must find the way can be
I need to find my way into the club
[음악]이거는 어디지
[MUSIC] This is where
[Music] Where is this
중앙색 노란종우형에 들어가면 있어요 아 이거
Central color Yellow Jongwoo hyung goes in is there Ah [ W5@@ this
If you go into the central yellow bell cow, you will find it. Oh this
어 여기 원래 닫혀 있었던 데였나아 맞네
uh here original closed was having Was it That's right
Uh, this place was originally closed. That's right.
닫혀 있었던데 열렸네 아까 못들어가던데 저는
closed was there was open earlier couldn't go in I am
It was closed, but it's open. I couldn't go in earlier, but I
센티넬 사람들을 보호하는 것이목적이었어 범주를 퇴치하고 질서를
sentinels people protecting was the purpose categories exterminate order
Its purpose was to protect the people of the Sentinel. It was aimed at eradicating categories and restoring order.
유지하는 일 말이야 하지만 도시의생활이 어려워지고 여러 집단이
keep work mean but city life [ W5@@ becomes difficult multiple groups
maintenance work, but life in the city becomes difficult and various groups
정확하게 시작하면서센트는 빠르게 권력자의 사냥개가
Exactly Starts cents Quickly Powerful Hounds
Starting precisely, Cent quickly becomes the hound of the powerful.
되었지 그들은 도시를 통제하기 위한완벽한 도구였어 순종적이고 의심하지
was they city control perfect for It was a tool obedient doubtful
Turned out they were the perfect tools to control the city, obedient and suspicious
않고 지칠 줄 모르니까요인류가 멸망한 후에도 그들은 계속해서
without exhausted line I don't know if humanity perished [ Even after W5@@ they are on and on
After the end of mankind, they continue to
통제했어항상 제 임무를 다하고 있지 가차없이
controlled always my mission done got Relentlessly
I'm in control, I'm always doing my duty relentlessly
어뭔가
something
뿌듯하다메모리 많이 모아 가지고
proud memory a lot gather have
I am proud of having collected a lot of memories
하나도 어디이건 이빨 빠져버렸네
not one anywhere teeth I'm missing
I've lost a tooth anywhere
이거는 지금 못할 것 같은데 나 이거본 적 없는 거 같은데 아 있나
this is now can't would be looks like I this is ever no that looks like Ah Is
I don't think I can do this right now, but I don't think I've seen this before.
어 이거 설마뒤에 계단
uh this no way stairs
Oh no way this is the stairs behind
아마존 나이트 클럽이야
Amazon Night Club
It's an Amazon nightclub
위로 올라가야 되나 위에 길이 있나
up up up over length Is there
I have to go up, but is there a way up?
올라가야 될 것 같으니까
should go up would be would be would be like
'Cause I think I'll have to go up
이 녀석
this guy
안녕 여기 어떻게 올라왔네 우리랑파티 할래 자 들어가서
Hello Here How are you It's up Party with us I want to do it now go in
Hi, how did you get up here? Do you want to party with us?
만져봐봐 얘기 좀 하게즐기고 있는 꼬마야 너 이거 알아
Touch it talk a little bit and have fun with kid you this I know
Touch it, let's talk, kid having fun, you know this
사용법 몰라 이거 훔쳤어너는 상상도 못할 바다
Usage I don't know This I stole you Imagine can't sea
I don't know how to use it, I stole this. The sea you can't imagine
어디서 훔쳤는지
Where stole
where did you steal
야 이거 드래곤 뭐야 이거
hey this dragon what this
Hey what is this dragon
내 마스크가 마음에 들어 내가 직접만들었어
I I I like I I I made it myself
I like my mask so I made it myself
센티넬의 스캔을 방해하는 데다 멋있어보이기까지 하나도
Sentinel's scanning interfering with and even looking cool not one
It interferes with the Sentinel's scans and doesn't even look cool.
어 여러분 같네요
uh everyone [It looks like W2@@
oh you look like
여러분 같네
everyone [Same as W1@@
It's like you
나는 오늘 춤 동작을 얻으려고경비원에게 추가비용을 지불했어 그가
I today dance action tell the guard to get [ W5@@ extra charge paid he
I paid the security guard extra money to get the dance moves today.
여가 시간에 홀로그램을 프로그래밍하거든
@@W0 at leisure] [@@W1 at W1@@ time] @@W2 hologram] and program
program holograms in your spare time
[음악]바텐더 거기 손님 VIP 발코니 못
[Music] Bartender There Guest VIP Balcony never
[Music] Bartender there guest VIP balcony nail
들어가 비공개로 사용하고 있거든블레이저라는 자가 예약한 거 같아요
go in privately use there's a blazer is [ W5@@ reserved that's looks like
I went in and was using it privately. I think someone called Blazer made a reservation.
[음악]왼쪽 오른쪽 삐뽀 쓱싹 이것이 제게
[Music] Left Right Bippo Squeak This is to me
[Music] Left right beep beep this is me
맛 댄스
Taste Dance
taste dance
이[음악]
This [Music]
this [music]
클럽은 형편이 없네 그 한심은vip룸에 가려고 했는데 나를
club is is in poor condition is not there that pathetic in the vip room tried to go tried me
The club sucks. That pathetic person tried to go to the VIP room
쫓아냈어 나를 믿어줘 그래서보복으로이 레버를 그냥 훔쳤어
kicked me out trust me trust me so as retaliation lever just stole
I kicked it out trust me so I just stole this lever in retaliation
음료를 가져다주면이 쓸모없는 레버를줄게 어
drink bring me this useless I'll give you a lever uh
Bring me a drink and I'll give you this useless lever
음료음료를 가져다주면
Beverages bring them
If you bring a drink
이거 빛나는구만
This It shines
It shines
레버 핸들 얻었어 레버 핸들간지 나는구만 맛있네
lever handle got lever handle I'm fine It's delicious
I got the lever handle. It's delicious.
여러분
everyone
DJ
시드 왔습니다파티를 시작해 볼까요
Sid Here's the party Let's start Let's see
Sid is here, let's start the party
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
한번 해볼까어 나 이거 안 되네 지금
once should I try or this not It's done now
I want to try this I can't do this right now
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
해보고 싶다 이거 뭔가 있을 것같은데 지금 안 되나 봐
try want this something be Looks like now not looks like look
I want to try this.
[음악]어
[Music]uh
[music] uh
레버
Lever
lever
어 나이스 지금
uh nice now
ah nice now
위로 올라왔어
up up
came up
아 올라가기 전에 메모리 찾을 수있어요 잠깐만
ah go up before memory find You can Wait a minute
Oh, you can find the memory before it goes up. Wait a minute.
올라가면 못 찾아요
go up can't look for
I can't find it when I go up
어 여기 뭐야
uh here what
uh what is this
아 이거 뭐 엘리베이터 같은데 그런가보네
Ah This What Elevator [Similar to W4@@ Is that so? Seen
Ah, this looks like an elevator, I guess.
[음악]아
[MUSIC] Ah
야 이거는
hey this is
장난꾸러기들만 찾을 수 있는 곳이구만여기네
Naughty Guys Find Can  This is where
It's a place only mischievous people can find.
내가 인간이었을 때 친구들과 모여서밤새 파티를 하고 냈어 덕분에 다음날
I was when I was human when with friends got together all night Party and paid [Thanks to W8@@ the next day
When I was human, I got together with my friends and partyed all night. Thanks to you, the next day
아침에 늘 힘들었지 살 수 없는표면에 가는 것보단 이곳에서 즐거움을
in the morning always it was hard year old be On the surface without go rather than here fun
It was always hard in the morning, rather than going to an unlivable surface, I had fun here
찾는게 기분 좋았거든 하지만 지하생활의 환경은 점점 더 열악해졌고
Looking for Feeling I liked it But Underground life The environment is getting worse getting worse getting worse
It felt good to find it, but the conditions in underground life were getting worse and worse.
회사와 같은 기업의 자본주의적 탐욕과센티넬이 만든 경찰국가도 더
company and same company capitalistic greed and sentinels made by police state also more
The capitalist greed of corporations such as corporations and the police state created by Sentinels are also more
추악해졌지 이제 우리가 왜 이렇게됐는지 기억이 났어
got ugly now us why this is [ W5@@ I remember I got it
It got ugly Now I remembered why we ended up like this
와우 아 두 개 아 이빨 빠져가지고씁쓸하구만
Wow Ah Two Two Ah teeth , it's bittersweet
Wow ah two ah my teeth are falling out It's bittersweet
아 살짝 길 만드는 거 같은 느낌이네길
ah slightly way making almost like I hope
Oh, I hope it feels like making a little road
하나씩 다 둘러봐야겠다
one by one all I need to look around
I'll have to look around each one
어 이거다됐어 됐어 됐어
uh That’s it that’s it that’s it
Uh, that’s it, it’s it, it’s it
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
블레이즈 어디 가냐 어드디어 다 왔는데
Blaze Where Are you going Where are you Everything I came
Blaze, where are you going?
화장실 가나
Toilet Ghana
toilet kana
[음악]반갑다
[Music] Nice to meet you
나는 센티널도 아주 좋은 관계를유지하고 있어
I sentinel also very good keeping relationship [ There is W5@@
I also have a very good relationship with the Sentinels.
다른 애들이 센트레일에 왜 그렇게많이 불평하는지 모르겠어
other kids on the centerrail why so much [ W5@@ Are you complaining I don't know
I don't know why the other kids complain about Centerrail so much
클레멘타에 묶여 있는데 블레이저쓰레기 같은 놈 설마 어 아닌가
clementa tied up got blazer trash like bastard no way uh isn’t it
I'm tied to Clementa, but I can't believe he's a blazer trash
어일석이조네 생각만큼 생각만큼 똑똑하지
I'm confused As much as I thought As much as I thought Not as smart as
It's crazy, you're as smart as you think
않구나 작은 고양이에 어쨌든 나쁜감정이 있어서 그런 건 아니란다 단지
nope small cat anyway bad feelings there is that thing no just
It's not because I have bad feelings for the little cat anyway, it's just
사업일 뿐이지
business day only
it's just business
배신이었네꺼져 할 때부터
It was a betrayal do [From W2@@
It was a betrayal, ever since I said goodbye
했는데[음악]
did [Music]
I did [music]
금목걸이부터가 사업이고 돈이야난 오점이나 동지애보다 돈을 더
Start with a gold necklace It's business It's money It's a stain More than camaraderie money more
Gold necklaces are business, and money is more money than stains or camaraderie
중요하게 생각해둘 다 끌고가
Importantly Think about it Everything Drag
Take everything you think is important
[음악]애용 소리 들렸어 방금
Favorite [Music] Sound Heard Just
[Music] I heard your favorite sound just now
어 내 가방 어디 갔어 어비 어디 가서 비
uh my bag where gone Irby where go non
Uh where did my bag go
그렇지난 스마트한 고양이다
That's right Smart It's a cat
That's right, I'm a smart cat
감옥프리즌 브레이크를 찍어야겠구만
Prison Prison Break I need to shoot
I'll have to shoot the prison prison break
이거 해주고
this do it
do this
천재 천재 못하는게 없다 못하는게없어
genius genius nothing nothing nothing
Genius genius, there is nothing you can't do, there is nothing you can't do
헐
Huh
omg
고문 받고 있나 봐
Advisor Get Got Look
I guess you're being tortured
전기충격 같은 거 다 하고 있나
Electric shock same thing everything and Is there
Are you doing something like an electric shock?
여기 들어가야 되는데
Here should go in should be
I have to go in here
걸리지 말고
takes , not
don't get caught
여기 아래로 내려가는 거
here down down go
going down here
방들에 다 들어갈 수가 있네
rooms all go in number there
I can go into all the rooms
아 바로 내려갈걸뒤로 바로 잽싸게 달라고 하면 되는데
ah right go down right quickly Ask for would be would be
Oh, you should go down right away, but you can ask for it quickly
타이밍 때문에[음악]
Timing Because [Music]
Because of the timing [music]
대기 대기
wait wait
waiting waiting
어 여기 있다
uh here there
uh here it is
찾았다
Found
found
야 비 없어졌어 비 어 저기 있다고
hey non gone non uh over there says
Hey, the rain is gone, the rain is over there
지금 비가 없으니까 소통이 안 돼요그렇지 해석할 수가 없잖아 고양이랑
now rain no no communication no Yes, yes Interpretation Sue There is no with cat
Since there is no rain right now, we can't communicate with the cat.
아주
very
고양이랑
with the cat
with cat
가방이 없으니까
I don't have a bag because I don't have one
Because I don't have a bag
가방이 없으니 불편하구만
The bag is isn't there It's inconvenient
It's inconvenient because I don't have a bag
가져왔다
brought
[음악] [박수]
[Music] [Applause]
가자따라오라고 알았어
Let's go and follow me Okay
Let's go, follow me I got it
어디로 가야 돼
Where Go Go
where should i go
뭐라는 거야모르겠어 뭔 말인지
what I don't know what you mean
I don't know what you're talking about
고양이 너무 귀엽다 그렇지 뒤에 작은거
cat too cute right behind small huge
The cat is so cute right? The small one at the back
뭔가 불긴한데 느낌이[음악]
Something It's kind of bad feeling [Music]
There's something sinister about it [Music]
어 뭐야 최고부한 등급이 왜 갇혀있는 거야 혼자서 어
uh what highest level rating why trapped is alone uh
Uh what, why is the highest rank being locked up alone?
[음악]이럴 순 없는 거야
[Music] Damn net no go
[Music] It can't be like this
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아 여기 좀 빡셀 것 같다 그치선택지 나와라 버리고 갈라는 그런
ah here kinda paksel seems like  That's the choice Come out throw away gala that
Oh, I think it's going to be a little tough here, but the choice is to come out and leave
갈래 이런 느낌으로 바로 버리고살려야겠지
I want to go like this [With the feeling of W2@@ right away I should throw away
I want to go, I should just throw it away and live with this feeling
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
더
more
줄까 안 도와줄 것 같은데 어서 갔다와 시간이 없어 이럴 것 같은데 같이
should not help would looks like Come on went out of time no IMHO would be looks like looks like
I don't think they'll help me, but I'm afraid I'm running out of time.
가나요리
Kana Cuisine
Ghanaian cuisine
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
야 너 그냥 여기 가만히 있어 답답해어 나였으면 지금 아래로 그냥
hey you just here stay still here I'm frustrated If it were me now down just
Hey, you just stay here, it's frustrating. If it were me, just go down now
지나갔다[음악]
Passed [Music]
gone [music]
가만히
Stay still
Still
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
타이밍 마스터 다시 넘어가는 건가보네
Timing Master Again Going Over Guess
I guess I'm passing the timing master again.
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]아
[MUSIC] Ah
찜구이 될 뻔했네 아주
Steamed meat would be It was obvious very
It almost became steamed
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
넘어갈걸
will pass
한번 대기[음악]
Once Wait [Music]
Wait Once [Music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
와
and
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
어떻게 챙기지 잽싸게 챙기고 뛰어야되나
How to take care quickly take care Should I run
How do I get it? Should I get it quickly and run?
어 몰라 그냥 바로
uh I don't know just just
I don't know, just right
야 이거잔인한 거 아니냐 어
hey this is cruel that isn’t it uh
Hey, isn’t this cruel?
고양이 어떻게 이렇게[음악]
Cat How Like [Music]
How Cats Like This [Music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
오케이 오케이
ok ok
okay okay
오케이
ok
okay
왔다
is here
come
언니도 움직일 수 있으면 빨리빨리움직이란 말이야
Unnie can move can  move quickly [ W5@@ I mean
If unnie can move too, then move quickly.
맨날놔두면 움직인다니까
If you leave it on all the time It's moving
If you leave it alone every day, it will move
어 다시
uh again
뺏지 생김 아 나이스 또다시 연구실에컴퓨터 시스템에 같이 느낌이었어
take away is born ah nice again Computer in the lab in the system like felt like
I felt like I was on a computer system in a lab again.
철저히 고독하게 너가 내가내게 내가 너한테 돌아오던 애
thoroughly alone you me me to you coming back kid
Thoroughly lonely, you, me, me, I, the child who came back to you
믿겨지지가 너 좋은 친구야
I can't believe it you good my friend
I can't believe you are a good friend
함께 할 수 있어서 기쁘네 하지만아직 안전한 상태 아니야
with with with with glad but yet secure status not
I'm glad we can be together, but it's not safe yet
빨리 들어와야
quickly must come in
come in soon
들어와
come in
쟤 왜 안 들어옴
That Why Not Enter
why isn't he coming
너 렉 걸렸냐뭐 해
You Lek Did you get caught Do
did you have lag what are you doing
아 된다 아이로봇 갑자기 뭐야 어
Ah becomes iRobot Suddenly What is uh
Ah, iRobot, what is it all of a sudden?
트로이목마 걸렸나
Trojan Horse Caught
Got a trojan horse
깜짝 놀랐네
Surprised Surprised
I was surprised
정신 차리라고 빨리 해 뭐 하는데얘기를 좀 해봐봐 뭐
spirit get it done quickly do it what Talk about it a little bit try what
Come to your senses, do it quickly. What are you doing? Talk to me.
나 유리창 깨려고 위에
me glass window to break on top of
I'm on top trying to break the window
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
야 이거는 진짜 나한테 평생 뭐은혜를 갚아야겠는데 클레멘타인은
hey this is for real to me forever What grace I have to pay it back Clementine
Hey, I really have to repay the favor for my whole life, but Clementine
이 정도면저 센티넬이 또다시 길을 막고 있어요
this this sentinel again way [ Block W5@@ [There is W6@@
At this rate, the Sentinel is blocking the road again.
이래서는 금방 들켜버릴 거야너가 감방으로
this is soon will be caught you are to the cell
If you do this, you will be caught soon. You go to the cell.
녀석들 유인한 다음에 가두는 거 같아
Guys Yoo-in Next Confinement Things I think
It's like luring them in and then locking them up
나
or
me
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
저기 바닥에 있는 저 남자 보여재부팅 당한 로봇이야 난 기억을 잃고
there there there there man Reboot Got I'm a robot I'm remember lost
I see that guy on the floor over there. He's a rebooted robot. I lost my memory.
싶지 않아 너무 무서워
don't want don't too scared
I don't want to, I'm so scared
유인한 다음에 여기 뭐 해야 된다는거 같은데
yin then here what should Being able to do it [It looks like W6@@
I think I need to do something here after luring it out.
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
이 회복센터는 나에게 가장 큰 도움이되었어 마음이 맑아지고 깨끗해졌어
this recovery center to me the most big It was helpful My heart became clearer became clearer
This recovery center has helped me the most. My mind is clear and clear.
나는 이제 뭐 음식입니다
I am now what is food
What food am I now
여기 가둬야 되나 보다지내가 못 먼저 사용하기
here must be locked up can be I can't see can't First [Using W6@@
Should I keep it here, but I can't use it first
와 개빡세다 아 유인 먼저 했어야됐나 아 생각보다 얘 못 들어이 양반
and It's tough Ah Yooin first Should have done it Ah I thought hey couldn't heard this Man
Wow, he's tough. Ah, should I have done Yoo-in first?
못 들어오네
couldn't came in
I can't come in
나이스
Nice
nice
여러분
everyone
메모리다 어 마지막 외모리 같은데그러면
is memory uh last looks like is the same then
It's a memory, it looks like the last one, then
맞지 일반 메모리는 이게 끝이야그러면
That's right normal memory is this is is the end then
That's right, this is the end of normal memory. Then
엔딩 다가가나 보네이 불쌍한 녀석 센티넬은 저항하는
Ending Coming to Bonay Poor guy Sentinel is resistant
The ending is approaching, but the poor fellow Sentinel is resisting
자에게 무자비한 거 같아
ruthless that like
You seem ruthless to me
내가 염려하는 대로네 그들은이 녀석을완전히 삭제했어 더 이상 감정도
i care yes they have guys totally deleted more more empathy
As far as I'm concerned, they deleted this guy completely. No more emotions.
자각도 추억도 없어그러네 절대 잡히면 안 돼
Awareness Memories I don't have Never If I get caught not can
I have neither awareness nor memory.
아98%의 남자
Ah 98% man
Ah 98% of men
이봐 나를 곤란하게 하지마 이제758년 밖에 남지 않았단 말이야 그
Hey Me Embarrass Don't do it Now 758 years only left didn't do it  that
Hey don't bother me I only have 758 years left
외에는 자유라고
[@@W0 other than W0@@] free
free except
758년이래 758
Since 758 758
여기가 닫아야겠는데
This is I need to close it
this should be closed
아 근데 쟤가 문제네 쟤도 데려와야되는데
Ah But He's That's a problem He's I have to bring it, but
Ah, but he's a problem. I have to bring him too.
아 이러면은
Ah This is
Oh if this
빨리 와 빨리
quickly and quickly
come quickly
또 내가 해야 돼길 뭐야 이거
again I should hopefully what this
What else do I have to do
어 뭔가 나갈 수 있을 것 같은느낌이 들어 이제
uh something go out be be be feels like heard now
Uh, I feel like something could come out now
여기에서 나갈 수 있는 유일한출구라고 저쪽 재현실에서 낼 수 있을
here out out in only exit over there in the replay room be be be
The only way out of here is to come out in the reenactment room over there.
것 같아제어실에 접근할 수 있는 방법을
Control Room Access   method
Looks like a way to access the control room
찾아야 해둘러보자
Find Let's try
Let's find out
여기스위치 있네
Switch here there
there is a switch here
인물이야
person
It's a person
그래
yes
okay
찾아보자는 뭐야 너가 하라는 거지 어나보고 하라는 거잖아
Let's find What is You say  beggar Look at it say that's it
What are you trying to find? You're telling me to do it.
나 열쇠
or key
my key
운이 좋았어 문에 키가 꽂혀있네그러기에 올라타
lucky good at the door keys are are plugged in so Get on
You're lucky, the key is stuck in the door, so get on
넘어서 이제 접근할 수 있을 거래뒤에 올라
beyond now reach be be After the transaction go up
Go beyond and climb behind the deals you can now access
가자
let's go
어느 정도 똑바로 안 해 어
which about straight not do uh
I don't do it right to some extent
똑바로 하란 말이야 운전
Straight Haran I mean Driving
I mean drive straight
[음악]야 차 타고 빨리 튀자
[Music] Hey Car Ride Quickly Let's jump
[Music] Hey, let's jump in the car and bounce
[박수]빨리 나가자
[Applause] Quickly Let's go
[Applause] Let's get out of there.
친구야야
It's my friend
hey friend
친구야이거
This is my friend
this is my friend
친구야야
It's my friend
hey friend
너 나 잊었냐친구야
You Me Forgot my friend
did you forget me my friend
와 이거는 뒤도 안 돌아보고 가는 거봐봐 개싸가지 없는 거 봐봐
and this is and not not look back go look at that shit @@W8 without] look look
Wow, look at this one without looking back
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
치사했겠다고클레멘타인
Clementine
I'll kill you, Clementine
[음악]그걸 쫓아오다가 다른 애들
[Music] That Chase Another kids
[Music] The other kids chasing it
30초에
@@W0 at 30 seconds]
in 30 seconds
하고 있네
and there
are doing
뭐 하는 거야 왜 아마 우리둘 다 센트를 감시망을 빠져나갈 순
what do do why maybe the two of us Da Cents Watch Get Out Net
What are you doing Why can't we both get cents off guard
없어 내가 녀석들의 주의를 끌 테니너 이틀면 넌 도망가
no I guys pay attention turn off Tenner Two days you run away
No, I'll get them attention. You'll run away in two days.
아웃사이더 선언문에는 우리는 어떤대가를 치르더라도 아웃사이드로도 가야
Outsider Manifesto We are At any price At any cost Outside Gaya
The Outsider Manifesto says we must go outside at all costs.
한다고라고 써 있어
say write there
It says do
넌 이제 우리 중 하나가 됐어 모두가아웃사이더로 가야 하는 것은 아니야
you now us of one of Okay Everyone is an outsider should go is is no
You're one of us now, not everyone has to go outsider
하지만 오리 중에 하나는 가야 해지하철
but duck one one go Cancellation subway
But one of the ducks has to go
빨리가 너에 대한 기록을 내 램에저장할게 작은 아웃사이더
go fast you  record my I'll save it to RAM Small Outsider
Hurry up, I'll save a record about you in my RAM, little outsider
지금 충분히 같이 갔겠다 어솔직히 인정 이거 문 닫고 갔으면
now enough as I should have gone to be honest acknowledge this door close go
I think we went together enough right now. Admit it honestly.
충분히 갔을듯 어떻게 들어가응
Enough must have gone How did you go in
How did you get in?
인간형 센트를 온다고 하더라도 걸릴것 같은데
humanoid cents coming would take would take Looks like
I think it will take even if you come with a humanoid cent.
괜히 혼자 감동 드라마 찍고 있네바로 아래 있구만 게다가
I don't care alone touching drama filming is there Immediately [under W6@@ is there plus
I'm filming an impressive drama by myself for no reason. You're right below me.
여기다
here
It's here
네코
Neko
코퍼레이션[음악]
Corporation [Music]
와우 이제 열쇠 꽃게 먹으면 되나지금 5시간 반째 하고 있어요 5시간
Wow Now Key Crab Eating Now 5 hours half time and I have 5 hours
Wow now I can eat the key crab I've been doing it for 5 and a half hours now 5 hours
반유튜브에 보면 대부분 한 3시간
half on YouTube watch mostly one 3 hours
If you look at anti-YouTube, most of them are about 3 hours
떼던데 역시편집을 야물딱지게 하셨고만들 응
I heard that also edited wild bugs and made yes
I heard you took it off, but you made the editing hard and you make it.
나도 좀 빨리 끼려면 빨리 깰 수있는데 그 도전과제나 이런 것들 좀
Me too A little bit quickly  quickly Wake up you can that challenges or like this things kinda
If I want to get into it quickly, I can wake up quickly, but the challenges and things like that
찾느라고 좀 걸린 거 같아 그렇지솔직히 말해서
looking for kinda stuck almost looks like That's right, honestly I mean
I guess it took me a while to find it, to be honest
[음악]딱히 막히는 부분은 그렇게 많지는
[Music] Not really blocked part is like that not much
[Music] There aren't that many things that really get stuck
않았어
didn't
did not
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
그래도 98%의 남자가 되잖아
but 98% man that's
You still become 98% of men
분위기가
mood
atmosphere
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
안녕 얘들아안녕하세요 뭘 도와드릴까요
Hello Hello guys What Can I help you
hello guys hello how can i help you
헬퍼477
helper477
helper 477
얘네들은설마 인간에 쓰는 로봇
these guys can't believe humans writing robots
These guys are robots for humans
이름이 따로 정해져 있지 않네 뭐지
name is separately is decided is is not What is it
There is no specific name. What is it?
성벽도시 99의 주민님 안녕하세요맞지 얘네들은 각자 이름들이 없다
Walled City 99's residents Hello, that's right these guys are each names no
Hello residents of Walled City 99, that's right, these guys don't have names.
청소만 하고 있어 지금청소를 위한 로봇인가 봐
cleaning only and and cleaning now for Is it a robot look
I'm only cleaning. I guess I'm a robot for cleaning now.
이 구역의 페인트칠하는 중입니다암말은 페인트를 조심하세요
this [@@W1 in the W1@@ section] painting the mare is painting be careful
This area is being painted. Mares be careful with the paint
뭔가 깔끔해요
Something It's neat
something neat
성벽도시 99회 주민님 안녕하세요이모는 표면으로 통하면 현재 격리
Walled City Episode 99 Residents Hello Aunt to the surface through current isolation
Hello residents of the 99th Walled City, my aunt is currently quarantined if it goes through the surface
절차로 인해 잠겨 있습니다[음악]
procedure due locked are [music]
Locked out due to procedure [music]
제어실에 있는 공인 엔지니어에게물어봐 주세요
@@W0 in control room] [@@W1 in W1@@] Authorized Ask Engineer Please
Ask the certified engineer in the control room
안녕하세요 뭘 도와드릴까요청소 열심히 해 인마 어 미끄러지게
Hello What Can I help you clean Work hard Do dude uh slide
Hello, what can I help you with?
안녕하세요 현재 창문 청소 중입니다
Hello Currently Windows Cleaning busy
Hello, I am currently cleaning the windows.
제어실로 가야 되는데
to the control room to go to go
I have to go to the control room.
안전을 위해 도시를 봉쇄했습니다그래 엔지니어에게 갈게
to safety to to Locked down yes to Engineers I'll go
I've sealed the city for safety. Okay, I'll go to the engineer.
컨트롤룸 여기 같은데
control room here looks like
The control room looks like this
이거는 뭐 어떻게 하지
this is what how not
what do you do with this
뭔가를 해야 될 것 같은데
something should be would be would be would be
i think i have to do something
인간만 들어갈 권한이 있대[음악]
only humans enter permission has [Music]
They say only humans have the right to enter [Music]
힘을 합치면 통을 열 수 있을 거예요
force sum trough heat count There will be will be
Together, we can open the barrel.
인간으로 보이기 어떻게 만들지인간으로 보이게 해야 되나
as human visible how to as human visible should be [would be W6@@
How to make it look human How to make it look human
어 너 일로 와봐
uh you work come
come to your work
생각해 보니까 내가 그거잖아꼬물이잖아 꼬물이
Think See Me That's it
Come to think of it, I'm that one.
맞지 내가물렁이잖아 어
That's right I'm soft uh
That's right, I'm soft
뭐야
What is
what
또 뭐가 필요하나 보네
again what need see
I see what else you need
이제 뭐 할 수 있나 지금 만들 것같지 않아
now what do be be now make don't think don't
What can I do now I don't think I'll make it now
그냥각자 뭐 하는 거였구나
Just each one What doing was it
What were each of you doing?
그렇지 이게 정답이지
right this is is the correct answer
yes this is the correct answer
여긴 전체 도시에 제어실이야 여기에서모든 것을 통제했어 그리고 이제는
this is all city this is the control room all @@W4 here] [ W5@@ controlled and now
This is the control room for the whole city, I controlled everything from here and now
아무것도 없어 아무것도 없어내가 그들을 증오했던게 기억이 나
nothing nothing nothing nothing I them What I hated I don't remember me
Nothing, nothing, I remember I hated them
그들은 모든 것을 가졌거든 깨끗한공간 무한한 힘 이동의 차예요 하지만
they have all things they have cleanspace infinite power move car but
They've got it all, clean space, infinite power movement car, but
그들은 그런 걸 제대로 쓰지 못했어전염병 지금 기억났어
they that that properly  can't I did the plague now I remembered
They didn't use it properly. Epidemic. I remembered now.
모두 죽어가고 있었지만 그들은자신들만 생각했어 아무것도 도와주지
everyone dying but they only thought [ W5@@ nothing help
Everyone was dying, but they only thought of themselves. Nothing helps.
않았지 내 가족들이 눈앞에서 죽어가는걸 봤어 무력감을 느꼈지 가족들을
didn't my my family in front of my eyes dying [ W5@@ saw felt helpless felt family
I saw my family dying in front of my eyes. I felt helpless.
위해 할 수 있는게 아무것도 없었거든
to to to to nothing to There
there was nothing I could do for
하지만 나는 지금 너를 도울 수 있고함께 아웃사이드에 나갈 수 있지
but I now you help be with outside out out out
But I can help you now and we can go outside together
인류야 내가 사랑했던 사람들의 추억을간직하겠어
Mankind I I loved people I will keep the memories
Humanity, I will keep the memories of the people I loved
오 진짜 어 92%의 남자 뭐야 어98% 아니네
oh real uh 92% man What is it uh 98% it's not
Oh really uh 92% of men what is uh 98% not
아 뭐 수치로 따지면 그럴 수 있지92%가
ah what numerically  that Can there's 92%
Ah well, in terms of numbers, it can be 92%
이게 바로 메인 컴퓨터야
This is is Main Computer
this is my main computer
메인 프레임에 따르면 몇 년 동안여기 아무도 없었어 오래전부터
Main Frames According Few Years While here no one didn't exist a long time ago
According to the mainframe, no one has been here for years. It's been a while.
도시 전체가 록다운 사이클에 갇혀있어 이걸 비활성화하면 우리도 나갈
City Entire Lockdown  Stuck [ W5@@ this disable us get out
The whole city is stuck in a lockdown cycle, disable it and we'll get out too.
수 있을 거야이 시스템에 나머지 부분을 온라인
be be be be rest part online
You'll be able to online the rest of this system
상태로 전환해야 해우리에게 필요한 데이터는이 컴퓨터
state needs to switch to needs needs data has computer
The data we need is this computer
안에
in
너가 전원을 켜는 동안 나는 시스템접속 비밀번호 암호화된 키를 찾을게
you turn turn while I System access password encrypted key will find
While you turn on the power, I will find the system access password encryption key
마음이다
is the heart
it's heart
자 뭐 어떻게 할까 말만 해
now what how should just say do
Now, just tell me what to do
아이가 다 키는 거네맞지
child everything height is that's right
The child is all growing up, right?
일부러 이렇게 한 번에 지나가면서키려고 세팅한 거예요
on purpose like this one at once passing by [ W5@@ set [It's W6@@
I deliberately set it up to turn it on while passing by at once like this.
나의 큰 그림이지
My Big Pictures
my big picture
성공해서 정말 잘했어 친구 찾았다도시를 여는 방법 알아냈어 여기에
Success Really Nice job Friends Found the city [ W5@@ opening how to figured it out here
I'm so glad I succeeded I found a friend I figured out how to open a city here
뭔가 문제가 있나 본데뭐 오해할
Something Problem Got What Misunderstanding
I saw that there was something wrong.
방법이 있을 거야
way way way
there must be a way
[음악]로프
[MUSIC]Rope
[music] rope
컨트롤
Control
control
저게 도시를 여는 워크스테이션이야보안 레이어가 있어서 사용할 수 없네
That's City Opening Workstation Security Layers available available available available
That's a workstation that opens the city. It has a security layer, so I can't use it.
우리가 제일 잘하는 걸 해보자 난기기를 해킹하고 넌 파괴하는 거야
we are is the best is good at girl let's try Hack You Destroy You
Let's do what we do best, hack the rig and you destroy it
그래 자머파기 할까 어떤 거 부셔줄까요
Yes Jammer Should I What Something Shall I break it down
Shall I break it? Shall I break something?
이거구만다 부쳐줄게
That's all I'll send it to you
I'll send you all this
자 하나 했어자 그 다음에 또 어디
one one one that then again where
Now, let's do one thing. Then, where else?
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아 해킹도 이거 다해주는 건가 보네
Oh Hacking This Do it Is that Bone
Ah, it seems that hacking can do this too.
어뭐야 뭐지
What is What is
what is what
탱고
Tango
tango
아 이거 그냥스토리인가 보네 맞지
Ah Is this Is this just a story I see Right
Ah, I guess this is just a story, right?
스토리인 거 같아
is the story is is like
I think it's a story
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
아치 자 마지막 저거 아까 했는데 안했던 거 이거 여기서 또 해킹해야 돼
arch now last that earlier  didn't do it that this here again [ W11@@ must be hacked must be hacked
Arch, I did that last one earlier, but I didn’t. I have to hack this again here.
어 여기 해킹하는 거 없나 하나남았는데 여기였지
uh here hacking that is there There was one left It was here
Hey, is there any hacking here? There is one left, but it was here
[음악]뭔가 느려졌어
[MUSIC] Something slow
[MUSIC] Something slowed down
얘 터지는 거 아니야[음악]
dude popping stuff no [music]
He's not exploding [Music]
아 또 시작됐네 아픈 척하려고 어동체가 망가진 거 같아
ah again started sick trying to pretend The body is is broken is like looks like
Ah, it started again, I think I broke my body to pretend to be sick
난 괜찮을 거야 그냥 워크스테이션으로데려다줘 저 경보는 끌 수 있어
I am will be fine will be just take me to the workstation [ W5@@ that alarm off can got
I'll be fine. Just take me to the workstation. I can turn that alarm off.
또 개꿀 빨라
again sweet fast
It's quick again
됐어 이제
OK now
okay now
저기 할 말이 있어 하지만 하지만이쓰레기 같은 놈아 할 수 있어
there do say there but but This crap like nigga do be have
There's something to say, but, but you trash man, you can do it.
조금만 더 힘내 너 어차피 그냥배터리 빼고 내가 데려다줄게
A little bit more cheer up you anyway just Battery [Except W6@@ I I'll take you there
Cheer up a little bit more, anyway, just remove the battery and I'll take you there
충전기만 넣으면 되겠구먼 어
charger only [Put in W1@@ I guess uh
I just need to put in the charger.
도시의 중앙제어 시스템 무너뜨리려면굉장히 많은 전력이 필요하다는 것을
city central control system very much to break a lot power need that
We know that it takes a lot of power to bring down the city's central control system.
알고 있었어이 드론 동체가 버틸 수있는 것 이상으로 말이에요 이제
knew had this drone fuselage hold out Can would be more than mean now
I knew more than this drone fuselage could hold out now.
보안이 비활성화 되어 있으니 내가시스템을 제어하고 도시를 개방할 수
security is is disabled is is is the system control city open
Security is disabled, so I can't control the system and open the city.
있어 이걸덮었으면 내 소프트웨어가 파괴될 수
has if this is covered my software is will be destroyed [ W5@@ number
Covering this could destroy my software.
있어 하지만 처음 컴퓨터에 연결했을때 나는 그 선택을 했어 그리고 지금
has but first time to computer connected I did that chose did and now
Yes but I made that choice when I first connected it to my computer and now
이게 그 결과예요아웃사이드를 함께 보진 못하겠네
this is that results outside with bojin [ W5@@ I can't do it
This is the result. We can't see the outside together.
미안해 나는 인류의 기억을 이어가야한다고 생각했어 과거를 붙들고 있어야
I'm sorry I'm humanity remember I have to continue I thought the past hold onto should be
I'm sorry, I thought I had to carry on the memories of mankind, I had to hold onto the past
한다고 하지만 이제캠페니언들에게서 미래가 보여요 그리고
says but now from the campaigners the future I can see and
But now I see the future from the campaigners and
너에게서도 자 이걸 떼어줄게
You too Now This I'll take it off
Come on, I'll take this off of you too.
넌 내가 그리던 최고의 친구였어고마워
You I I was drawing The best Thank you for being my friend
You were the best friend I've ever been, thank you
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
안 돼[음악]
no no [music]
no [music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
진짜 세상을 구해냈구먼 고양이야 나뒤져라이
Really The world You saved it It's a cat Go after me
You saved the real world, you cat, go after me
저기 뭐야[음악]
over there what [Music]
what's there [music]
얘네들 얼마나 놀았을까 결국 내가해낸 거잖아 고양이가
These guys How much Did you play In the end I made it that's it the cat
How long did they play? In the end, I did it, the cat
세상에 고양이가드디어 해냈다네 이거 말도 안 돼
Oh my God Catguard finally I did it this words not can
Oh my god, the cat finally did it, this is unbelievable
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
뭐센티넬들
What sentinels
what the sentinels
클레멘타인도 결국 살았네
Clementine Finally I'm alive
Clementine is still alive
[음악]
[Music]
[music]
데려가는 거 아니야
I'm not taking you
내가 여기서 개고생을 했다네믿기지가
I can't believe I went through hardship here
한 6시간 동안
for 6 hours
미리 어디로 가야 되지나가는 건가
Where can I go in advance?
아니 그러니까고양이도 가차없이 그냥 저거 어떻게
No, even the cat is relentless, just how
해서 일단 살릴지도 모르는 건데 그냥버리고 가는 거 봐봐 어
So I might be able to save it, but watch him just throw it away
역시 고양이들은
Also cats
강아지였으면 좀 더 들고 갔다 진짜
If it was a puppy, I would have taken it a little longer.
비둘기들
pigeons
오랜만에 본다
long time no see
친구는 만났으려나 이제 만나려나
Do you want to meet your friends? Do you want to meet them now?
[음악]
[music]
마지막에 저거 뭐야뭘 알려주려고 했던 걸까
What was that at the end, what was it trying to tell you?
장장[음악]
long [music]
5시간50분 만에
in 5 hours 50 minutes
클리어 했습니다스트레이
Cleared Stray
아주 괜찮은 고양이 게임이었고도전과제랑 막 뱃지 못느라고
It was a very good cat game and I just couldn't get the achievements and badges.
개고생했는데
I had a hard time
일단 아쉬운 점은 열심히 해서 뺏지모았더니 마지막에는 맨몸으로
First of all, the regrettable thing was that I worked hard to collect it, and in the end, I was naked
나간다는게플레이어들에게 이게
Going out tells the players this
맞네
That's right
이게 무슨 헛짓거리였는지개같이 뭐하던데 맨몸으로 나가면
What kind of nonsense was this?
의미가 있나요 자 그래도 92%
Does it have any meaning, but still 92%
메모리 먹느라고 열심히 했습니다오케이 다들 고생 많으셨고 여기서
I worked hard to eat memory. Okay, everyone worked hard, and here
마무리할게요 좋아요
I'll finish it. Okay
[음악]
[music]